<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11517644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckae144.1374</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckae144.1374</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Poster Displays</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>DF. Poster display: Climate change / Urban health</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Climate Change, Air Pollution, African Dust Impacts on Public Health and Sustainability in Europe</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Adamopoulos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Environmental Hygiene and Public Health Inspections, Hellenic Republic, Region of Attica</institution>, Athens, <country country="GR">Greece</country></aff><xref rid="ckae144.1374-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--adamopoul@gmail.com--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Syrou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Physical Education and Sport Science, University of Thessaly</institution>, Trikala, <country country="GR">Greece</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckae144.1374-cor1">Contact: <email>adamopoul@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-10-28"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><issue-title>17th European Public Health Conference 2024 Sailing the Waves of European Public Health: Exploring a Sea of Innovation Lisbon, Portugal 12&#x02013;15 November 2024</issue-title><elocation-id>ckae144.1374</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ckae144.1374.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s4855"><title>&#x02002;</title><p>Climate change poses a significant threat to environmental sustainability and public health, leading to extreme weather events, rising sea levels, and biodiversity loss. Research on air pollution from African dust adversely associated with climate change highlights its significant role in trapping heat in the atmosphere and causing heat-related illnesses, cardiovascular disorders, and respiratory ailments. Smog, dust, acid rain, and ozone depletion also negatively impact ecosystems. The methods of the study also include the dynamics of climate change-induced air pollution. The implications for public health and environmental sustainability through GWR modeling and MODIS-NDVI analysis of controlling air pollution are crucial for reducing the climate crisis, safeguarding public health, and maintaining ecosystem sustainability. Results from particulate matter (PM 2.5-10), which consists of tiny particles with varying diameters, can enter the respiratory system through inhalation. This can lead to a diameter of less than 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m (PM 2.5-10). According to the relevant legislation, the limit value refers to the daily average value and must not exceed 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/m3. While ozone in the stratosphere serves a protective function against ultraviolet radiation, excessive levels at ground level can be harmful and have been recorded in atmospheric samples ranging from 146.6&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/m3 up to 702.3&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/m3. impacting the respiratory and cardiovascular systems. Policy leaders, businesses, and individuals need to be proactive in reducing air pollution, adopting clean energy technology, and implementing stricter pollution rules. Stricter pollution rules, environmentally friendly transportation choices, and the adoption of clean energy technology. The sustainability of the ecosystem and public health are significantly impacted by climate change linked to air pollution. To solve these global problems and move toward a healthier, cleaner future for future generations, we must act now on climate justice.</p></sec><sec id="s4856"><title>Key messages</title><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Examine the impact of African dust air pollution on public health and its significant impacts from climate change, provide solutions to mitigate its effects on environmental sustainability in Europe.</p><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Public health workers, Policymakers and stakeholders must prioritize reducing emissions and enforcing strict air quality laws to mitigate the negative impact of African dust on European populations.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>