<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="EN" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ACS//DTD ACS Journal DTD v1.02 20061031//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ACSJournal-v102.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.02?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName acs2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Sci Technol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ Sci Technol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">es</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">esthag</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Science &#x00026; Technology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0013-936X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1520-5851</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11137869</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38752553</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.3c10711</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Policy Analysis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Socio-environmental
Opportunities for Organic Material
Management in California&#x02019;s Sustainability Transition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath1"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6200-2883</contrib-id><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Anaya L.</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Ponomareva</surname><given-names>Aleksandra I.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Torn</surname><given-names>Margaret S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>Matthew D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Energy
&#x00026; Resources Group <institution>University of California&#x02014;Berkeley</institution> 345 Giannini Hall Berkeley, California 94720, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Climate
and Ecosystem Sciences Division <institution>Lawrence
Berkeley National Laboratory</institution> Berkeley, California 94720, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Department
of Environmental Science, Policy, and Management <institution>University of California&#x02014;Berkeley</institution> 130 Mulford Hall Berkeley, California 94720, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>&#x02225;</label><institution>Carbon
Direct, Incorporated</institution> 17 State Street New York, New York 10004, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>anayahall@berkeley.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>28</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>58</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>9031</fpage><lpage>9039</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Permits the broadest form of re-use including for commercial purposes, provided that author attribution and integrity are maintained (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="es3c10711_0005" id="ab-tgr1"/></p><p>Contemporary resource management is doubly burdened by
high rates
of organic material disposal in landfills, generating potent greenhouse
gases (GHG), and globally degraded soils, which threaten future food
security. Expansion of composting can provide a resilient alternative,
by avoiding landfill GHG emissions, returning valuable nutrients to
the soil to ensure continued agricultural production, and sequestering
carbon while supporting local communities. Recognizing this opportunity,
California has set ambitious organics diversion targets in the Short-Lived
Climate Pollutant Law (SB1383) which will require significant increases
(5 to 8 million tonnes per year) in organic material processing capacity.
This paper develops a spatial optimization model to consider how to
handle this flow of additional material while achieving myriad social
and ecological benefits through compost production. We consider community-based
and on-farm facilities alongside centralized, large-scale infrastructure
to explore decentralized and diversified alternative futures of composting
infrastructure in the state of California. We find using a diversity
of facilities would provide opportunity for cost savings while achieving
significant emissions reductions of approximately 3.4 &#x000b1; 1 MMT
CO<sub>2</sub>e and demonstrate that it is possible to incorporate
community protection into compost infrastructure planning while meeting
economic and environmental objectives.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="short"><p>This policy
analysis provides a framework and methodology
for policymakers and stakeholders to incorporate environmental, economic,
and social objectives into compost facility planning to support broader
organic waste and climate change mitigation goals.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>carbon sequestration</kwd><kwd>climate change mitigation</kwd><kwd>environmental justice</kwd><kwd>food waste</kwd><kwd>organics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Science Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000160</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>1739676</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>California Strategic Growth Council</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100022421</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>es3c10711</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>es3c10711</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Increasing the use of
composting is frequently touted as an opportunity
to simultaneously divert organic materials from landfills, where they
produce high quantities of methane, and to sequester carbon (C) in
degraded soils, offering a double win for climate change mitigation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> To help ensure a just sustainable transition, composting also offers
an opportunity to unite climate change mitigation and landscape restoration
goals with broader social justice objectives.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> In
this paper, we evaluate overlapping economic and socio-environmental
goals associated with developing new composting infrastructure in
the state of California.</p><p>California has implemented a suite
of programs and policies to
tackle landfill emissions, the source of 20% of the state&#x02019;s
anthropogenic methane emissions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></sup> The most
comprehensive piece of legislation is Senate Bill 1383, passed in
2016, (Short-lived Climate Pollutants (SLCP): Organic Waste Reductions;
Lara, Chapter 395), which sets bold goals for landfill methane reduction,
including a 75% reduction in the statewide disposal of organic waste
from the 2014 level by 2025.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup> Much of this
material is expected to be composted, but at present there is not
enough capacity to handle all of this diverted organic waste. A key
objective of this bill is to prompt a paradigm shift in how waste
is managed in California, creating a circular system in which food
scraps and organic materials are recovered and repurposed, rather
than a linear system in which they are landfill-bound. This transformation
requires new infrastructure and significant changes in the management
of organic materials, including how they are used, collected, processed,
and redistributed.</p><p>California is increasingly looking to its
working lands (grazed
grasslands and cultivated croplands) for climate mitigation and biodiversity
enhancement. As part of its Natural and Working Land Climate Smart
Strategy and the Healthy Soils Program, the state has set clear goals
around increasing carbon (C) storage and improving soil health through
compost application.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> Once land applied, compost, the
product of controlled aerobic microbial decomposition, promotes C
sequestration in soil by stimulating microorganism activity and increasing
the soil&#x02019;s photosynthetically derived C biomass.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> Compost can increase water retention and nutrient availability,
and can displace the use of traditional fertilizers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> California has over 24 million acres of rangelands and
cultivated cropland which make up nearly a fifth of the State&#x02019;s
land area&#x02014;they provide a significant compost application opportunity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup></p><p>Enhancing the role of compost in California&#x02019;s waste
management
paradigm also offers an opportunity to incorporate considerations
of environmental and economic justice into the state&#x02019;s sustainability
transition. Traditional waste management has historically burdened
disadvantaged communities with disproportional environmental harms;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> repeated studies have shown waste facilities
tend to be concentrated in areas of relative social deprivation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> Beyond methane emissions reductions, composting
can benefit food security and economic resiliency through local production
of food and expanded employment opportunities, especially when developed
at smaller, community-centered scales.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> Actively considering the social and economic cobenefits of climate
change mitigation policies such as organic waste diversion can offer
benefits to disadvantaged communities in line with California&#x02019;s
codified environmental justice (EJ) principles.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup></p><p>This is the first study that we know of to focus
on the necessary
expansion of composting infrastructure in California and to consider
the diversity of facility types available to meet organics management
capacity needs and social justice goals. Building on field trials
that demonstrate the carbon (C) sequestration potential of a single
application of compost,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> past work has quantified
the potential costs and emissions benefits associated with compost
diversion in California.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> However, these studies focus only on existing conventional,
industrial-scale composting facilities and do not consider the variety
of composting facility types that may be deployed to simultaneously
meet both environmental and social objectives.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup></p><p>To address this knowledge gap, we investigate how
California&#x02019;s
additional composting infrastructure needs can be met under a range
of social, economic, and environmental constraints. We build on past
studies analyzing existing infrastructure using a similar lifecycle
approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> to address
three primary goals: (1) review the variety of composting facility
types and their different technical and economic factors; (2) estimate
the distribution and size of new composting facilities needed to minimize
cost or emissions; and (3) evaluate whether social and environmental
policy objectives can be met by incorporating community and on-farm
composters. Although this analysis centers on California, the results
are intended to provide a framework and methodology for decision-makers
across the country.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This analysis
was completed in three steps. First, we collected
spatially explicit data estimates on available biomass feedstocks
across the state, existing composting capacity, land-use characteristics
for compost application on working lands, and relevant policy considerations
for composting infrastructure development, including air quality and
contemporary pollution burden. Second, we consulted literature and
expert stakeholders to develop a typology of composter facilities,
in which small-scale community-based and on-farm composting were considered
alongside conventional centralized, large-scale infrastructure. This
allowed for a better comparison of trade-offs based on bundled attributes
of each facility type and for appropriate parametrization of our model.
Finally, we constructed a linear optimization model to evaluate these
variables and determine where best to locate new composting facilities
under policy-relevant objectives and constraints.</p><p>We developed
a set of 12 scenarios that minimized either cost or
GHG emissions to robustly assess the impact of incorporating facility
diversity and socio-environmental considerations in new compost infrastructure
development. The results of the model return least-cost supply chains
for compost, including geographically bounded estimates of new build
per facility type (in tonnes), mass and distance of feedstock and
compost moved, net CO<sub>2</sub>e reductions and cost. Modeled scenario
results outline a framework for organic material management that incorporates
the social and ecological objectives of California&#x02019;s climate
change mitigation, working land, and environmental justice planning.</p><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Compost Facility Considerations</title><p>To
achieve its compost-related diversion, soil health, and mitigation
goals, the State of California will need to add 5&#x02013;8 million
tonnes/year of additional compost capacity to handle municipal solid
waste material newly diverted away from landfills.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> The distribution and size of these new facilities will depend on
regional attributes, like land use in the area, feedstock availability,
end-market access, and air quality and community health considerations.
Though it possesses numerous beneficial qualities, compost is an expensive
product to transport, as it is water-rich and heavy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> As a result, the strategic placement of new facilities
such that they are close to feedstock collection points and end uses
is paramount to minimize costs and emissions for the whole system.</p><p>The analysis considered two feedstock source types: the organic
fraction of municipal solid waste (OFMSW, hereafter MSW, consisting
of food scraps and green waste) and agricultural materials (manure
and orchard residue). We focused primarily on MSW in line with SB1383
goals. However, agricultural feedstocks represent an impressive volume
of organic materials in the state and are included in a few scenarios
to assess their potential impact on emission reduction outcomes and
to envision a future where feedstocks are managed holistically across
California.</p><p>We also considered compost facility heterogeneity;
operations range
from small-scale community facilities to on-farm agriculturally based
facilities to large-scale industrial facilities, each associated with
different sizes, costs, land uses, technologies, and community impacts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> For example, diversified and decentralized composting
infrastructure, as opposed to large industrial facilities, has been
shown to reduce transportation cost, provide for greater community-buy
in, and can be more resilient and adaptable to local conditions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup></p><p>Finally, we included air quality and community health considerations
in compost facility development. Regional air quality constraints
may restrict the type of facilities that can be developed in an area&#x02014;air
districts that have already reached maximum capacity for air pollutant
concentrations may not be permitted to build new large industrial
facilities due to the volatile organic compounds they release.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> For the same reason, areas that have been identified
as Disadvantaged Communities (DAC) based on their high CalEnviroScreen
score, which indicates that they already experience a high pollution
burden, may not be able to accommodate a large industrial facility.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> Consideration of environmental justice is critical
as the state expands composting capacity&#x02014;at present, over 35%
of existing composters are in DAC census blocks according to our analysis
of CalRecycle data. By volume, over half of existing capacity is located
in these communities. We investigated how these socio-environmental
constraints can be managed while still meeting state capacity needs.</p><sec id="sec2.1.1"><label>2.1.1</label><title>Facility Typology</title><p><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref> illustrates a general compost
facility typology drawn from expert interviews and literature review.
We highlight several key differentiating factors for facility type
including size, feedstock, end-markets, land use type, and capital
costs. Maximum facility size, feedstocks, and capital costs were all
included in the next step of the analysis, the spatial optimization
model. It is important to note that facilities exhibited important
differences in community benefits, though these are challenging to
quantify and were not directly modeled in this work.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Composting facility typology.
Capacity is measured in tons per
year (TPY) (tonnes). Feedstocks include municipal solid waste (MSW)
and agricultural residue (AG). Capital costs include a per ton estimate
for construction of a new facility&#x02014;land costs and labor are
not included. *Denotes values used in the analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="es3c10711_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>Industrial composters are currently the dominant
model of compost
processing facilities in the state. The average facility processes
60&#x0202f;000 tonnes per year of capacity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> Existing facilities are located throughout the state, with a noticeably
heavy presence in the Central Valley, and near urban centers in Northern
and Southern California (see <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>). They can process most feedstocks (including MSW,
agricultural, and wood) and are associated with high capital costs
and stringent permitting requirements based on throughput and footprint.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Key model
inputs and zones. Black hexagons delineate the zones
used in this analysis. Panel (a) presents organic fraction of municipal
solid waste (MSW) within each zone. Panel (b) shows both the locations
of existing composters and the maximum CalEnviroScreen Environmental
Justice score in each zone. Panel (c) displays the distribution of
end-markets for land application of compost.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="es3c10711_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig><p>On-farm composters are those facilities located
on actively operating
agricultural enterprises. They tend to be smaller in scale, and to
process uncontaminated agricultural residue (like manure, crop, and
orchard residue) as feedstocks, though can accept MSW as well.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> Finally, community composters tend to be associated
with community gardens and operated by nonprofit organizations to
produce soil amendments for local community members. They are the
smallest type of compost facility and often provide a range of social
cobenefits, including added community green space, education opportunities,
local jobs, food security, and embeddedness in communities. Although
community composters produce much less compost than industrial processors
and face unique challenges related to land access, feedstock contamination,
and processing capacity, there is increasing interest in using these
decentralized facilities across the state and beyond as demonstrated
by recently established sources of funding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> We
investigate the technical and economic potential of on-farm and community
composters given their smaller throughput capacity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Siting Model</title><p>Given this facility
typology, a linear programming model was developed to estimate build-out
of compost infrastructure across available facility types and efficiently
allocate newly diverted organic feedstocks from generation through
end-use land application. We developed two functional forms for this
model, one in which the objective is to minimize cost and one in which
the objective is to minimize emissions. This spatially explicit model
was used to evaluate multiple scenarios under a series of physical
and policy-motivated constraints.</p><p>To effectively model the heterogeneity
of resources across California, we regionalized the state into 78
hexagonal zones shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>, which allow for more granularity and consistency
than a county-scaled model. Although the zones are not uniform given
the geography of the state, they reflect realistic waste management
and compost market regions. The use of hexagons aligns our zones with
the scale and radii of average collection and hauling distances for
a robust assessment of transportation logistics and resource distribution.</p><p>Each zone was associated with an array of attributes relevant to
the decision of whether to site a new composting facility: these included
land use, feedstock availability, existing composting infrastructure, end-market access (i.e., cultivated
cropland or rangeland where finished compost can be applied), air
quality indices, and environmental justice scores. The solved results
of the model are the capacities (in tonnes) of each newly built facility
type per zone. More information on model formulation, parameter descriptions
and data sources can be found in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Supporting Information</ext-link> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">SI</ext-link>).</p><p>A set of
scenarios were developed to reflect potential policy objectives,
detailed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>. Business-as-usual (&#x0201c;BAU&#x0201d;) was defined by limiting
potential builds to industrial only, both with and without a maximum
cap allowed per zone. &#x0201c;Baseline&#x0201d; incorporated the additional
facility types of community composters and on-farm composters. The
&#x0201c;Land-use&#x0201d; scenario incentivized community and/or on-farm
facilities to align land use and facility characteristics by limiting
the amount of industrial facilities built in zones where the proportion
of land classified as &#x0201c;developed&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;agricultural&#x0201d;
was above the 60<sup>th</sup> percentile across all zones. Under this
scenario, in those zones, maximum industrial capacity was uniformly
reduced by 75%. Maximum community was increased 100% in urban zones;
on-farm capacity was increased 100% in agricultural zones. The &#x0201c;EJ&#x0201d;
scenario prohibited building industrial facilities in DAC zones, defined
as those with EJ scores above 75%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> Another
scenario (&#x0201c;AQ&#x0201d;) also prohibited industrial facilities
in zones that included any portion of an impacted airshed. These two
constraints were combined in the &#x0201c;EJ &#x00026; AQ&#x0201d; scenario.
A final scenario did not allow industrial facility build in any zone
(&#x0201c;Community &#x00026; On-Farm&#x0201d;).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Scenario Definitions for Each of 24
Scenarios</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">scenario
name</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">feedstock</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">objective</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">constraints</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU No Cap</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost;&#x000a0;emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">only&#x000a0;industrial, no cap on build per zone</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU Cap</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost;&#x000a0;emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">only&#x000a0;industrial, cap on build per zone</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Baseline</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">facility
diversity (all&#x000a0;types&#x000a0;permitted)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Land-use</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">incentives for community
and on-farm by zone land-use</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">no industrial in EJ zones</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">AQ</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">no industrial in AQ zones</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ &#x00026; AQ</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">no
industrial in EJ or AQ
zones</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Comm.&#x000a0;&#x00026;&#x000a0;On&#x000a0;Farm</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">no industrial allowed</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU Cap +</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW + AR</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">both&#x000a0;feedstocks; only industrial</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Baseline +</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW + AR</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">both&#x000a0;feedstocks; facility diversity</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Land-use +</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;AR</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">both&#x000a0;feedstocks; land-use incentives</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ &#x00026; AQ +</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">MSW&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;AR</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">cost; emis.</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">both&#x000a0;feedstocks; no industrial in EJ&#x000a0;&#x00026;&#x000a0;AQ&#x000a0;zones</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>We also evaluated four of these scenarios (&#x0201c;BAU
Cap&#x0201d;,
&#x0201c;Baseline&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Land-use&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;EJ &#x00026;
AQ&#x0201d;) with both the organic fraction of MSW and agricultural
residue, for a total of 12 scenarios, each of which was evaluated
under both cost and emissions minimization objectives. For both objective
functions, the solved model returns the tonnage of new composting-facility
builds of each type per zone, the total cost (USD), total CO<sub>2</sub>e emissions reductions, and the amount and distance (tonne-km) of
organic materials moved in each scenario. Emissions estimates represent
a combination of annual avoided emissions from diverting organic feedstocks
away from landfills, emissions associated with transporting materials
and producing compost, and the county-specific annual net carbon sequestration
benefit from a one-time compost application to crop or rangelands.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> Results present annual values for material handling
and one-time compost application.</p><p>We used the open-source package,
CVXPY to solve the optimization
problem with an academic license of the GUROBI software. This package
is used for a variety of mathematical programming problems, including
linear programming, quadratic programming, and mixed integer linear
programming among others. We rely on their linear programming solutions.
The model is implemented in the Python programming language.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Sensitivity Analysis</title><p>The parameters
used in this model are displayed in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">SI Table S1</ext-link> and are consistent with the existing literature evaluating the techno-economic
potential of compost applications. A parametric sensitivity analysis
was performed to evaluate the impact of five key input uncertainties
on the results through 15 additional scenarios, presented in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Table S3</ext-link> in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">SI</ext-link>.</p><p>Overall costs and emissions are both a function of organic
material flow patterns, feedstock to compost conversion rate, compost
processing emissions, diversion rates, and upfront capital costs for
facility development. First, we evaluated the impact of feedstock
constraints as defined in our typology. In this sensitivity analysis,
on-farm only accepted agricultural residue while community composters
accepted both municipal and agricultural feedstocks. Industrial facilities
always accepted all feedstocks.</p><p>The impact of volumetric conversion
during composting was assessed
at low (50%) and high (150%) levels of the initial parameter. We also
include a higher estimate of the greenhouse gas emissions associated
with producing compost (or processing emissions) drawn from the literature,
as well as lower estimate of on-farm capital cost. Finally, while
the focus of our assessment was on compost, as part of the sensitivity
analysis we include one scenario that alters diversion rates to include
the potential role of anaerobic digestion (AD) in absorbing a portion
(40%) of the diverted organic material as suggested by SB1383.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> This scenario also addresses potential changes
in agricultural feedstock availability due to changing industry dynamics.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Technical Build</title><p>The results for both
cost and emissions objectives demonstrate that incorporating facility
diversity and environmental justice considerations can cost less than
BAU scenarios, on both a per tonne and overall basis, while resulting
in approximately similar levels of emissions reductions (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Tables <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref></xref> and <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">3</xref>). GHG reductions include both the C sequestration benefits
of using compost as a soil amendment and the avoided emissions from
diverting organic waste from landfills with the latter constituting
the bulk of the emissions reductions modeled here. Under a cost minimization
objective there is less new capacity built overall (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), with each MSW scenario just meeting the SB1383 diversion requirements
of 8 MMT of new capacity, leading to fewer opportunities to sequester
carbon with newly processed compost. No on-farm composters were constructed
in these scenarios, likely due to the high up-front capital costs.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Facility
build by composter type for MSW only scenarios. The horizontal
axes denote the scenario and the stacked bars represent new capacity
built in that scenario. Panel (a) shows results for the emissions
minimization runs and panel (b) shows results from the cost minimization
runs. The black line indicates the amount of new composting capacity
necessary to meet SB1383 goals.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="es3c10711_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Facility build by composter type in scenarios that account
for
MSW and agricultural residue. The horizontal axes denote the scenario
and the stacked bars represent new capacity built in that scenario.
Panel (a) shows results for the emissions minimization runs and panel
(b) shows results from the cost minimization runs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="es3c10711_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Cost Minimization Model Results for
Main Scenarios</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">scenario
name</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">GHG reduction (MMT&#x000a0;CO<sub>2</sub>e/yr)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">cost (million&#x000a0;USD)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">USD/tCO<sub>2</sub>e</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">USD/t
of
new capacity</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">mass distance (10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;t-km)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU&#x000a0;No&#x000a0;Cap</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.5585</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1587</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$620.25</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$196.25</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">326</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU Cap</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.6112</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1532</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$586.52</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$189.40</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">100</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Baseline</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.4685</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$906</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$367.16</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$112.08</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">514</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Land-use</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.4489</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$903</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$368.71</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$111.67</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">572</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.4327</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$900</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$369.90</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$111.28</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">634</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">AQ</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.4278</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$898</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$369.76</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$111.02</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">655</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ &#x00026; AQ</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.4281</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$898</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$369.76</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$111.02</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">655</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Comm.&#x000a0;&#x00026;&#x000a0;On&#x000a0;Farm</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">2.4285</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$898</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$369.66</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$111.02</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">655</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU Cap +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">15.8297</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$12&#x0202f;157</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$768.01</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$220.54</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6324</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Baseline +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">16.4445</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$10&#x0202f;965</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$666.76</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$198.90</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4662</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Land-use +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">15.2604</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$12&#x0202f;383</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$811.42</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$224.62</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7855</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ &#x00026; AQ +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">15.3223</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$12&#x0202f;412</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$810.06</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$225.16</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">8006</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Emissions Minimization Model Results
for Main Scenarios</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">scenario
name</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">GHG reduction (MMT&#x000a0;CO<sub>2</sub>e/yr)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">cost (million&#x000a0;USD)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">USD/tCO<sub>2</sub>e</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">USD/t
of
new capacity</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">mass distance (10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;t-km)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU No Cap</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.3824</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$2164</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$639.75</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$200.70</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">587</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU Cap</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.4661</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$2069</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$596.82</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$191.87</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">240</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Baseline</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.4950</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1776</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$508.21</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$164.74</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">112</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Land-use</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.4456</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1896</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$550.38</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$175.89</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">332</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.4606</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1812</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$543.89</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$174.57</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">261</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">AQ</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.4348</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1873</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$545.35</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$173.74</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">373</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ &#x00026; AQ</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.4348</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1906</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$554.76</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$176.74</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">373</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Comm. &#x00026; On Farm</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3.4025</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$1896</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$557.10</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$175.81</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">497</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">BAU Cap +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">19.9981</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$16&#x0202f;692</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$834.69</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$236.59</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">11,791</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Baseline +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">22.0964</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$16&#x0202f;047</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$726.24</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$218.33</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7,827</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Land-use +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">19.3146</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$16&#x0202f;740</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$866.69</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$241.70</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">12&#x0202f;686</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EJ &#x00026; AQ +</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">20.1838</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$18&#x0202f;210</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$902.23</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">$247.76</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">14&#x0202f;652</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>As additional constraints were included in the modeled
scenarios,
emissions reductions decreased slightly, while cost per ton of CO<sub>2</sub>-equivalent avoided also decreased. This result is consistent
across both cost and emissions minimizations objectives and both feedstock
scenarios. Overall cost associated with transporting feedstocks, constructing
facilities, and land-applying compost dropped significantly, even
as the hauling and collecting distance increased. This is especially
pronounced in the MSW feedstock-only runs: BAU costs are about 50%
higher than scenarios that allow diverse facility types to be built.
One unexpected result was that the AQ and EJ &#x00026; AQ scenarios yielded
identical results from the optimization model under the cost minimization
objective. We display both results in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Tables <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref></xref> and <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">3</xref>, but only present
the mapped distribution of new facilities for EJ &#x00026; AQ in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link>.</p><p>In the cost minimization model
runs, on-farm composting facilities
are only built in the scenarios that include both the organic fraction
of MSW and agricultural feedstocks (the scenarios marked with a &#x0201c;+&#x0201d;).
In the emissions minimization runs, this facility type was utilized
even under the MSW scenarios to absorb organic material around major
population centers that are surrounded by agricultural landscapes,
decreasing the transport distance (t-km) that material needed to be
moved.</p><p>Adding agricultural feedstocks into the model considerably
increased
both the cost and the net C sequestration approximately 6-fold due
to the increased volume of organic matter that could be processed
into compost and land applied. Both cost per ton of new capacity and
cost per ton of CO<sub>2</sub>e avoided and sequestered was nearly
doubled in these scenarios. The scenarios that include MSW and agricultural
feedstocks highlight the contribution of large scale, industrial composting
facilities in organic waste management&#x02014;community composters
and on-farm composters alone are not able to handle the volume of
material produced.</p><p>In general, the spatial distribution of new
composters tended to
cluster around the large population areas in the southern coast and
Bay Area (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">SI</ext-link> for maps). Cost minimization
runs restricted to MSW feedstocks privileged community composters,
resulting in a similar spatial arrangement across scenarios as constraints
are added to the baseline runs (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link>). Under the emissions minimization objective we found greater variability
across scenarios, including limiting industrial composting capacity
in the Central Valley where EJ scores tend to be higher and incorporating
more on-farm composting in the southern and Bay regions (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Figure S3</ext-link>). When both agricultural and MSW feedstocks
were included, this spatial trend inhibiting industrial composters
in the Central Valley is even more pronounced (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Figure S4</ext-link>).</p><p>The spatial patterning of the land use scenario,
in which the maximum
capacity for community composters and for on-farm facilities was increased
in urban and agriculturally dense zones, respectively, and the maximum
capacity of industrial facilities was lowered, was strikingly similar
to the results of the baseline scenario in which all three facility
types could be used. This is likely driven by the existing spatial
arrangement of feedstock sources from municipal areas and working
lands for compost application as well as the high cost (both in dollars
and greenhouse gas emissions) of transporting compost large distances.
The inclusion of EJ and air quality constraints had a more noticeable
impact on the distribution of new composters by restricting industrial
facilities in the Central Valley and South Coast regions. Surprisingly,
this scenario still results in a high level of industrial facility
build out by shifting development of industrial composters to the
northern regions of the state, particularly under the emissions minimization
run (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Figure S5</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Sensitivity Analysis Results</title><p>The
results of the sensitivity analysis demonstrate the influence of select
key parameters on overall climate change mitigation impact and associated
cost (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">Table S3</ext-link>). Relative to the Baseline
scenario, altering the conversion rate of waste to compost alters
the overall mitigation and cost, but, unsurprisingly, does not change
build volumes. In the scenario where diversion rates were lower, only
community composting facilities were built. Using a higher estimate
of composting processing emissions had little effect on CO<sub>2</sub>e emissions reductions, but resulted in less on-farm capacity and
more industrial.</p><p>Altering the allowed feedstocks accepted at
composter types had little effect on the land-use, EJ, and EJ &#x00026;
AQ scenarios, except to slightly increase the amount of community
composting built and decrease the other two facility types. This result
is unsurprising given that community composting is the lowest cost
and faces the least constraints under those scenario runs.</p><p>One
surprising result from the sensitivity analysis was the impact
of lowering the on-farm capital cost to the lower literature estimate.
In this run, the cost per ton of carbon sequestered was much higher
than in Baseline for MSW feedstock because the model builds a much
greater volume of on-farm facilities to achieve approximately similar
emissions reductions, but the distance materials must be moved is
significantly higher, which drives up the overall cost. This suggests
that transportation costs likely drive cost outcomes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>We have evaluated the techno-economic
potential of expanding compost
infrastructure as a cost-effective climate change mitigation approach
that complements healthy soil initiatives and just transition goals.
The overall results of this analysis demonstrate that incorporating
social environmental justice objectives into waste management planning
can be accomplished without sacrificing environmental impact or increasing
overall cost. We further reveal that the diversification of composting
facility types and feedstocks allows policymakers to not only better
meet capacity needs, but also provides the opportunity to reduce costs
and maximize emissions reductions.</p><p>Expansion of small-scale
community and on-farm composting programs
may offer significant cobenefits while advancing the policy goals
of SB1383 and as such it is critical to understand the technical and
economic potential of incorporating them into planning processes.
The current stage of targeted investment in new waste management infrastructure
presents an opportunity for prioritizing EJ in sustainability transition
planning.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref></sup> Through this high-level analysis,
we aim to provide a framework for decision-makers as they consider
these investments in new waste management infrastructure from a standpoint
of overlapping climate change mitigation and social vulnerability.</p><p>Our findings complement and uphold existing analyses that have
also utilized a broad lifecycle assessment, including the cost and
emissions associated with organic waste diversion through existing
composting facilities and subsequent land application, to evaluate
statewide nutrient cycling systems. Harrison et al., for instance,
found that landfill diversion and farmland compost applications could
reduce emissions by an average of 6.3 MMT CO<sub>2</sub>e annually.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> Delonge et al., focusing on compost application
to grazed grasslands, demonstrated that the widespread use of compost
may provide a net savings of more than 8 MMT CO<sub>2</sub>e over
15 years if applied to just 6% of California&#x02019;s rangelands.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup></p><p>While we found lower estimates of overall
emissions reductions
than previous studies, the results presented here could be considered
conservative estimates for two important reasons. First, the model
does not account for avoided fertilizer use on cultivated cropland,
which would likely be displaced by the use of compost. Synthetic fertilizer
is energy-intensive to produce. Thus, emissions reductions associated
with the application of compost in lieu of traditional fertilizer
may be greater than what is modeled here. Second, because this analysis
was focused on siting of new infrastructure to meet the needs set
out by SB1383, the goal was to present a cross-sectional analysis
of scenarios that the state and local jurisdictions could reasonably
pursue. Consequently, the findings reflect only a single year of facility
development and emission outcomes, rather than estimates of long-term
impacts. Once these facilities are built, we can assume that the operation
and maintenance costs, which are typically proprietary, would be much
lower than the upfront capital costs, while avoided landfill emissions
and C sequestration could be expected to continue. Once these facilities
are up and running, the cost per tCO<sub>2</sub>e abated will likely
be much lower. Future work could build on this analysis to address
both considerations and produce more refined estimates of long-term
soil C stocks resulting from compost applications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup></p><p>This analysis could also be extended in the future
through the
inclusion of processing emissions associated with different composting
management practices and feedstocks. Field research is currently underway
that may enhance the differentiation among facility types in the typology
developed here. Data were not available for land-use price or operating
costs, which is a limiting factor for this analysis that could be
addressed by future work. Changing dynamics of agriculture that limit
availability of manure and residues may also be fruitfully explored
in later studies, such as increased fallowing of land due to California&#x02019;s
Sustainable Groundwater Management Act or projected closures of dairy
operations in the state.</p><p>Although this model attempts to capture
some of the complexity
of the regulatory process of siting and constructing new composting
infrastructure through air quality regulations, structural barriers
including land-use zoning can vary on a city-by-city basis and were
not represented in this model.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup> These barriers include
convoluted and cost-prohibitive permitting processes, lack of reliable
feedstock collection systems, material contamination challenges, and
lack of education about composting best practices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup> Expanding composting infrastructure in a way that centers
cobenefits for climate, land, and community will require attention
to the heterogeneity of policy contexts, including concerted efforts
to expand organic material collection programs across the state and
create central repositories for data on where these programs exist.</p><p>Across the country, contemporary waste management paradigms are
characterized by high rates of organic material disposal in landfills,
contributing 16% of anthropogenic emissions of the potent greenhouse
gas methane,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref></sup> and perpetuation of historical
harms from pollution on disadvantaged communities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> At the same time, soils continue to lose C due to conventional
agricultural practices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> Engineering approaches and nature-based
solutions to climate change mitigation policies can offer remediation
opportunities on each of these fronts through thoughtful, participatory
planning and development of new infrastructure. In developing a resilient
and just organic waste management system, policymakers in every state
should consider multiple scales of composting infrastructure to achieve
benefits that incorporate cost, emissions, and community impact.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="notes1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>The Supporting Information
is
available free of charge at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711?goto=supporting-info">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Full formulation, parameter values, and data sources
used in the spatial optimization siting model, along with scenario
maps displaying the geographical distribution of new facility capacity
built by composter type (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.3c10711/suppl_file/es3c10711_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="es3c10711_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>es3c10711_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="notes2"><p>The authors
declare the following competing financial interest(s): M.D.P. is the
Chief Science Officer for Carbon Direct Inc., a company combining
science, technology, and capital to deliver quality CO<sub>2</sub> management at scale. M.D.P. is a shareholder in the company and
thus stands to benefit financially from environmental management targeted
at climate change mitigation. The remaining authors declare no competing
financial interest.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Funding gratefully acknowledged from the National
Science Foundation under Grant No. 1739676 and the Working Lands Innovation
Center from California&#x02019;s Strategic Growth Council. The authors
would like to thank Calla Rose Ostrander, Matthew Cotton, and the
LA Compost Council for their invaluable input. We also thank the anonymous
reviewers who helped improve this manuscript greatly.</p></ack><glossary id="dl1"><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>CDFA</term><def><p>California
Department of Food and
Agriculture</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GHG</term><def><p>Greenhouse gas</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSW</term><def><p>Municipal Solid Waste</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit1"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Pachauri</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Broome</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dahe</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dubash</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Edenhofer</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Elgizouli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Friedlingstein</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fuglestvedt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gomez-Echeverri</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hallegatte</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hegerl</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Howden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jimenez Cisneroz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kattsov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marotzke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mastrandrea</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Minx</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mulugetta</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Oppenheimer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pichs-Madruga</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Plattner</surname><given-names>G.-K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>P&#x000f6;rtner</surname><given-names>H.-O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ravindranath</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Reisinger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Riahi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rusticucci</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Scholes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Seyboth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sokona</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stavins</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tschakert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Ypserle</surname><given-names>J.-P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Climate Change 2014: Synthesis Report.
Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment
Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source>; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pachauri</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, Eds.; <publisher-name>IPCC</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>, <year>2014</year>; p <fpage>151</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Digging Deeper:
A Holistic Perspective of Factors Affecting Soil Organic Carbon Sequestration
in Agroecosystems</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>3285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3301</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.14054</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Sanderman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hengl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Soil Carbon
Debt of 12,000 Years
of Human Land Use</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.
S. A.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>114</volume> (<issue>36</issue>), <fpage>9575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9580</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1706103114</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28827323</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ramanathan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Well below 2 &#x000b0;C: Mitigation Strategies for Avoiding
Dangerous to Catastrophic Climate Changes</article-title>. <source>Proc.
Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>114</volume> (<issue>39</issue>), <fpage>10315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10323</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1618481114</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28912354</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit5"><source>USDA.
USDA Announces Cooperative Agreements for Community Compost and Food
Waste Reduction</source>. <publisher-name>USDA Farm Service Agency</publisher-name>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://fsa.usda.gov/news-room/news-releases/2021/usda-announces-cooperative-agreements-for-community-compost-and-food-waste-reduction">https://fsa.usda.gov/news-room/news-releases/2021/usda-announces-cooperative-agreements-for-community-compost-and-food-waste-reduction</uri> (accessed <year>2024</year>-03&#x02013;25).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit6"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Shattuck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silvestri</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Estrada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Holt-Giminez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Healthy Soils, Healthy
Communities: Opportunities to Bridge Environmental Justice and Soil
Carbon Sequestration</source>; <publisher-name>Policy Brief #21; Food
First/Institute for Food and Development Policy in partnership with
the Carbon Cycle Institute and Silvestri Strategies</publisher-name>, <year>2017</year>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ww2.arb.ca.gov/sites/default/files/2020-08/resource_ff-cci-2017-healthy-soils-healthy-communities.pdf">https://ww2.arb.ca.gov/sites/default/files/2020-08/resource_ff-cci-2017-healthy-soils-healthy-communities.pdf</uri> (accessed 2024&#x02013;03&#x02013;25).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit7"><article-title>CARB. Current
California GHG Emission Inventory Data</article-title>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ww2.arb.ca.gov/ghg-inventory-data">https://ww2.arb.ca.gov/ghg-inventory-data</uri> (accessed <year>2024</year>&#x02013;03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit8"><source>Lara.
SB-1383 Short-Lived Climate Pollutants: Methane Emissions</source>; <publisher-name>Dairy and Livestock: Organic Waste: Landfills</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201520160SB1383">http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201520160SB1383</uri> (accessed 2020&#x02013;10&#x02013;14).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit9"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Shobe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The California Healthy Soils
Program: A Progress Report; California Climate and Agriculture Network</article-title>, <year>2020</year>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://calclimateag.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/CA-HSP-Progress-Report-CalCAN_FinalWeb.pdf">https://calclimateag.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/CA-HSP-Progress-Report-CalCAN_FinalWeb.pdf</uri> (accessed 2024&#x02013;03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit10"><article-title>CDFA.
Healthy Soils Program. CDFA Office of Environmental Farming
&#x00026; Innovation</article-title>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdfa.ca.gov/oefi/healthysoils/">https://www.cdfa.ca.gov/oefi/healthysoils/</uri>(accessed <year>2024</year>-03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit11"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Reul-Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abbs</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Composting In California - Addressing
Air Quality Permitting and Regulatory Issues for Expanding Infrastructure;
California Air Pollution Control Officers Associaion</source>; <publisher-name>California Air Resources Board</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>CalRecycle</publisher-loc>, <year>2018</year>; p <fpage>110</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lowenthal</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.-W. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Motallebi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Black and
Organic Carbon Emission Inventories: Review and Application to California</article-title>. <source>J. Air Waste Manag. Assoc.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>60</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3155/1047-3289.60.4.497</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20437785</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eviner</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Soil Carbon
Pools in California&#x02019;s
Annual Grassland Ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Rangel. Ecol. Manag.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>63</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>136</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2111/REM-D-09-00106.1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Parton</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Long-term Impacts of Manure Amendments
on Carbon and Greenhouse Gas Dynamics of Rangelands</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>4533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4547</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.13044</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Shiralipour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Uses and Benefits of MSW Compost:
A Review and an Assessment</article-title>. <source>Biomass Bioenergy</source>
<year>1992</year>, <volume>3</volume> (<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>), <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>279</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0961-9534(92)90031-K</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Huntsinger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bartolome</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cows? In California? Rangelands and
Livestock in the
Golden State</article-title>. <source>Rangelands</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>36</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2111/Rangelands-D-14-00019.1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit17"><article-title>NASS. USDA/NASS 2023 State Agriculture Overview
for California</article-title>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nass.usda.gov/Quick_Stats/Ag_Overview/stateOverview.php?state=CALIFORNIA">https://www.nass.usda.gov/Quick_Stats/Ag_Overview/stateOverview.php?state=CALIFORNIA</uri> (accessed <year>2024</year>&#x02013;03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Bullard</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Solid Waste
Sites and the Black Houston Community*</article-title>. <source>Sociol.
Inq.</source>
<year>1983</year>, <volume>53</volume> (<issue>2&#x02013;3</issue>), <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-682X.1983.tb00037.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11635985</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bulkeley</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Just Waste? Municipal
Waste Management and the Politics
of Environmental Justice</article-title>. <source>Local Environ</source>
<year>2005</year>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13549830500160966</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit20"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><source>State of Composting in
the U.S.: What, Why, Where &#x00026; How</source>. <publisher-name>Institute
for Local Self-Reliance</publisher-name>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ilsr.org/state-of-composting/">https://ilsr.org/state-of-composting/</uri>(accessed <year>2024</year>&#x02013;03&#x02013;25).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kissel</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Climate Change Mitigation,
Air Pollution, and Environmental Justice in California</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>52</volume> (<issue>18</issue>), <fpage>10829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10838</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b00908</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30179479</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit22"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon Sequestration
and Greenhouse Gas Mitigation Potential of Composting and Soil Amendments
on California&#x02019;s Rangelands</article-title>; <source>California&#x02019;s
Fourth Climate Change Assessment CCC4A-CNRA-2018&#x02013;002</source>; <publisher-name>California Natural Resources Agency</publisher-name>, <year>2018</year>; p <fpage>62</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Effects of Organic Matter Amendments on Net Primary
Productivity and Greenhouse Gas Emissions in Annual Grasslands</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>23</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>46</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/12-0620.1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23495635</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>DeLonge</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Lifecycle Model to Evaluate Carbon
Sequestration Potential and Greenhouse Gas Dynamics of Managed Grasslands</article-title>. <source>Ecosystems</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>16</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>962</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>979</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10021-013-9660-5</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantifying
the
Farmland Application of Compost to Help Meet California&#x02019;s Organic
Waste Diversion Law</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>54</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>4545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4553</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.9b05377</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32162912</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Life-Cycle Assessment
Harmonization and Soil Science Ranking Results on Food-Waste Management
Methods</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>51</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>5360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5367</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.6b06115</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28414913</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Saer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lansing</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Davitt</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Life Cycle Assessment
of a Food Waste Composting System: Environmental Impact Hotspots</article-title>. <source>J. Clean. Prod.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>234</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2013.03.022</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Near-Term Potential
of Organic Waste
Management Infrastructure for Soil Carbon Sequestration in Rangelands</article-title>. <source>Environ. Res. Infrastruct. Sustain.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>045007</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/2634-4505/ac970f</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit29"><source>CalRecycle. Analysis of the Progress Toward the SB 1383 Organic Waste
Reduction Goals</source>; <publisher-name>DRRR-2020-1693; CalRecycle</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit30"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Coker</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>; <article-title>Ziegenbein. <italic>California Composting</italic>. BioCycle</article-title>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.biocycle.net/california-composting/">https://www.biocycle.net/california-composting/</uri>(accessed <year>2024</year>&#x02013;03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Emission Characteristics
and Health Risk Assessment of Volatile Organic Compounds Produced
during Municipal Solid Waste Composting</article-title>. <source>Waste
Manag</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wasman.2018.07.024</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30343745</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit32"><source>CalEPA. SB 535 Disadvantaged
Communities</source>. <publisher-name>OEHHA</publisher-name>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://oehha.ca.gov/calenviroscreen/sb535">https://oehha.ca.gov/calenviroscreen/sb535</uri> (accessed <year>2024</year>&#x02013;03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit33"><source>CalRecycle. SWIS Facility/Site Search</source>. <publisher-name>Solid
Waste Information System (SWIS)</publisher-name>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www2.calrecycle.ca.gov/SolidWaste/Site/Search">https://www2.calrecycle.ca.gov/SolidWaste/Site/Search</uri> (accessed <year>2024</year>&#x02013;03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Cerda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Artola</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Font</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barrena</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gea</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Composting of Food Wastes: Status and Challenges</article-title>. <source>Bioresour. Technol.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>248</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2017.06.133</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28693949</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Don</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Seidel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Leifeld</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>K&#x000e4;tterer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pellerin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Emde</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chenu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Carbon Sequestration in Soils and
Climate Change Mitigation&#x02014;Definitions
and Pitfalls</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<year>2024</year>, <volume>30</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <elocation-id>e16983</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.16983</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit36"><source>CalRecycle. SB 1383 Regulations Short-Lived Climate
Pollutants: Organic
Waste Methane Emission Reduction</source>; <publisher-name>Final Environmental
Impact Report DRRR-2019&#x02013;1655; CalRecycle</publisher-name>, <year>2019</year>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://calrecycle.ca.gov/organics/slcp/">https://calrecycle.ca.gov/organics/slcp/</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>Mahady</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Octaviano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Araiza Bola&#x000f1;os</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kammen</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mapping Opportunities for Transportation
Electrification to Address Social Marginalization and Air Pollution
Challenges in Greater Mexico City</article-title>. <source>Environ.
Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>54</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>2103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.9b06148</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31909600</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Sanderman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Baldock</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Accounting for Soil Carbon Sequestration in National
Inventories: A Soil Scientist&#x02019;s Perspective</article-title>. <source>Environ. Res. Lett.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>034003</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/5/3/034003</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit39"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rynk</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Loder-Rossiter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site Planning, Development,
and Environmental Protection</article-title>. In <source>The Composting
Handbook</source>; <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>, <year>2022</year>; pp <fpage>409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-323-85602-7.00018-2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit40"><article-title>EPA. Inventory of U.S. Greenhouse Gas Emissions
and Sinks</article-title>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/ghgemissions/inventory-us-greenhouse-gas-emissions-and-sinks">https://www.epa.gov/ghgemissions/inventory-us-greenhouse-gas-emissions-and-sinks</uri> (accessed <year>2024</year>&#x02013;03&#x02013;26).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Soil Health
and Carbon Management</article-title>. <source>Food Energy Secur</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fes3.96</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>