<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Soc Determinants Health Health Serv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Soc Determinants Health Health Serv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOH</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjoh</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Social Determinants of Health and Health Services</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2755-1938</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2755-1946</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11457435</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39149891</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/27551938241269188</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_27551938241269188</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>I. Social Determinants of Health: State-of-the-Art and Future Directions</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Theorizing epidemiology, the stories bodies tell, and embodied truths: a status update on contending 21<sup>st</sup> c CE epidemiological theories of disease distribution</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4815-5947</contrib-id><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1-27551938241269188" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="corresp1-27551938241269188" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff1-27551938241269188">
<label>1</label>Department of Social and Behavioral Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">1857</institution-id><institution content-type="university">Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health</institution></institution-wrap>, Boston, MA, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-27551938241269188">Nancy Krieger, PhD, Department of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, 677 Huntington Avenue, Boston, MA 02115 (USA). 
Email: <email>nkrieger@hsph.harvard.edu</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>54</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>This critical review considers the status of 21st-century epidemiological theories of disease distribution, updating to 2024 prior analyses published up through 2014, and discusses the implications of these theories for research, practice, and pedagogy. Three key trends stand out: (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) the continued dominance of individualistic biomedical and lifestyle theories; (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) growth and elaboration of social epidemiological alternatives; and (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) the ongoing inattention to epidemiologic theories of disease distribution in the training of epidemiologists and public health professionals and in current efforts to improve the rigor of epidemiological research and causal inference. In a context of growing global political polarization, climate crisis, broader environmental and ecological crises, and stubbornly persistent health inequities within and between nations, producing actionable knowledge relevant to improving the people&#x02019;s health and advancing health justice will require much greater engagement with social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution in research, pedagogy, and practice. At issue is critically engaging with the embodied truths manifested in the stories bodies tell in population patterns of health, disease, and well-being.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>epidemiological theories of disease distribution</kwd><kwd>social epidemiology</kwd><kwd>biomedical model</kwd><kwd>ecosocial theory of disease distribution</kwd><kwd>lifestyle theory</kwd><kwd>psychosocial</kwd><kwd>social determinants of health</kwd><kwd>political economy of health</kwd><kwd>causal inference</kwd><kwd>epidemiology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="award1-27551938241269188"><funding-source id="funding1-27551938241269188">
<institution-wrap><institution>American Cancer Society</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id rid="funding1-27551938241269188">Clinical Research Professor Award</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts19</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Who and what explains the people&#x02019;s health&#x02014;that is, the embodied truths manifested in the stories bodies tell in population patterns of health, disease, and well-being<bold>,</bold> including dynamic trends in both on-average rates and the magnitude of health inequities<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>? This question gets to the core of epidemiology as a population science. It is not a question that can be answered by methods alone. At issue instead are the substantive&#x02014;and contending&#x02014;epidemiological theories of disease distribution that epidemiologists and other public health researchers, practitioners, and advocates draw upon to guide their conceptualization of causal pathways, hypotheses, and interpretations regarding accountability and action to address the exposure&#x02013;outcome relationships of concern<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>.</p><p>Moreover, as the phenomena of population health are dynamic and historically contingent, varying by time, place, and social group, so too are epidemiological theories of disease distribution. This variation exists for multiple reasons, which are relevant to any science, not epidemiology alone: there are changes in what needs to be explained, changes in technology, new discoveries, and changes in who does science<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr3-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>.</p><p>Hence, keeping abreast of changes in and contentions between diverse epidemiologic theories of disease distribution is as necessary as keeping up with methodological developments and discoveries in the field. In a context of global upheaval tied to climate crisis, broader environmental and ecological crises, COVID-19, mounting wealth inequities, and rising political polarization, this critical review accordingly provides a status update on the present state of contending epidemiologic theories of disease distribution, both dominant and alternative&#x02014;and their implications for research, practice, and pedagogy.</p><sec id="section2-27551938241269188"><title>Search Strategy</title><p>The search strategy for this critical review drew principally on literature searches I conducted between January and July 2023 to prepare the second edition of my book <italic toggle="yes">Epidemiology and The People&#x02019;s Health: Theory and Context</italic><sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>; it also is informed by the literature searches I conducted for prior critical reviews on the topic, published in 1994<sup>
<xref rid="bibr4-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</sup>, 2001<sup>
<xref rid="bibr5-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
</sup>, and 2014<sup>
<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup>. For the book revision, I conducted a new literature search for each paragraph in the text to see if new literature addressed the points covered or if the cited authors had published new work on the topic; the databases included PubMed, Web of Science, Google Scholar, SCIELO, and the Harvard library HOLLIS systems (for books as well as articles). Second, I expanded the scope of the literature search (using the same databases) for new areas of work and conceptual frameworks that were either nascent or nonexistent at the time of preparing the first edition of the book (which I researched between 2008 and 2010, building on my scholarship in the area dating back to the late 1980s).</p></sec><sec id="section3-27551938241269188"><title>Selection Criteria</title><p>The literature cited in this critical review draws chiefly on the nearly 2,500 references included in the second edition of <italic toggle="yes">Epidemiology and The People&#x02019;s Health: Theory and Practice</italic><sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>. The selected books and articles cited provide exemplars of the specified theories of disease distribution and their application.</p></sec><sec id="section4-27551938241269188"><title>Big Picture: Continuities and Some Notable Changes</title><p>Succintly stated, over the first quarter of the 21st century, the biomedical and lifestyle theories of disease distribution remain the dominant theories employed, as they were in the 20th century, and alternative social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution have expanded (see <xref rid="table3-27551938241269188" ref-type="table">Textbox 1</xref>; 1, 6). Evidence supporting this statement based on data from the National Institute of Health (NIH) and PubMed is provided in <xref rid="table1-27551938241269188" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-27551938241269188"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Scientific prominence: active NIH funding (for July 2013* and for 2014&#x02013;2022) and article citations in PubMed (for 2003&#x02013;July 2013* and for August 2013&#x02013;August 2022) for dominant theories (biomedical and lifestyle) and social epidemiologic alternatives.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_27551938241269188-table1" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Search terms</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">NIH grants: NIH RePorter</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">PubMed</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Active funding, July 2013*</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Active funding, 2014-2022</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">January 1, 2003&#x02013;July 2013*</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">August 1, 2013&#x02013;August 31, 2022</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(biomedical OR lifestyle)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80,522</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">343,050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">727,864</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(biomedical OR lifestyle OR (genetic OR gene OR genomic OR genome))</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,859</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">449,756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,636,273</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,833,649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(social AND epidemiology)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">454</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144,285</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">((social AND epidemiology) OR (health AND disparities))</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,286</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,516</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,862</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200,646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">((social AND epidemiology) OR ((health AND disparities) NOT (genetic OR gene OR genomic OR genome)))</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,853</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,494</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,607</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196,597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOTAL for time period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,056</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">698,482</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,237,302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,437,187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-27551938241269188"><p>*The results for the July 2013 search were originally published as a figure in Krieger, 2014<sup>
<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Searching for terms employed in NIH grants and in PubMed or other databases can only offer a rough picture of funding and publication priorities; still, the crude picture is compelling. More nuance is provided by a study focused on racism and health that analyzed articles published in four of the world&#x02019;s leading medical journals between 1990 and 2020 (<italic toggle="yes">The Lancet</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">New England Journal of Medicine</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">British Medical Journal</italic>)<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup>. Attesting to their gross neglect of work on this highly salient topic, among the 226,305 items published by these prestigious journals, only 1,213 (0.5%) included the term &#x0201c;racism,&#x0201d; of which over 90 percent were commentaries, viewpoints, or letters&#x02014;not empirical research articles. Of these, the vast majority appeared in 2020, triggered by the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic and the brutal murder of George Floyd by police on May 25, 2020<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="section5-27551938241269188"><title>New Developments in the Complementary Dominant Biomedical and Lifestyle Theories of Disease Distribution</title><p>New 21st-century developments in the dominant theories used in epidemiological research and applied in population health are well captured by their proponents&#x02019; designated terms: <italic toggle="yes">precision medicine</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">lifestyle medicine</italic>, and the <italic toggle="yes">developmental origins of health and disease</italic> framework<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>.</p><p>Initially termed <italic toggle="yes">personalized medicine</italic> and now increasingly called <italic toggle="yes">precision medicine</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr8-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bibr9-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>, this new field has a foundational basis in genomics and advances in big data science. Its premise is that precise knowledge of a person&#x02019;s genome plus other molecular information spanning the full range of the &#x0201c;omics&#x0201d; will enable more precise diagnosis, clinical treatment, and prevention, at not only the individual but also the population level<sup><xref rid="bibr8-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bibr9-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. In 2015, the corresponding term <italic toggle="yes">precision public health</italic> was coined to refer to &#x0201c;1) applying emerging methods and technologies for measuring disease, pathogens, exposures, behaviors and susceptibility in populations; and 2) developing policies and targeted public health programs to improve health&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup>.</p><p>According to proponents of precision medicine, the chief obstacle to precise medical care, including preventive medicine, is inadequate information on individuals, commencing with their genomes<sup><xref rid="bibr8-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bibr9-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. Proponents of precision public health<sup><xref rid="bibr10-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> in turn consider key impediments to be &#x0201c;the immaturity of (a) data and (b) analytics&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup>. By contrast, more critical assessments of the promises and pitfalls of precision medicine and precision public health have pointed to problems of power and resources; a core component of the critique is that data, however important, by themselves have never been an antidote to entrenched inequities in exposures and resources shaping individuals&#x02019; health status and health care<sup><xref rid="bibr12-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bibr13-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>.</p><p>The formal emergence of the field of <italic toggle="yes">lifestyle medicine</italic> has paralleled that of <italic toggle="yes">precision medicine</italic>. As clearly stated in the lead editorial in the 2007 inaugural issue of the <italic toggle="yes">American Journal of Lifestyle Medicine</italic>, its theoretical standpoint holds that the &#x0201c;epidemic of inactivity, obesity, poor nutritional habits, cigarette smoking, and other negative behaviors is driving most disease in the industrialized world&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr14-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</sup>, p. 7) and that &#x0201c;[w]hen it comes to the impact of lifestyle medicine on health, perhaps the cartoon character Pogo best summarized the problem when he stated, &#x02018;We have met the enemy and he is us&#x02019;&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr14-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</sup>, p. 9). The foci remains individual-level health behaviors, as elaborated variously in conceptual essays<sup><xref rid="bibr14-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bibr15-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>, epidemiologic analyses, meta-analyses<sup>
<xref rid="bibr16-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</sup>, and even prescriptions for &#x0201c;planetary health&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr17-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
</sup>. The societal and ecological context in which individuals make their &#x0201c;choices&#x0201d; is treated as a given, with individuals advised to make the healthiest choices possible<sup><xref rid="bibr14-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="bibr15-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr16-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr17-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>.</p><p>The impact of these dominant theories is likewise evident in the 21st-century <italic toggle="yes">developmental origins of health and disease</italic> (DOHaD) paradigm, which is primarily focused on the impact on adult disease risk of what was initially termed &#x0201c;fetal programming&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr18-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
</sup> and then expanded to the &#x0201c;first 1,000 days of life&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr19-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</sup>, p. 1); the field&#x02019;s first journal was founded in 2010<sup>
<xref rid="bibr20-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
</sup>. Indicative of its approach, a 2019 DOHaD article by senior authors in the field included a section on &#x0201c;policy interventions&#x0201d; that declared, &#x0201c;measures such as reducing the rates of gestational diabetes and promoting breastfeeding can minimize the prevalence of evolutionary mismatch, while promoting prudent maternal nutrition from prior to conception and throughout pregnancy is likely to reduce the risk of developing erroneous PARs [predictive adaptive responses]&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr21-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
</sup>, p.1), yet the authors provided no specifics as to what such policies would entail.</p><p>Hence, in a context of important 21st-century advances in work on myriad -omics and in data science, these dominant theories of disease distribution notably continue to focus predominantly on individual-level mechanisms of disease causation (spanning from the organism-level down to sub-molecular), defined principally in relation to genetics and behavioral &#x0201c;choices&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>. The locus of action remains centered on medical interventions, dominated by private health care and life sciences industries<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr12-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bibr13-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="section6-27551938241269188"><title>New Trends in Social Epidemiologic Sociopolitical Theories of Disease Distribution</title><p>Concomitantly, work on and use of alternative social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution has been on the rise, despite garnering only a miniscule fraction of the resources and attention commanded by adherents of the dominant theories of disease distribution<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bibr23-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. Three notable new trends in the 21st century involving the sociopolitical group of social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution include: (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) the rise and subsequent depoliticization of <italic toggle="yes">social determinants of health</italic> (SDOH); (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) a renewed emphasis on the <italic toggle="yes">political economy of health</italic>, combined with new framings of <italic toggle="yes">political, commercial</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">societal determinants of health</italic>; and (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) the rising visibility of <italic toggle="yes">Latin American social medicine-collective health</italic>, including in English-language literature<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>. Other sociopolitical theories of disease distribution continue to be employed in the 21st century, including <italic toggle="yes">health and human rights</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">fundamental cause</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">population health</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.</p><p>Also germane is the rising influence in epidemiology&#x02014;and in public health more broadly&#x02014;of two frameworks coming from outside of these fields: <italic toggle="yes">intersectionality</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr24-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="bibr25-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">decolonization</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr26-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="bibr27-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. Introducing ideas relevant to analyzing population health, it is important to recognize that these frameworks were not intended to analyze explicitly how social conditions affect people&#x02019;s biology and health status, including on what timescales, and involving what social and biological pathways. Instead, their critical contribution is to offer conceptual tools to analyze and challenge the intertwined adverse impacts of injustice in multiple domains (not health alone), as shaped by past and present power relations involving both societal systems (including colonialism, settler-colonialism, enslavement, capitalism, and imperialism) and the social groups forged by these systems (involving social relations of social class, racialized groups, gender, sexuality, nationality, Indigenous status, immigrant status, disability status, and more, singly and combined; <sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="bibr25-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr26-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr27-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr28-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>). A growing number of social epidemiologic books, conceptual articles, and empirical studies invoke these frameworks when presenting their analysis of causal processes driving health inequities and interventions to advance health justice, including reproductive, environmental, and climate justice<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="bibr29-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr30-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr31-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr32-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> while also drawing on social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution to explicate the specific types of exposures, etiologic periods, and social and biological pathways at issue. The rising number of such publications suggests this trend of increasing influence will continue<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>.</p><sec id="section6A-27551938241269188"><title>Social Determinants of Health</title><p>In 2008 the World Health Organization (WHO) held its inaugural global conference on the social determinants of health, whose materials drew extensively on decades of social epidemiologic theorizing and empirical research<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr33-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. A PubMed search readily revealed (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 121; <sup>
<xref rid="bibr34-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
</sup>) that the search term <italic toggle="yes">social determinants of health</italic> identified only one article for the years 1980&#x02013;1989 and 18 articles for 1990&#x02013;1999. For 2010&#x02013;2019 the number jumped to 9,227, and for 2020&#x02013;2022 the number equaled 11,035 articles (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 121; <sup>
<xref rid="bibr34-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
</sup>). Usage of the SDOH framework has been explicitly embraced by numerous influential global and national health agencies and, bridging public health practice and academia, is increasingly included in both policy documents and textbooks<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr33-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="bibr35-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="bibr36-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr37-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. One characteristic feature in contrast to the DOHaD framework is to accord explicit attention to the societal context&#x02014;and specific socially patterned exposures&#x02014;that people are exposed to, and to do so across the life course<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr5-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bibr23-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr35-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="bibr36-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr37-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. not solely from conception to the &#x0201c;first 1,000 days of life&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr19-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</sup>, p.1). An explicit goal of the SDOH framework is to produce knowledge that can advance policy and action to improve the contexts in which people are born, live, work, play, ail, and die<sup><xref rid="bibr32-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="bibr34-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">34</xref><xref rid="bibr35-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr36-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>.</p><p>Suggesting, however, that some recalibration of the SDOH framework may be underway, during the decade after its rise to prominence, the 2019 report by the Pan American Health Organization (PAHO) on <italic toggle="yes">Just Societies: Health Equity and Dignified Lives</italic> notably altered the WHO&#x02019;s Commission on Social Determinants of Health (CSDH) 2008 model to lead with explicitly labeled &#x0201c;structural drivers&#x0201d; and included &#x0201c;more emphasis on colonialism, structural racism, and the importance of relationships to land&#x0201d; along with &#x0201c;the environment and climate change; human rights; and inequities according to gender, ethnicity, sexual orientation, life stage, and disability&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr37-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
</sup>, p. 2249). Related, in 2023, the editors of the newly renamed <italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Social Determinants of Health and Health Services</italic> argued against what they termed &#x0201c;the unfortunate meaning, still common in reports and conferences, whereby SDOH becomes a list of individualized &#x02018;risk factors&#x02019;&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
</sup>, p.118), while nevertheless noting that &#x0201c;SDOH remains a useful umbrella term to capture the political, economic, cultural, and ecological determinants of health&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
</sup>, p.117).</p></sec><sec id="section6B-27551938241269188"><title>Political and Commercial Determinants of Health</title><p>Also indicative of concerns about the rise of depoliticitized social epidemiologic frameworks, distanced from their roots in analyses of the <italic toggle="yes">political economy of health</italic><sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, are new calls, since 2012, for work on both the <italic toggle="yes">political determinants of health</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">38</xref><xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr41-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr42-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr44-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr45-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr46-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> (a topic first discussed explicitly in epidemiology literature in the 1980s; <sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>) and the <italic toggle="yes">corporate</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">commercial determinants of health</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">38</xref><xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bibr47-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> (drawing on prior decades of work on the <italic toggle="yes">political economy of health</italic>; <sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bibr23-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">38</xref><xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>). Examples of new theorizing and empirical analysis in political epidemiology address the following: how democratic governance or its suppression or corruption is associated with population rates of health outcomes and health inequities<sup><xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref><xref rid="bibr41-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr42-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr44-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>; the health impacts of sociopolitical stressors (e.g., campaign rhetoric and policies that target and dehumanize marginalized social groups)<sup>
<xref rid="bibr45-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
</sup>; and how political ideologies of politicians and their constituents (sometimes delimited by processes involving gerrymandering) affect population health profiles<sup><xref rid="bibr42-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="bibr46-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. In part spurred by the near collapse of the U.S. banking industry in 2008 and the global recession thereby triggered<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="bibr49-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>, and by broader work critiquing neoliberalism, market fundamentalism, and the concomitant privatization of public goods and erosion of democratic governance<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="bibr47-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">47</xref><xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr49-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>, work on commercial determinants of health builds on decades of prior research exposing the adverse and inequitable health impacts of corporations and governments that prioritize shareholder value and private profits above all else<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="bibr47-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">47</xref><xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr49-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>. Auguring further refinement of ideas and evidence is both the growing engagement of political scientists, in part spurred by the COVID-19 pandemic and by the growing impacts of political polarization on population health<sup><xref rid="bibr42-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">42</xref><xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr44-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>, and the debates over whether work on the commercial determinants of health should focus on harmful commodities versus all commercial activities versus capitalism per se<sup><xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="bibr47-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>, with some of this latter work distinguishing between different &#x0201c;varieties&#x0201d; of capitalism&#x02014;that is, different types of welfare states<sup>
<xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
</sup> and other work referring to &#x0201c;capitalism&#x0201d; overall<sup><xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bibr47-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. Attesting to the rising prominence of work in this area, in 2023 the WHO announced it will host its first global conference on the commercial determinants of health<sup>
<xref rid="bibr50-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>
</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="section6C-27551938241269188"><title>Latin American Social Medicine-Collective Health and the Social Determination of Health</title><p>Also noteworthy is the growing influence of the varied theories of disease distribution termed <italic toggle="yes">Latin American Social Medicine</italic> and, in Brazil, <italic toggle="yes">collective health</italic>, which together emphasize what these theories term the <italic toggle="yes">social determination of the health-disease-care proces</italic>s and call for the practice of &#x0201c;critical epidemiology&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. In the 21st century, these theories have become increasingly visible in and beyond Latin America<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup> and have begun to engage more explicitly with Indigenous health and Indigenous frameworks, while also expanding their focus on environmental integrity<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup>.</p><p>Reflecting in part different sociopolitical contexts, Latin American Social Medicine-Collective Health (LASM-CH) theoretical work has differed from most of the English-language social epidemiologic theories in several ways<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. First, it has devoted more attention to the impact of capitalist development, imperialism, and politics on health<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup>. Second, it has elevated critiques of biomedical positivism, structural functionalism, and their joint focus on static &#x0201c;risk factors&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;outcomes&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. Third, it has objected to the phrase &#x0201c;social determinants of health&#x0201d; because it is held to obscure <italic toggle="yes">who</italic> is doing the <italic toggle="yes">determining</italic> of (i.e., is causing and accountable for) the relevant exposures and, in effect, reducing these &#x0201c;social determinants&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;risk factors;&#x0201d; as an alternative, they focus on the <italic toggle="yes">social determination</italic> of what was initially termed the <italic toggle="yes">health&#x02013;illness process</italic>, and then later the <italic toggle="yes">health&#x02013;illness&#x02013;care process</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. Another difference stems from the histories of Latin American military dictatorships and oligarchies and the coercive power of the state, leading LASM-CH to emphasize the critical importance of collective action by non-state actors&#x02014;that is, <italic toggle="yes">collectivities</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">social subjects</italic>, such as social classes and popular movements&#x02014;to shape and improve population health and health equity via democratic empowerment of the people<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. As societal conflicts over the meaning and exercise of economic and social democracy continue to grow in a context of increased strife tied to climate crisis and ecological degradation, the influence of LASM-CH will likely continue to rise<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section7-27551938241269188"><title>New Foci in Psychosocial Theories of Disease Distribution</title><p>During the 21st century, the focus of the social epidemiological psychosocial theories of disease distribution has remained on individuals&#x02019; brain-mediated psychological perceptions of&#x02014;and their health-damaging or health-enhancing responses to&#x02014;social conditions, social interactions, and social status<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr5-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bibr23-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr36-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. What has become increasingly prominent, however, is use of the constructs of &#x0201c;allostasis&#x0201d; (first proposed by Sterling and Eyer in 1988 (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr53-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>
</sup>, p.631; <sup>
<xref rid="bibr54-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
</sup>), and measurement of &#x0201c;allostatic load&#x0201d; (first proposed by McEwan and Stellar in 1993; <sup><xref rid="bibr55-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="bibr56-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup>).</p><p>The idea of <italic toggle="yes">allostasis</italic> refers to regulatory systems that achieve &#x0201c;stability through change,&#x0201d; using &#x0201c;feed-<italic toggle="yes">forward</italic> control from the brain to <italic toggle="yes">prevent</italic> errors&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr54-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
</sup>, p.169; emphasis appears in the original), and stands in contrast to the dominant notion of <italic toggle="yes">homeostasis</italic>, primarily conceptualized as being error-correcting feedback (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr54-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
</sup>, p.169). As argued by Sterling in 2020, the model of allostasis thus &#x0201c;clarified why the brain should be in charge: it is simply more efficient to predict a need to satisfy it than to wait for an error and correct it&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr54-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
</sup>, p. xi). <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><italic toggle="yes">llostatic load</italic> in turn refers to &#x0201c;wear-and-tear from chronic over-activity or underactivity&#x0201d; of systems &#x0201c;that protect the body by responding to internal and external stress,&#x0201d; as measured by biomarkers pertaining to the functioning of &#x0201c;the autonomic nervous system, the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, and cardiovascular, metabolic, and immune systems&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr56-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>
</sup>, p.171). Elaborated since&#x02014;especially with reference to early life exposures, cumulative disadvantage across the lifecourse, and psychoneurobiology<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bibr23-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr36-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="bibr54-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>&#x02014;the concepts of <italic toggle="yes">allostasis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">allostatic state</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">allostatic overload</italic>, along with their associated metaphors of imbalance, have increasingly informed 21st-century epidemiologic psychosocial ideas and research. For example, 76 percent of the 5,426 Web of Science entries indexed using these three terms have been published in the past decade (i.e., since 2013)<sup>
<xref rid="bibr57-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>
</sup>. Notably, alongside this increased focus on allostatic load as either outcome or mediator, the emphasis remains on psychological pathways and mechanisms, not on who and what socially structures the relevant patterns of exposures or precipitates the anticipatory activation of physiological responses to psychosocial stimuli<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="section8-27551938241269188"><title>New Advances in the Ecosocial Theory of Disease Distribution</title><p>The ecosocial theory of disease distribution, which I first proposed in 1994 and have elaborated since (<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="bibr5-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>; see <xref rid="fig1-27551938241269188" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) currently stands as the most systematically articulated and widely-used social epidemiological theory of disease distribution in literature published in English that engages with societal (including structural), biological, and ecological phenomena, at multiple levels across the lifecourse and historical generation (<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr58-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="bibr59-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup>; see <xref rid="table4-27551938241269188" ref-type="table">Textbox 2</xref>). New developments include conceptualizing health outcomes as <italic toggle="yes">emergent embodied phenotypes</italic><sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr60-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> that, through their population distributions, reveal <italic toggle="yes">embodied truths</italic> that are actionable in both courts of law and in the court of public opinion&#x02014;hence they are relevant to fostering change for health justice<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. Core constructs and theses of the ecosocial theory of disease distribution are provided in <xref rid="fig1-27551938241269188" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="table4-27551938241269188" ref-type="table">Textbox 2</xref>, respectively. Recent examples of the theory&#x02019;s application both empirically and conceptually, published in the last five years (i.e., since 2019) are provided in Supplemental <xref rid="table3-27551938241269188" ref-type="table">Textbox 1</xref>, with the theory increasingly used to guide work conducted in multiple continents on frameworks for understanding health inequities; cancer; reproductive health; mental health; impacts of racism on health outcomes, health behaviors, and health care; substance use; policing, carceral systems, and health; HIV care and outcomes; COVID-19; and climate change, political ecology, and health equity, articulated in relation to occupational and environmental health, environmental justice, and planetary health. Together, these growing applications and extensions of the ecosocial theory of disease distribution may well have the potential to take epidemiology to a new level&#x02014;literally.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-27551938241269188"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Core features of the ecosocial theory of disease distribution.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_27551938241269188-fig1" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="table2-27551938241269188"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_27551938241269188-table2" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Core constructs: The Ecosocial Theory of Disease Distribution and Embodying (In)justice: Levels, Pathways, and Power</bold> The four core and conjoint constructs of the ecosocial theory of disease distribution are as follows, all of which involve processes conditional upon extant political economy and political ecology and structured chance [1, 2, 6]. They comprise [2, pp. 32&#x02013;33]:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Embodiment</italic>: referring to how we humans, and all other biological organisms, literally biologically incorporate, that is, embody, our societal and ecologic context. While this may seem to be an obvious truism, as noted above, this approach to conceptualizing embodiment stands in direct opposition to the dominant frameworks of &#x0201c;nature&#x0201d; vs. &#x0201c;nurture&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;gene x environment interaction.&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Pathways of embodiment</italic>: referring to the concrete and concurrent social and biophysical processes and mechanisms, from macro to micro, involved in organisms embodying their societal and ecological context, thereby producing population distributions of health, disease, and death. Identification of these pathways is guided by ecosocial theory&#x02019;s other core constructs and consideration of both political economy and political ecology; both the &#x0201c;why&#x0201d; as well as &#x0201c;how&#x0201d; of causal processes matter.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Cumulative interplay of exposure, susceptibility, and resistance</italic>: in relation to the pathways of embodiment, at each and every level, and in relation to both lifecourse and historical generation. Social movements resisting injustice and organizing for equity, for example, are every much a part of resistance relevant to shaping population health profiles as are individual-level interactions or resilience.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Agency and accountability</italic>: referring both to who and what, at each and every level, is responsible for health inequities and also for the research to explain population health. Key questions are: who benefits from injustice &#x00026; from research which ignores injustice, and, conversely, who is harmed by injustice and by the overt suppression, lack of funding, and self-censorship that can limit research on these issues.</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn2-27551938241269188"><p>* This graphic and textbox are reproduced from my book <italic toggle="yes">Epidemiology and The People&#x02019;s Health: Theory and Context</italic> (second edition; 1, p. 261).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><boxed-text position="float"><label>Textbox 1.</label><caption><p>Core features of the dominant epidemiologic theories of disease distribution&#x02014;biomedical and lifestyle&#x02014;and the social epidemiological alternatives<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="bibr5-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.</p></caption><table-wrap position="float" id="table3-27551938241269188"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_27551938241269188-table3" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1) <bold>Biomedical:</bold>
<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p><bold>Core assumptions: &#x0201c;</bold><italic toggle="yes">1</italic>) the &#x02018;real&#x02019; causes of disease comprise biophysical agents, genes, and &#x02018;risk factors,&#x02019; with exposure largely a consequence of individual characteristics and behaviors; <italic toggle="yes">2</italic>) these &#x02018;real&#x02019; causes of disease in individuals are <italic toggle="yes">the</italic> causes of&#x02014;and are sufficient to explain&#x02014;population rates of disease; and <italic toggle="yes">3</italic>) theorizing about disease occurrence is equivalent to theorizing about disease causation in relation to mechanisms occurring within biological organisms; by implication, population-level theorizing is largely, if not wholly, irrelevant&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 149).</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Corollaries: &#x0201c;</bold>It emphasizes biological determinants of disease amenable to intervention through the health-care system, considers social determinants of disease to be at best secondary (if not irrelevant), and views populations simply as the sum of individuals and population patterns of disease as simply reflective of individual cases. In this view, disease in populations is reduced to a question of disease in individuals, which in turn is reduced to a question of biological malfunctioning. This biologic substrate, divorced from its societal context, thus becomes the optimal locale for interventions, which chiefly are medical in nature&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 164).</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>2) <bold>Lifestyle:</bold>
<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p><bold>Core assumptions: &#x0201c;</bold>Health behaviors&#x02009;=&#x02009;freely-chosen &#x02018;risk factors&#x02019; (e. g., involving diet, smoking, sleep, sex) that lead to exposures that are harmful or beneficial to health, via pathways ultimately involving molecular biology and endogenous processes of pathogenesis&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 165), with &#x0201c;lifestyle&#x0201d; defined in the 2018 2<sup>nd</sup> edition of the <italic toggle="yes">Oxford Dictionary of Public Health</italic> as &#x0201c;The behavior pattern, customs, and habits of persons or groups, generally considered in the context of consequences for health, and including nature and amount of exercise, dietary habits, and use of tobacco, alcohol, coffee, tea, stimulant and sedative substances (licit or illicit), and recreational time&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 172).</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Corollaries: &#x0201c;</bold><italic toggle="yes">Lifestyle</italic> equals individual &#x02018;choice&#x02019; equals &#x02018;health behavior&#x02019; equals individual&#x02019;s exposure to &#x02018;health behavior-related risk factors,&#x02019; chiefly involving smoking, alcohol, illicit drugs, food, exercise, and sexual behaviors&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 178).</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
<bold>3) Social epidemiologic alternatives</bold>
<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>
<bold>Common features:</bold>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>&#x0201c;the longstanding thesis that distributions of health and disease in human populations cannot be understood apart from&#x02014;and necessarily occur in&#x02014;their societal context;</p></list-item><list-item><p>the corollary that social processes causally (albeit probabilistically) determine any health or disease outcome that is socially patterned; and</p></list-item><list-item><p>the prediction that as societies change, whether in their social, economic, cultural, or technological features, so too will their population levels and distributions of health and disease&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 195).</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Three major subsets:</bold>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>&#x025fc; <italic toggle="yes">Sociopolitical theories of disease distribution</italic>, which focus on &#x0201c;analyzing patterns of disease distribution in relation to power, politics, economics, and rights&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 198), and whose variants include: &#x0201c;social production of disease; political economy of health; social determinants of health; political determinants of health; commercial determinants of health; societal determinants of health; fundamental cause; Latin American social medicine-collective health; health and human rights&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 197).</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x025fc; <italic toggle="yes">Psychosocial theories of disease distribution,</italic> which emphasize &#x0201c;individual&#x02019;s psychological perceptions of&#x02014;and their health-damaging or health-enhancing responses to&#x02014;social conditions, social interactions, and social status&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 233).</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x025fc; The <italic toggle="yes">ecosocial theory of disease distribution,</italic> which analyzes (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) how people (and other living organisms) &#x0201c;literally embody, biologically, their societal, ecological and historical context&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 195), thereby producing population patterns of health, disease, and well-being, and (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) both &#x0201c;who and what drives current and changing patterns of social inequalities in health&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 260) and &#x0201c;who generates and shapes the content of epidemiologic theories of disease distribution&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, p. 195).</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></boxed-text><boxed-text position="float"><label>Textbox 2.</label><caption><p>Ecosocial theory of disease distribution: emergent embodied phenotypes, and embodied truths of health (in)justice: 11 theses*.</p></caption><table-wrap position="float" id="table4-27551938241269188"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_27551938241269188-table4" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>People literally embody, biologically, their lived experience, in societal and ecologic context, thereby creating population patterns of health and disease.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Societies&#x02019; epidemiologic profiles (for human health and the health of other species) are shaped by the ways of living afforded by their current and changing societal arrangements of power, property, and the production and reproduction of both social and biological life, involving people, other species, and the biophysical world in which we live.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Determinants of current and changing societal patterns of disease distribution, including health inequities, are exogenous to people&#x02019;s bodies, and manifest at different levels and involve different spatiotemporal scales, with macro-level phenomena more likely to propel and constrain meso- and microlevel phenomena than vice versa; to the extent genes are relevant to societal distributions of disease, at issue is gene expression rather than gene frequency.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Consequently, &#x0201c;the notion of &#x02018;embodiment&#x02019; advances three critical claims: 1) bodies tell stories about&#x02014;and cannot be studied divorced from&#x02014;the conditions of our existence; 2) bodies tell stories that often&#x02014;but not always&#x02014;match people&#x02019;s stated accounts; and 3) bodies tell stories that people cannot or will not tell, either because they are unable, forbidden, or choose not to tell. Just as the proverbial &#x02018;dead man&#x02019;s bones&#x02019; do in fact tell tales, via forensic pathology and historical anthropometry, so too do our living bodies tell stories about our lives, whether or not these are ever consciously expressed&#x0201d; [2, p. 3]&#x02014;and: &#x0201c;These embodied stories constitute what I have newly termed &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">embodied truths.</italic>&#x02019; [2, p. 3]&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hence, &#x0201c;all organisms live their phenotype(s), not genotype&#x02014;and this phenotype is not fixed. What we live is our <italic toggle="yes">emergent embodied phenotype</italic>, one which emerges through engagement with the dynamic social and biophysical features of the dynamic changing world we inhabit and alter.&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>In societies exhibiting social divisions based on property and power, and in which those with the most power and resources comprise a small percent of the population, the more prevalent the health outcome, the greater the absolute burden (and potentially the relative burden) on those with less power and fewer resources, as they comprise the majority of the population; a corollary is that for more rare or infrequent (nonendemic) diseases, it cannot be presumed, in advance, whether health inequities in the outcome exist and, if they do, the direction of the gradient.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Explanations of disease distribution cannot be reduced solely to explanations of disease mechanisms, as the latter do not account for why rates and patterns change in complex ways over time and place.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Practice of a reflexive epidemiology that situates in broader societal context an investigation&#x02019;s motivating theories, hypotheses, methods of analysis, and interpretation of findings will improve the likelihood of epidemiologists being better positioned to understand and convey the meanings and limitation of our study results and explanations for population patterns of health, disease and well-being.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A rigorous approach to identifying both embodied <italic toggle="yes">biological expressions of injustice</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">unjust interpretations of biology</italic> will likewise enhance the ability of epidemiologists and others to analyze health inequities critically by challenging longstanding ideologies of biological determinism and innate superiority and inferiority, including in relation to: (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) racism, white supremacy, and racialized social groups; (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) sexism, sex-linked biology, and gender identities; (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) heterosexism and sexualities; (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) social class; and (<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>) any other social divisions treated as &#x0201c;natural&#x0201d; and heritable characteristics of individuals.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Rigorous research to improve population health and rectify and prevent health inequities thus entails rejecting <italic toggle="yes">biological essentialism</italic> and instead embracing <italic toggle="yes">embodied integration</italic> to guide hypotheses, methods, and interpretation of results.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hence, &#x0201c;the reason to analyze health inequities is not to prove that injustice is wrong, since injustice is wrong by definition. Rather, the point is to illuminate how both injustice and equity can respectively shape people&#x02019;s health and the health of our planet for bad and for good, so as to guide action and allocation of resources for prevention, redress, accountability and change.&#x0201d; [2, p. 4] Or, to paraphrase the 11th thesis on Feuerbach written in 1845 by Karl Marx, the point is not simply to interpret the world, it is to change it.</p></list-item></list>Note: Theses 1&#x02013;3 and 6&#x02013;8 were articulated in 2011 (in Krieger N. Epidemiology and The People&#x02019;s Health: Theory and Context. New York: Oxford University Press, 2011); theses 4, 5 and 9&#x02013;11 were added in 2024.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn3-27551938241269188"><p>*This textbox is reproduced from my book <italic toggle="yes">Epidemiology and The People&#x02019;s Health: Theory and Context</italic> (second edition; 1, pp. 262-263)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></boxed-text></sec><sec id="section9-27551938241269188"><title>Problematic Paradox: A Continued Resounding Silence on the Importance of Epidemiologic Theories of Disease Distribution for Rigorous Research, Training, And Action</title><p>Yet, despite the growth and vitality of theorizing and empirical research premised on the social epidemiological alternative theories of disease distribution<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bibr23-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr35-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="bibr36-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr37-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr41-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr42-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr43-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr44-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr45-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr46-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr47-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr49-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr50-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr52-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr53-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr54-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr55-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr56-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr57-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr58-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr59-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr60-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> biomedical and lifestyle theories problematically remain the dominant influences on epidemiologic training and research (<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>; see <xref rid="table1-27551938241269188" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Not only do contemporary epidemiologic training and textbooks still include very little critical discussion of epidemiological theories of disease distribution, their history, content, and application<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, but similar omissions plague current recommendations for improving graduate education and training in epidemiology worldwide<sup><xref rid="bibr61-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">61</xref><xref rid="bibr62-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr63-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup>. A global survey of applied epidemiologists based in 64 countries in 2019&#x02013;2020 failed to ask any questions about the training these epidemiologists had received in epidemiological theories of disease distribution; by contrast, extensive questions were asked about the range of methods learned<sup>
<xref rid="bibr63-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>
</sup>. Revealingly, however, when summarizing the free text entry responses, the study authors noted the theme of more &#x0201c;training with a focus on cultural, political, and contextual understanding was needed&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr63-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>
</sup>. Similarly, within the United States, a 2015 review sponsored by the American College of Epidemiology noted that the training of epidemiologists insufficiently addressed what they termed the &#x0201c;&#x02018;upstream&#x02019; causes of disease&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;broader societal factors that shape population health&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr61-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>
</sup>, p. 463). A follow-up report issued in 2017 remained silent on the need for training in epidemiologic theories of disease distribution<sup>
<xref rid="bibr62-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>
</sup>.</p><p>Additionally, 21st-century guidelines to improve the rigor of epidemiologic research continue to ignore the impact of epidemiological theories of disease distribution. Illustrating this problem are the original STROBE (&#x0201c;STrengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology&#x0201d;) guidelines, first published in 2007, along with their updates and many extensions<sup>
<xref rid="bibr64-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>
</sup>. None of the STROBE guidelines include any mention of the relevance of epidemiologic theories of disease distribution for framing, critiquing, or improving study hypotheses, methods, or interpretation of findings. Thus, while the guidelines do call for hypotheses to be clearly stated, they are silent on recommending that researchers state the epidemiologic theories of disease distribution that inform the hypotheses being proposed, let alone how the findings are interpreted and contextualized.</p><p>The neglect of attention to epidemiologic theories of disease distribution is also evident in the 21st-century &#x0201c;causal revolution,&#x0201d; as designated by its proponents<sup>
<xref rid="bibr65-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>
</sup>, to improve methods for causal inference that is sweeping across epidemiology and other disciplines. From the outset, the singular focus has been on quantitative methods to analyze data, variously obtained from observational and experimental studies and mined for &#x0201c;machine learning&#x0201d; from &#x0201c;big data&#x0201d; sources, in order to identify causal effects<sup>
<xref rid="bibr65-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>
</sup>. However, even though early on epidemiologists vitally involved in this work recognized the crucial role of &#x0201c;background knowledge&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr66-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>
</sup> for understanding and correctly modeling the causal processes at play, there remains total silence about the role of epidemiological theories of disease distribution in shaping this &#x0201c;background knowledge,&#x0201d; let alone who and what structures this knowledge<sup><xref rid="bibr65-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">65</xref><xref rid="bibr66-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr67-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup>.</p><p>Not surprisingly, such theoretical stances have spurred considerable controversy and debate led by epidemiologists explicitly trained in and employing social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution, who are appreciative of the methodological advances but leery of how they are being deployed<sup><xref rid="bibr68-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">68</xref><xref rid="bibr69-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr70-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr71-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup>. These sharp exchanges have led to some backpedaling of initial claims that social epidemiologic research lies outside of the bounds of rigorous sciences that use causal inference methods<sup><xref rid="bibr72-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,<xref rid="bibr73-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup>. It has likewise spurred new work explicitly informed by epidemiologic theories of disease distribution to improve use of causal inference methods in social epidemiology and to show the harms to causal inference posed by research that ignores the actual societal and ecological contexts in which people are born, live, ail, and die<sup><xref rid="bibr69-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">69</xref><xref rid="bibr70-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr71-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,<xref rid="bibr74-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></sup>.</p><p>Consequently, in a context of continued dominance of biomedical and lifestyle theories of disease distribution, the bulk of epidemiologists, both in the field and those being trained, are left to their own devices, free to populate myriad causal diagrams and webs with undertheorized assorted &#x0201c;variables,&#x0201d; as if hypotheses were independent of theoretical frameworks, and as if approaches to causal theorizing about determinants of population distributions and risk of disease are either self-evident, requiring no analysis, or else simply a matter of idiosyncratic inspiration (or ideological proclivities)<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>. If, however, transparency of assumptions is vital for valid scientific research, then explicit attention to epidemiologic theories of disease distributions is essential for the field&#x02014;and as this article and the scholarship it cites make clear, the cost of ignoring these theories can be high, whether measured in wasted effort or, more profoundly, in people&#x02019;s lives.</p></sec><sec id="section10-27551938241269188"><title>A Wake-Up Call</title><p>In closing, it is time&#x02014;past time&#x02014;for epidemiologists and others in public health to take stock and reject the status quo<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>. As climate crisis grows, as environmental and ecosystem degradation worsens, as health inequities stubbornly persist within and between nations, and as new evidence makes clear the myths of inevitable &#x0201c;epidemiologic transition&#x0201d; and ever-improving population health<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bibr23-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="bibr29-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr30-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr31-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr32-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="bibr36-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">36</xref><xref rid="bibr37-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr39-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr40-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bibr47-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr58-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="bibr59-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> (take, for example, the recent trends of alarming declines in life expectancy in the United States, in a context of already much worse mortality and morbidity rates compared to many other wealthy industrialized nations; <sup><xref rid="bibr75-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,<xref rid="bibr76-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></sup>), it is clear that biomedical and lifestyle theories of disease distribution are not up to the task of confronting these challenges.</p><p>The continued dominance of these individualistic theories is inexcusable; the vital alternatives provided by diverse social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution offer more promise. But these social epidemiologic theories of disease distribution cannot be purely &#x0201c;social&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;social ecological&#x0201d; or be concerned solely with socially-defined &#x0201c;fundamental causes&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Instead, they must engage, vitally, with the biophysical realities of life on this planet&#x02014;as necessitated by the health impacts on humans and other species whose lives are causally interconnected, of mounting socially-structured ecological and environmental crises, both independent of and intertwined with climate crisis<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="bibr48-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="bibr49-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr77-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,<xref rid="bibr78-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></sup>. As emphasized by the ecosocial theory of disease distribution, taking on this challenge requires engaging with political ecology as much as it does with any notions of &#x0201c;social ecology&#x0201d;&#x02014;and this joint reckoning with how we and other organisms embody our societal and ecological context, shaped by political economies spanning from global to local, is fundamental, causally, for understanding, analyzing, and working to change population patterns of health among humans and other species (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, pp. 290&#x02013;292).</p><p>Underscoring these points, since 2010, impelled both by climate change and, since the 2020 COVID-19 pandemic, conceptual and empirical research has been published in public health journals that explicitly draws on political ecology in conjunction with the ecosocial theory of disease distribution (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup>, pp. 290&#x02013;292). Conceptually, this work has sought to sharpen the critical political economy (and typically anti-capitalist) focus of research and interventions addressing links between climate change, ecological degradation, and the health of people and other species, alongside new work in social epidemiology renewing critical attention to the political, economic, and commercial determinants of health<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr38-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr77-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">77</xref><xref rid="bibr78-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr79-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr80-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr81-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></sup>. One focus of this work has been to develop explicit critiques of the lack of attention in the &#x0201c;One Health&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;planetary health&#x0201d; literature to political economy, health inequities, and Indigenous knowledge<sup><xref rid="bibr51-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bibr79-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">79</xref><xref rid="bibr80-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="bibr81-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></sup>. Other theoretical efforts have sought to clarify the overlaps and distinctions between &#x0201c;occupational and environmental health; political ecology of health; environmental justice; ecohealth; One Health; ecological public health; and planetary health&#x0201d; (<sup>
<xref rid="bibr80-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>
</sup>, p. 420). Together, this conceptual and empirical research, drawing on political ecology and combined with further systematic articulation and application of the ecosocial theory of disease distribution, can strengthen the reach and rigor of the work epidemiologists do. Especially in this era of global climate change and fierce battles for climate and environmental justice, the stakes could not be higher for apt use of theory to get the questions and answers right regarding who and what is causing, and can change, the epidemiologic profiles of both people and other species.</p><p>By making conscious use of epidemiologic theory and having informed debates over the different epidemiologic theories of disease distribution at play, those of us who are epidemiologists or other public health professionals and advocates more broadly stand a better of chance of producing epidemiologic knowledge that reveals embodied truths that unmask accountability for the state of the people&#x02019;s health and health inequities<sup><xref rid="bibr1-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-27551938241269188" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Such knowledge is essential for all engaged in the multisectoral, multigenerational work to prevent disease, improve population health and health equity, and advance health justice.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="section11-27551938241269188" specific-use="figshare"><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material id="supp1-27551938241269188" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>sj-docx-1-joh-10.1177_27551938241269188 - Supplemental material for Theorizing epidemiology, the stories bodies tell, and embodied truths: a status update on contending 21<sup>st</sup> c CE epidemiological theories of disease distribution</title></caption><media xlink:href="sj-docx-1-joh-10.1177_27551938241269188.docx"/><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-1-joh-10.1177_27551938241269188 for Theorizing epidemiology, the stories bodies tell, and embodied truths: a status update on contending 21<sup>st</sup> c CE epidemiological theories of disease distribution by Nancy Krieger, PhD in International Journal of Social Determinants of Health and Health Services</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The author declares there is no conflict of interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Declaration of funding:</bold> This work was supported in part by the author&#x02019;s American Cancer Society Clinical Research Professor Award; the funder had no role in study design, data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or writing of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Nancy Krieger <ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4815-5947" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4815-5947</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Correction (August 2024):</bold> Article updated after OnlineFirst publication to correct Figure 1. For more details, see [DOI: <ext-link xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1177/27551938241281636" ext-link-type="uri">10.1177/27551938241281636</ext-link>].</p></fn></fn-group><bio id="d67e4188"><title>Author Biography</title><p><bold>Nancy Krieger</bold> (PhD in epidemiology, University of California-Berkeley) is a professor of social epidemiology and the American Cancer Society clinical research professor at the Harvard T. H. Chan School of Public Health (HSPH) and director of the HSPH interdisciplinary concentration on women, gender, and health. She is an internationally recognized social epidemiologist and Clarivate/Institute for Scientific Information (ISI) highly cited scientist, with a background in biochemistry, philosophy of science, and history of public health, with over 35 years of activism involving social justice, science, and health. In 2023, she was awarded the Sedgwick Memorial Medal for Distinguished Service in Public Health by the American Public Health Association. Krieger&#x02019;s academic work to advance health justice focuses on the use of conceptual frameworks in analyses of population distributions of disease, past and present, including developing the ecosocial theory of disease distribution; etiologic research; and methodologic research.</p></bio><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-27551938241269188"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Epidemiology and the People&#x02019;s Health: Theory and Context</source>. <edition>2nd ed (revised and expanded)</edition>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2024</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-27551938241269188"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Ecosocial Theory, Embodied Truths, and The People&#x02019;s Health</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-27551938241269188"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oreskes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Why Trust Science?</source>
<publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-27551938241269188"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology and the web of causation: has anyone seen the spider?</article-title>
<source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>903</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7992123</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-27551938241269188"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Theories for social epidemiology in the 21st century: an ecosocial perspective</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>668</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>677</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11511581</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-27551938241269188"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Got theory? &#x02013; on the 21<sup>st</sup> c CE rise of explicit use of epidemiologic theories of disease distribution: a review and ecosocial analysis.</article-title>
<source>Current Epidemiol Reports</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-27551938241269188"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Maio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maybank</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medicine&#x02019;s privileged gatekeepers: producing harmful ignorance about racism and health</article-title>. <source>Health Affairs Blog</source>. <comment>April 20, 2021</comment>. <comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.healthaffairs.org/do/10.1377/hblog20210415.305480/full/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.healthaffairs.org/do/10.1377/hblog20210415.305480/full/</ext-link>
</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-27551938241269188"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varmus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A new initiative on precision medicine</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>372</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>795</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25635347</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-27551938241269188"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Precision medicine in 2030-seven ways to transform healthcare</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>184</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1419</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33740447</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-27551938241269188"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <comment>Precision public health and precision medicine: two peas in a pod. US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Genomics and Precision Health Blog, March 2, 2015. <ext-link xlink:href="https://blogs.cdc.gov/genomics/2015/03/02/precision-public/" ext-link-type="uri">https://blogs.cdc.gov/genomics/2015/03/02/precision-public/</ext-link> (accessed: March 28, 2023)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-27551938241269188"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Canfell</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kodiyattu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eakin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Real-world data for precision public health of noncommunicable diseases: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2166</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-14452-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36434553</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-27551938241269188"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chowkwanyun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>&#x0201c;Precision&#x0201d; public health &#x02014; between novelty and hype</article-title>. <source>New Engl J Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>379</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1400</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30184442</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-27551938241269188"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Great future or greedy venture: Precision medicine needs philosophy</article-title>. <source>Health Sci Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<comment>e376</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-27551938241269188"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rippe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angelopoulos</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The American Journal of Lifestyle Medicine: a forum, a vision, and a mandate</article-title>. <source>Am J Lifestyle Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-27551938241269188"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lianov</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adamson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lifestyle medicine core competencies: 2022 Update</article-title>. <source>Am J Lifestyle Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>734</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>739</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36389051</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-27551938241269188"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Combined lifestyle factors, all-cause mortality and cardiovascular disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32892156</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-27551938241269188"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lifestyle medicine prescriptions for personal and planetary health</article-title>. <source>J Climate Change Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>100077</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joclim.2021.100077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-27551938241269188"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The origins of the developmental origins theory</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>261</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>417</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17444880</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-27551938241269188"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Poston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gluckman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Developmental Origins of Health and Disease</source>. <edition>2</edition><sup>nd</sup> edition. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-27551938241269188"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Journal of Developmental Origins of Health and Disease (J DOHaD)</collab>. <comment>About This Journal. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-developmental-origins-of-health-and-disease/information/about-this-journal" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-developmental-origins-of-health-and-disease/information/about-this-journal</ext-link> (Accessed: March 23, 2024)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-27551938241269188"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gluckman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evolutionary and developmental mismatches are consequences of adaptive developmental plasticity in humans and have implications for later disease risk</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>374</volume>(<issue>1770</issue>):<fpage>20180109</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2018.0109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30966891</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-27551938241269188"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glymour</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Social Epidemiology</source>. <edition>Second edition</edition>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-27551938241269188"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Diez Roux</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Social epidemiology: past, present, and future</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Public Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34982586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-27551938241269188"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crenshaw</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mapping the margins: intersectionality, identity politics, and violence against women of color</article-title>. <source>Stanford Law Review</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1299</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-27551938241269188"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hill Collins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bilge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Intersectionality</source>. <edition>2</edition><sup>nd</sup> ed. <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-27551938241269188"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tuck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decolonization is not a metaphor</article-title>. <source>Decolonization: Indigeneity, Education &#x00026; Society</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-27551938241269188"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Decolonizing Methodologies&#x0202f; Research and Indigenous Peoples</source>. <edition>Third edition</edition>. <publisher-name>Zed</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-27551938241269188"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measures of racism, sexism, heterosexism, and gender binarism for health equity research: from structural injustice to embodied harm-an ecosocial analysis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Public Health</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31765272</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-27551938241269188"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incorporating intersectionality theory into population health research methodology: challenges and the potential to advance health equity</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24704889</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-27551938241269188"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bowleg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>We're not all in this together: on COVID-19, intersectionality, and structural inequality</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>917</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32463703</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-27551938241269188"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cormack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paine</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Colonial histories, racism and health&#x02014;The experience of M&#x00101;ori and Indigenous peoples</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31171363</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-27551938241269188"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Diffey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ashleigh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decolonizing diabetes: the importance of an anti-racist and anti-colonial lens in Indigenous health</article-title>. <source>Canadian J Diabetes</source>. <year>2023</year>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcjd.2023.05.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-27551938241269188"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization, CSDH</collab>. <part-title>Closing the Gap in a Generation: Health Equity Through Action on the Social Determinants of Health</part-title>. In: <source>Final Report of the Commission on Social Determinants of Health</source>. <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-27551938241269188"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>PubMed</collab>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link> (accessed: September 27, 2023)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-27551938241269188"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>World Health Organization (WHO)</collab>. <comment>Social determinants of health. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/social-determinants-of-health#tab=tab_1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/health-topics/social-determinants-of-health#tab=tab_1</ext-link> (Accessed: March 23, 2024)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-27551938241269188"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Braveman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The Social Determinants of Health and Health Disparities</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-27551938241269188"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Just societies, health equity, and dignified lives: the PAHO Equity Commission</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>392</volume>:<fpage>2247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2250</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30262335</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-27551938241269188"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muntaner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Why social (political, economic, cultural, ecological) determinants of health? part 1: background of a contested construct</article-title>. <source>Int J Soc Det Health Health Serv</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-27551938241269188"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kickbusch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Addressing the interface of the political and commercial determinants of health</article-title>. <source>Health Promot Int</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23144264</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-27551938241269188"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schrecker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bambra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>How Politics Makes Us Sick: Neoliberal Epidemics</source>. <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan UK</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-27551938241269188"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dawes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The Political Determinants of Health</source>. <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press Books</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-27551938241269188"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Democracy and Population Health</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-27551938241269188"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The political economy of health: bringing political science in</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Pol Sci</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-27551938241269188"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fafard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Leeuw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Integrating Science and Politics for Public Health</source>. <publisher-name>Springer Int.</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-27551938241269188"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Wye</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Severe sociopolitical stressors and preterm births in New York City: 1 September 2015 to 31 August 2017</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30327451</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-27551938241269188"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Testa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanage</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relationship of political ideology of US federal and state elected officials and key COVID pandemic outcomes following vaccine rollout to adults: April 2021-March 2022</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg Health Am</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>100384</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2022.100384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36338898</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr47-27551938241269188"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Diderichsen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Beyond &#x02018;commercial determinants&#x02019;: shining a light on privatization and political drivers of health inequalities</article-title>. <source>Eur J Public Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>672</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34137787</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr48-27551938241269188"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daube</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Commercial determinants of health: future directions</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>401</volume>(<issue>10383</issue>):<comment>P1229</comment>&#x02013;<lpage>P1240</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr49-27551938241269188"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oreskes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The Big Myth: How American Business Taught Us to Loathe Government and Love the Free Market</source>. <publisher-name>Bloomsbury Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr50-27551938241269188"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ghebreyesus</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Achieving health for all requires action on the economic and commercial determinants of health</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>401</volume>(<issue>10383</issue>):<comment>P1137</comment>&#x02013;<lpage>P1139</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr51-27551938241269188"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breilh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Critical Epidemiology and the People&#x02019;s Health</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr52-27551938241269188"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>In Pursuit of Health Equity: A History of Latin American Social Medicine</source>. <publisher-name>Chapel Hill, NC University of North Carolina Press</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr53-27551938241269188"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sterling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <part-title>Allostasis: a new paradigm to explain arousal pathology</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reason</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Handbook of Life Stress, Cognition and Health</source>. <publisher-name>J. Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>1988</year>:<fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>649</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr54-27551938241269188"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sterling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>What Is Health?: Allostasis and the Evolution of Human Design</source>. <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr55-27551938241269188"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stellar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Stress and the individual: mechanisms leading to disease</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>2093</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8379800</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr56-27551938241269188"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Stress, adaptation, and disease: allostasis and allostatic load</article-title>. <source>Ann NY Acad Sci</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>840</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9629234</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr57-27551938241269188"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Web of Science</collab>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www-webofscience-com.ezp-prod1.hul.harvard.edu/wos/woscc/basic-search" ext-link-type="uri">https://www-webofscience-com.ezp-prod1.hul.harvard.edu/wos/woscc/basic-search</ext-link> (accessed: September 27, 2023)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr58-27551938241269188"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wemrell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merlo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mulinari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Homborg</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Contemporary epidemiology: a review of critical discussions within the discipline and a call for further dialogue with social theory</article-title>. <source>Sociol Compass</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr59-27551938241269188"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Arminjon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maulini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>In&#x000e9;galites de Sant&#x000e9;: Fondements Historiques et Enjeux Contemporains de l&#x02019;&#x000c9;pid&#x000e9;mologie Sociale</source>. <publisher-name>Georg &#x000e9;diteur</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr60-27551938241269188"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>History, biology, and health inequities: emergent embodied phenotypes &#x00026; the illustrative case of the breast cancer estrogen receptor</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23153126</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr61-27551938241269188"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brownson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Charting a future for epidemiologic training</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>458</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25976024</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr62-27551938241269188"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brownson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bensyl</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Applied epidemiology and public health: are we training the future generations appropriately?</article-title>
<source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28038933</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr63-27551938241269188"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durrheim</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olowokure</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Housen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Shaping applied epidemiology workforce training to strengthen emergency response: a global survey of applied epidemiologists, 2019-2020</article-title>. <source>Hum Resour Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>58</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12960-021-00603-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33926469</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr64-27551938241269188"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>STROBE</collab>. <comment>Strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.strobe-statement.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.strobe-statement.org/</ext-link> (Accessed: March 23, 2024)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr65-27551938241269188"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The Book of Why: The New Science of Cause and Effect</source>. <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr66-27551938241269188"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Data, design, and background knowledge in etiologic inference</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11338312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr67-27551938241269188"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>VanderWeele</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <part-title>Causal effects and natural laws: towards a conceptualization of causal counterfactuals for nonmanipulable exposures, with application to the effects of race and sex</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Berzuini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dawid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernardinelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Causality: Statistical Perspectives and Applications</source>. <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>:<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr68-27551938241269188"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Causal identification: a charge of epidemiology in danger of marginalization</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27237595</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr69-27551938241269188"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The tale wagged by the DAG: broadening the scope of causal inference and explanation for epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27694566</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr70-27551938241269188"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Invited commentary: what social epidemiology brings to the table-reconciling social epidemiology and causal inference</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>189</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31566211</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr71-27551938241269188"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Causality and The People&#x02019;s Health</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr72-27551938241269188"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Galea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Win-win: reconciling social epidemiology and causal inference</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>189</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31579911</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr73-27551938241269188"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>VanderWeele</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Invited commentary: Counterfactuals in social epidemiology-thinking outside of &#x0201c;the box&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>189</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31566208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr74-27551938241269188"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matthay</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glymour</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A graphical catalog of threats to validity: linking social science with epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>376</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31977593</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr75-27551938241269188"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majmundar</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>High and Rising Mortality Rates Among Working-Age Adults</source>. <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr76-27551938241269188"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Falling behind: The growing gap in life expectancy between the United States and other countries, 1933-2021</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>970</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>980</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37262403</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr77-27551938241269188"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Climate Change and the People&#x02019;s Health</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr78-27551938241269188"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Birn</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pillay</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holtz</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Textbook of Global Health</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr79-27551938241269188"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>The dawn of Structural One Health: a new science tracking disease emergence along circuits of capital</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25311784</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr80-27551938241269188"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buse</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oestreicher</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Public health guide to field developments linking ecosystems, environments and health in the Anthropocene</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29330164</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr81-27551938241269188"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macmillan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Navigating fundamental tensions towards a decolonial relational vision of planetary health</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<comment>e834</comment>&#x02013;<lpage>e841</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00197-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>