<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables v1.3 20210610//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats-oasis2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Microbiol Biol Educ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Microbiol Biol Educ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jmbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Microbiology &#x00026; Biology Education</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1935-7877</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1935-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11044616</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00005-24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jmbe.00005-24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jmbe.00005-24</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Tips and Tools</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sss-taxonomy"><compound-subject><compound-subject-part content-type="code">jmbe-teaching-climate-change</compound-subject-part><compound-subject-part content-type="label">Special Series: Teaching Climate Change</compound-subject-part></compound-subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>An environmental justice fictional case study for engaging non-majors in human biology</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3192-7824</contrib-id><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>John Jacob</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Conceptualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Data curation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Formal analysis" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal analysis</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Investigation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Methodology" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Project administration" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Resources" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/">Resources</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Software" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Validation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Visualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; original draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; review and editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review and editing</role><email>john_peters@hms.harvard.edu</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution>Curriculum Fellows Program, Department of Biological Chemistry and Molecular Pharmacology, Harvard Medical School</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Boston</city>, <state>Massachusetts</state>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><role>Editor</role><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name><aff><institution-wrap><institution>Universidad de Chile</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Santiago</city>, <country>Chile</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to John Jacob Peters, <email xlink:href="mailto:john_peters@hms.harvard.edu">john_peters@hms.harvard.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e00005-24</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date>
</history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024 Peters.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Peters.</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" start_date="2024-03-05"/><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="jmbe.00005-24.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="primary"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>The impacts of climate change are and will continue to be far-reaching, and environmental justice communities are disproportionately impacted due to environmental racism and related forms of oppression. Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education encourages that the connection between science and society be explicitly taught in science classrooms. Here, I describe a fictional case study where students decide how to allocate a budget at a non-profit organization tasked with mitigating environmental issues in a town that contains environmental justice communities. Students are each assigned a role in the community and must reach a consensus on their budget in small groups before the whole class votes on a consensus budget. Afterward, students perform a metacognitive activity that encourages them to reflect on the human health impacts of their decisions and how their role impacted their decision-making process. Quantitative and qualitative feedback from students shows that by the end of the course, students appreciate the importance of science literacy in understanding global issues and that they are able to connect environmental justice to their lives and coursework. This case study helps fill an unmet need in climate change education by allowing students to practice empathy in topics related to climate change and environmental justice.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>environmental racism</kwd><kwd>environmental justice</kwd><kwd>climate change</kwd><kwd>roleplaying</kwd><kwd>case study</kwd><kwd>metacognition</kwd></kwd-group><counts><count count="4" count-type="supplementary-material"/><count count-type="authors" count="1"/><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="15"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="3859"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Many non-biology majors are required to take a science course as part of a core curriculum, and engaging this group of students can be challenging, especially with worsening attitudes toward science by students (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). One solution for improving this attitude suggested by Vision and Change is to develop curricula with explicit connections drawn between science and society (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). This includes equipping students with the ability to understand global issues as well as understanding the societal context in which science is done. By increasing a student&#x02019;s sense of connectedness to course material, they could have better attitudes toward biology, would be better informed on global issues, and would be better citizens (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Climate change is one of the most pressing global issues, and climate anxiety is negatively impacting the mental health of young people, making this topic particularly relevant to undergraduates (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). While climate change affects us all, the impacts of climate change are disproportionately felt by marginalized groups. Environmental racism describes how some communities have been targeted to experience a disproportionate amount of pollution and environmental hazards via racist environmental policies. Environmental justice is a response to environmental racism and other forms of environmental inequities and is described by the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) as &#x0201c;the fair treatment and meaningful involvement of all people regardless of race, color, national origin, or income, with respect to the development, implementation, and enforcement of environmental laws, regulations, and policies&#x0201d; (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In other words, environmental justice aims to ameliorate the disparities experienced by marginalized groups, which in the context of environmental justice are called environmental justice communities (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Environmental justice communities are exposed to several environmental hazards including the urban heat island effect, which is the result of racist redlining policies in the United States and leads to an increased risk of heat-related illness (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), and drinking water contamination by PFAS (per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances) and microplastics pollution. These environmental hazards will be exacerbated by climate change. Urban heat islands are directly tied to global warming (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), water contamination is predicted to worsen as extreme weather and changes in the water cycle increase the introduction of toxins into the water supply (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), and plastics contribute to climate change through lifecycle emissions (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) and water and food chain pollution through microplastics (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Here, I used environmental racism and environmental justice as a connecting point between students&#x02019; lives, global challenges, and human biology.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Key concepts and their connection to climate change<xref rid="T1_FN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Term</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Definition</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Connection to climate change and/or human health</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Environmental racism</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The intentional or inadvertent oppression of individuals or communities through racist environmental policies.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Environmental racism makes it such that communities of color disproportionately experience the effects of climate change which leads to increased mortality in these communities.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Environmental justice</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A response to ameliorate the effects of environmental racism and other inequities in environmental policy, including inequities stemming from social class.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Environmental justice practices can lead to the improvement of health for individuals experiencing environmental racism and related forms of oppression.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Environmental justice communities</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Groups that have experienced inequities due to environmental policy.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">These groups are more likely to be exposed to environmental hazards which negatively impact human health.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urban heat island effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Describes how building materials that are used in urban areas absorb more heat leading to greater air temperatures (1&#x000b0;C&#x02013;4&#x000b0;C).</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The urban heat island effect leads to increased risk of heat-related illness and is exacerbated by global warming.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PFAS</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chemicals found in a range of household products including flame retardants and non-stick pans.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PFAS are associated with immune deficits, cancers, and developmental issues. Increased extreme weather caused by climate change has increased the spread of PFAS from contaminated sites.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Microplastics</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Small (~1 mm) particles formed from the shattering of plastics.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Microplastics have been implicated in hormonal dysfunction and cancer. Increased extreme weather caused by climate change has increased the escape of microplastics from dumps.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><label>
<sup>
<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>
</sup>
</label><p>Definitions of key concepts from the case study activity and their relationship to climate change and/or human health.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To address the need for activities that allow for authentic engagement with issues related to climate change and environmental justice, I designed a fictional case study as a formative assessment for a semester-long exploration of environmental racism and environmental justice in my human biology lecture course. The learning objectives for this activity were for students to be able to:</p><list list-type="order" id="list1"><list-item><p>Describe ways in which the environment impacts human health,</p></list-item><list-item><p>Develop their own perspectives on the relationships between government policies, race, and human health, and</p></list-item><list-item><p>Empathize with individuals who experience environmental racism and related injustices.</p></list-item></list><p>The case study required students to allocate a hypothetical budget at a non-profit to help address environmental hazards related to the urban heat island effect and water contamination by PFAS and microplastics. These societal issues are relevant to all students and are already considered in EPA policy (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). One of the challenges with teaching about environmental justice is that each student has experienced environmental racism differently in their lives. To encourage students to develop empathy (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) and to promote student engagement in the activity (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), students were assigned roles within the fictional community to play throughout the activity. After the activity, students completed a reflection activity to reinforce learning and consider how their experience and the experience of the character they were playing influenced their decision-making. Feedback from students at the end of the course demonstrates that students valued science literacy as useful for understanding global issues and found environmental justice to be relevant to their lives and coursework. This case study activity helps fill a gap in pedagogical tools for teaching climate change and environmental justice.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>PROCEDURE</title><p>The environmental justice case study described here was used as a formative assessment three-fourths through the semester of a 41-student human biology course for non-majors at Wellesley College after several class sessions relating to environmental justice and human physiology. Briefly, students were asked to role-play through a budgeting process where community members in a fictional town are tasked with allocating monies to resolve environmental hazards affecting both environmental justice communities and communities without this designation. Before the activity, students should be able to define environmental racism and environmental justice as well as describe the human health impacts of PFAS, microplastics, and the urban heat island effect (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for an overview of these topics and Supplemental Material 1 for PowerPoint slides covering these topics). Prior to class, I provided a description of the activity to students (Supplemental Material 2) which includes a spreadsheet that describes a fictional town and its struggles with environmental hazards. This spreadsheet also includes a list of potential solutions to these hazards of varying impact and cost (see references in Supplemental Material 2 for more information about PFAS and microplastics). The total of these mitigation strategies is over $85 million but students were only allowed to spend a $25 million budget, so therefore, the challenge of the activity is prioritizing changes that will have the greatest impact on the community. Interventions were binned into three levels, from level 1 to level 3, based on total cost (with level 1 being the least expensive).</p><p>To start class, I reviewed the details of the case, highlighting which communities are environmental justice communities (see <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> for details of the lesson timeline and Supplemental Material 3 for slides to use in class for the activity). I also provided students with a list of discussion norms and guidelines so each student would be empowered to participate to their fullest capabilities (see Supplemental Material 4 for example norms). Students worked in four-person activity groups that had been consistently used throughout the semester, and each student was randomly assigned one of four fictional roles within the community: (i) a pregnant woman living near a firefighting training facility, (ii) an elderly resident living in a community with PFAS contamination, (iii) a fisherman living in an industrial area, or (iv) an individual living near an abandoned mall in a relatively affluent area. As described in the case study, some of these individuals are from historically redlined neighborhoods that are composed of communities of color. These hypothetical individuals would have experienced a range of injustices and have different health risk factors (e.g., a pregnant woman is more vulnerable to environmental toxins), and so the challenge for students is to empathize with individuals who may have experienced environmental hazards in a different way from themselves. Each group was asked to develop a $25 million budget however they saw fit with no limitations on the number of remedial strategies used from each category, keeping in mind the role they were playing. Students had approximately 20 minutes to discuss the remediation options and reach a consensus within their groups. Once a group reached a consensus, they submitted their budget by using a Google Form to vote for or against each remediation option. If a simple majority of groups voted for an option, that option was approved and added to the class budget. At the end of voting, I summed the total cost of approved options within the activity spreadsheet. Depending on the allocated budget at this stage, students proposed motions to add items (if they were underbudget) or remove items (if they were overbudget), and these motions were voted on via a simple majority. With my class of 41 students, there were four proposed motions, and I allotted 2&#x02013;5 minutes for each motion for students to express opinions before voting. The final consensus-reaching step took approximately 20 minutes, and this process could be extended if desired.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Recommended timeline for lesson<xref rid="T2_FN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Activity</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimated time</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Notes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Preparation for class</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02003;Background content delivery</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Introductory lectures and/or activities on organ systems, environmental justice, and the impacts of urban heat islands, PFAS, and microplastics on human health</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 &#x02013; 5 class sessions</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The activity presented in this lesson plan was used as a formative assessment at the end of a series of classes. Students should have some familiarity with liver and kidney function. Additionally, students should be able to define environmental justice, urban heat islands, and microplastics as well as list a few impacts of each of these on human health.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02003;Students prepare for class</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Before class, provide the case to students and ask them to read it.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 minutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asking the students to familiarize themselves with the case allows for more time in class to be spent on discussions.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Class session</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02003;Introduce case study</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remind students the details of the case and answer any questions.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 minutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02003;Students reach consensus on budget in groups of four</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Students discuss and decide in their small groups which remediation strategies to fund.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 &#x02013; 30 minutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">During this time, the instructor should roam the class answering any questions. Make sure each group is making progress at a reasonable rate.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02003;Class reaches a consensus on budget</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Groups vote on which projects to fund.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 &#x02013; 30 minutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any clicker tool or forms tool can be used to collect votes. A simple show of hands could be a low-tech alternative. Once the first round of voting is finished, students can propose motions to add/remove budget items. If time is short, it is not essential that the budget is perfectly used. A potential follow-up task for students could be to repeat the budgeting process with a different budget size.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">After class session</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02003;Metacognitive activity</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Students complete the reflection questions listed in Supplemental Material 1.</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 &#x02013; 45 minutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">These questions should be completed by each individual. Answers can be discussed in the next class session if time permits.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1"><label>
<sup>
<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>
</sup>
</label><p>A description of background class sessions needed prior to this lesson as well as a timeline for this lesson.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>After the activity, I assigned students a metacognitive activity which included the following questions:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="list2"><list-item><p>How did you decide which projects to fund? What factors were most important to you?</p></list-item><list-item><p>What were the human health ramifications for the projects you funded? What about the projects you didn&#x02019;t fund?</p></list-item><list-item><p>What was challenging about playing your role? How did your role impact your way of thinking?</p></list-item></list><p>This reflection helped to reinforce the empathy practice students had in discussion, gave students a chance to compare their own personal experiences with environmental racism to that of their assigned role, and encouraged students to consider how they made difficult decisions. The assignment should take about 30 minutes to complete and can be given as homework. I graded the assignment for effortful completion (at least 250 words) and provided brief feedback to students who demonstrated misconceptions about the definitions of some of the key terms. If time allows, this reflection can be followed by a group discussion in the following class where students share their responses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s3"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Students responded well to the activity (Exemption from Brandeis University Human Research Protection Program: IRB Protocol #24117R-E Peters). At the end of the semester, student responses to Likert scale survey questions showed that students valued the importance of biological literacy in understanding global issues (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>); 37 of 40 students either agreed or strongly agreed with the statement, &#x0201c;I believe that biological literacy (understanding) is required for understanding important global issues.&#x0201d; Students also thought that course learning objectives associated with describing connections between the environment and human health (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>, top) and developing their own perspectives on environmental justice issues (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>, bottom) were extremely well met. Thirty-eight of 40 students thought the course learning objective, &#x0201c;Students will be able to describe ways in which the environment impacts human health,&#x0201d; was either well met or extremely well met, and 37 of 40 students thought the course learning objective, &#x0201c;Students will be able to develop their own perspectives on the relationships between government policies, race, and human health,&#x0201d; was either well met or extremely well met.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1"><label>Fig 1</label><caption><p>Anonymous survey data from students. (<bold>A</bold>) At the end of the course, a majority of students agreed that biological literacy is important for understanding global issues (strongly agree = 24, agree = 13, neither agree nor disagree = 3, disagree = 0, strongly disagree = 0). (<bold>B</bold>) At the end of the course, a majority of students thought the course learning objective of, &#x0201c;Students will be able to describe ways in which the environment impacts human health,&#x0201d; was extremely well met (top; extremely well met = 24, well met = 14, somewhat met = 2, slightly met = 0, not at all met = 0). A majority of students also thought the course learning objective of, &#x0201c;Students will be able to develop their own perspectives on the relationship between government policies, race, and human health,&#x0201d; was extremely well met (top; extremely well met = 22, well met = 15, somewhat met = 3, slightly met = 0, not at all met = 0).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmbe.00005-24.f001" position="float"/></fig><p>Additionally, students performed a reflection activity at the end of the course (3 weeks after the case study activity) answering the following questions:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="list3"><list-item><p>Over the break, someone may ask you what you learned in biology class. What one thing would you share with them?</p></list-item><list-item><p>In what ways were the concepts you learned in BISC 109 related to topics from other classes you&#x02019;ve taken at Wellesley?</p></list-item></list><p>A thematic analysis of the 82 answers to these questions (all 41 students responded to each of the questions) showed that 41 of the responses mentioned environmental justice or environmental racism, and that 31 of the 41 students mentioned one of these topics in at least one of their answers. Twenty-two responses discussed how these topics connect to their other coursework (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, &#x0201c;Connectedness&#x0201d;), fourteen discussed how it was surprising or helpful to talk about these topics in a science course (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, &#x0201c;Novel&#x0201d;), and nine discussed implications for human health (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, &#x0201c;Human Health&#x0201d;). One limitation of this feedback is that it was collected 3 weeks after the case study activity; regardless, the feedback is suggestive of students responding well to a climate change and environmental justice curriculum. In sum, the described case study aligns well with the Vision and Change goal of increasing connectedness between students&#x02019; lives and their coursework. The topics in the fictional case study left a lasting and meaningful impact on students as measured by quantitative and qualitative student feedback.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F2"><label>Fig 2</label><caption><p>Thematic analysis of course metacognitive activity. Heat map showing the three most common themes from thematic analysis of two questions from an end-of-course metacognitive activity (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 41 students and each student responded to both questions for a total of 82 answers). Forty-one of the 82 answers discussed environmental justice or environmental racism, and the 34 that belonged to at least one of the three most common themes are displayed (each column represents a student response). Of those, 22 discussed how the material connected to their other coursework, 14 discussed the novelty of the topic in a science course, and nine discussed implications for human health.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmbe.00005-24.f002" position="float"/></fig></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>I would like to thank Dr. Anja Brandon for her help reviewing the policy recommendations in this activity. I would also like to acknowledge the Curriculum Fellows Program at Harvard Medical School for its support.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s4-1"><title>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL</title><p specific-use="print-only">The following material is available online at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/jmbe.00005-24" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1128/jmbe.00005-24</ext-link>.</p><supplementary-material id="SuF1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jmbe.00005-24.SuF1</object-id><label>Supplemental Material 1: Background PowerPoint Slides</label><caption><title>jmbe.00005-24-s0001.pptx</title><p>This PowerPoint contains slides that cover relevant background topics like environmental racism, environmental justice, environmental justice communities, urban heat islands, PFAS, and microplastics.</p></caption><media xlink:href="jmbe.00005-24-s0001.pptx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SuF2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jmbe.00005-24.SuF2</object-id><label>Supplemental Material 2: Activity spreadsheet with budget</label><caption><title>jmbe.00005-24-s0002.xlsx</title><p>This spreadsheet has all the instructions for the activity, including a table with the budget that students will use for the activity. The budget has formulas so students can keep track of their budget decisions as they reach a consensus. This PowerPoint contains slides that describe the scenario in the case study and provide a map of the fictional town in the case study.</p></caption><media xlink:href="jmbe.00005-24-s0002.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SuF3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jmbe.00005-24.SuF3</object-id><label>Supplemental Material 3: Activity PowerPoint slides</label><caption><title>jmbe.00005-24-s0003.ppt</title><p>This PowerPoint contains slides that describe the scenario in the case study and provide a map of the fictional town in the case study.</p></caption><media xlink:href="jmbe.00005-24-s0003.ppt"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SuF4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jmbe.00005-24.SuF4</object-id><label>Supplemental Material 4: Example community standards for discussion</label><caption><title>jmbe.00005-24-s0004.docx</title><p>This document contains community standards made for discussion. This was a collaborative effort with students.</p></caption><media xlink:href="jmbe.00005-24-s0004.docx"/></supplementary-material><p specific-use="online-only">ASM does not own the copyrights to Supplemental Material that may be linked to, or accessed through, an article. The authors have granted ASM a non-exclusive, world-wide license to publish the Supplemental Material files. Please contact the corresponding author directly for reuse. </p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Osborne</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Attitudes towards science: a review of the literature and its implications</article-title>. <source>Int J Sci Educ</source>
<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1079</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0950069032000032199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="report">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>AAAS</collab></person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Vision and change in undergraduate biology education: a call to action</article-title>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Partin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haney</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Worch</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Underwood</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nurnberger-Haag</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheuermann</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Midden</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Yes I can: the contributions of motivation and attitudes on course performance among biology nonmajors</article-title>. <source>J Coll Sci Teach</source>
<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>L&#x000e9;ger-Goodes</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malboeuf-Hurtubise</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mastine</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;reux</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paradis</surname>
<given-names>P-O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camden</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Eco-anxiety in children: a scoping review of the mental health impacts of the awareness of climate change</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<elocation-id>872544</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.872544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35959069</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hickman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marks</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pihkala</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewandowski</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayall</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wray</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mellor</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Susteren</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Climate anxiety in children and young people and their beliefs about government responses to climate change: a global survey</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e873</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00278-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895496</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>US EPA O</collab></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Environmental justice</article-title>. <source>Collections and lists</source>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/environmentaljustice" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.epa.gov/environmentaljustice</ext-link>. <comment>Retrieved</comment>
<date-in-citation>8 Aug 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheriff</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chakraborty</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manya</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Disproportionate exposure to urban heat island intensity across major US cities</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>2721</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-22799-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34035248</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heaviside</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macintyre</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vardoulakis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>The urban heat island: implications for health in a changing environment</article-title>. <source>Curr Environ Health Rep</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40572-017-0150-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28695487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schiedek</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sundelin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Readman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macdonald</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>Interactions between climate change and contaminants</article-title>. <source>Mar Pollut Bull</source>
<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1856</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2007.09.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17963794</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rykhus</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Satellite imagery maps hurricane Katrina-induced flooding and oil slicks</article-title>. <source>EoS Transactions</source>
<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2005EO410003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Strategies to reduce the global carbon footprint of plastics</article-title>. <source>Nat Clim Chang</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41558-019-0459-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Love</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rochman</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <article-title>Microplastics in seafood and the implications for human health</article-title>. <source>Curr Environ Health Rep</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40572-018-0206-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30116998</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>EG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>A review of microplastics in table salt, drinking water, and air: direct human exposure</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Technol</source>
<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>3740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3751</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.9b04535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32119774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Poorman</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <article-title>Biography and role playing: fostering empathy in abnormal psychology</article-title>. <source>Teach Psychol</source>
<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15328023TOP2901_08</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Role-play and student engagement: reflections from the classroom</article-title>. <source>Teach High Educ</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13562517.2015.1020778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>