<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11517537</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckae144.2272</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckae144.2272</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Poster Displays</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>DX. Poster display: Sexual and gender minority health</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Operationalizing Macro-Level Structural Sexual Minority Stigma: A Scoping Review of the Literature</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>van der Star</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Psychology, San Diego State University, San Diego</institution>, CA, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><xref rid="ckae144.2272-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--avanderstar@sdsu.edu--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garetti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Psychology, San Diego State University, San Diego</institution>, CA, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckae144.2272-cor1">Contact: <email>avanderstar@sdsu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-10-28"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><issue-title>17th European Public Health Conference 2024 Sailing the Waves of European Public Health: Exploring a Sea of Innovation Lisbon, Portugal 12&#x02013;15 November 2024</issue-title><elocation-id>ckae144.2272</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ckae144.2272.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s9123"><title>Background</title><p>Structural stigma, including discriminatory laws, inequitable policies, and negative attitudes, has been conceptualized as the general societal climate and institutional conditions that shape sexual minorities&#x02019; lives, mental, and physical health. While multidimensional indices have been used globally, U.S.-based studies have largely relied on single indicators (e.g., a law or policy; presence of resources). This scoping review aimed to identify structural sexual minority stigma indicators relevant to the U.S. context, to inform comprehensive, multidimensional future operationalizations.</p></sec><sec id="s9124"><title>Methods</title><p>Systematic database searches in PubMed, PsycINFO, and JSTOR, and snowball techniques resulted in 70 articles. After duplicate deletion and abstract review, 25 unique indices were long-listed relevant to structural sexual minority stigma at country or state level (i.e., macro level). School (district) and county (i.e., exo level) indicators were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="s9125"><title>Results</title><p>From the long-listed indices, a total of 112 legal and policy indicators were narrowed down to relevant 33 macro-level indicators and grouped across seven domains: criminal justice, hate crime protections, non-discrimination, religious refusal, relationship recognition, parenting, and youth laws and policies. Two different quantifications of population attitudes were identified that aggregated social and policy opinions across states regarding sexual minority adoption, hate crimes, health benefits, labor and housing, public speaking or teaching, marriage, sodomy, and civil unions.</p></sec><sec id="s9126"><title>Discussion</title><p>While a large variety of legal and attitudinal indicators was identified, few U.S.-based studies used multidimensional operationalizations (e.g., law, policy, opinion) needed to reduce risk of confounding bias through population-attitudes-to-law/policy backdoor pathways. To further advance the science on structural sexual minority stigma and health globally, future studies may benefit from multidimensional approaches.</p></sec><sec id="s9127"><title>Key messages</title><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;With many legal and attitudinal indicators identified, few studies used multidimensional operationalizations (e.g., law, policy, opinion) needed to reduce risk of confounding bias.</p><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;To further advance the science on structural sexual minority stigma and health globally, future studies may benefit from multidimensional approaches.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>