<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11516501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckae144.282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckae144.282</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Parallel Programme</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>5.D. Scientific session: Climate Change and Inequalities: Addressing Intersections and Impacts</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>5.D. Scientific session: Climate Change and Inequalities: Addressing Intersections and Impacts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>Organised by: EUPHA-ENV, -LAW</collab></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><collab>Chair persons: Marija Jevtic (EUPHA-ENV), Brigit Toebes (Netherlands)</collab><xref rid="ckae144.282-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--vlatka.m@gmail.com--></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckae144.282-cor1">Contact: <email>vlatka.m@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-10-28"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><issue-title>17th European Public Health Conference 2024 Sailing the Waves of European Public Health: Exploring a Sea of Innovation Lisbon, Portugal 12&#x02013;15 November 2024</issue-title><elocation-id>ckae144.282</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ckae144.282.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s845"><title>&#x02002;</title><p>Climate change poses one of the greatest challenges of our time, with far-reaching implications for environmental sustainability, social equity, and economic development. In recent years, growing attention has been paid to the intersecting dynamics between climate change and inequalities, recognizing that vulnerable populations are disproportionately affected by climate-related risks and impacts. This workshop aims to explore the multifaceted relationship between climate change and inequalities and examine the root causes of disparities. In this workshop we will explore intersectionality by examining how climate change intersects with various forms of inequality, including socio-economic and health status, gender, age, indigenous status, and geography, shaping differential vulnerabilities and experiences of climate impacts. This workshop aims to facilitate dialogue, knowledge exchange, and collaboration among public health researchers and professionals. We offer a unique opportunity to deepen our understanding of the complex interplay between climate change and inequalities, shedding light on overlooked aspects [?]. By bringing together diverse perspectives and expertise, the workshop aims to generate actionable insights and solutions that promote social justice, sustainability, and human rights in the face of climate change. The presentations in this workshop are thematically interconnected, addressing key aspects of climate change and inequalities from multiple angles. Topics include: Gender and climate justice, Climate change adaptation equity, Legal perspectives on climate change and inequalities and Climate Change Impacts on Respiratory Health. In conclusion, this workshop serves as a critical platform for advancing understanding, dialogue, and action on the intersection of climate change and inequalities.</p></sec><sec id="s846"><title>Key messages</title><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Climate change interacts with socio-economic, health, gender, age, indigenous status, and geography, influencing vulnerabilities and impacts.</p><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Vulnerable populations bear a disproportionate burden of climate change effects, including individuals with pre-existing lung conditions and children.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>