<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Nurs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Nurs</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Nursing</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6955</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10999088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1898</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12912-024-01898-w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The impact of perceived organizational justice on young nurses&#x02019; job performance: a chain mediating role of organizational climate and job embeddedness</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Jiamei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Xindi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Xiaojia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Guangli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chaoran</given-names></name><address><email>kfccr@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/003xyzq10</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256922.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9139 560X</institution-id><institution>Institute of Nursing and Health, School of Nursing and Health, </institution><institution>Henan University, </institution></institution-wrap>475004 Kaifeng, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/003xyzq10</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256922.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9139 560X</institution-id><institution>Institute of Business Administration, School of Business, </institution><institution>Henan University, </institution></institution-wrap>475004 Kaifeng, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>231</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The level of nurses&#x02019; job performance has always been of great concern, which not only represents the level of nursing service quality but is also closely related to patients&#x02019; treatment and prognosis. The aim of this study was to analyze the relationship between perceived organizational justice and job performance and to explore the mediating role of organizational climate and job embeddedness among young Chinese nurses.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A cross-sectional survey of 1136 young nurses was conducted between March and May 2023 using convenience sampling. Data were collected using the Job Performance Scale, Organizational Justice Assessment Scale, Nursing Organizational Climate Scale, and Job Embeddedness Scale, and the resulting data were analyzed using SPSS 25.0 and AMOS 26.0.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">There was a significant positive correlation between job performance and perceived organizational justice (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.477, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), organizational climate (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.500, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), and job embeddedness (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.476, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). Organizational climate and job embeddedness acted as chain mediators between perceived organizational justice and job performance. The total effect of perceived organizational justice on job performance (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.513) consisted of a direct effect (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.311) as well as an indirect effect (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.202) mediated through organizational climate and job embeddedness, with the mediating effect accounting for 39.38% of the total effect.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Organizational climate and job embeddedness play a chain mediating role between perceived organizational justice and job performance, so hospital managers should pay attention to the level of perceived organizational justice among young nurses, and develop a series of targeted measures to improve their job performance using organizational climate and job embeddedness as entry points.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Perceived organizational justice</kwd><kwd>Job performance</kwd><kwd>Organizational climate</kwd><kwd>Job embeddedness</kwd><kwd>Young nurse</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Henan University</institution></funding-source><award-id>HDXJJG2020-25</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">The World Health Organization (WHO) predicts that the global elderly population will be twice as large in 2050 as it was in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Therefore, comprehensive and even long-term person-centered care must be provided to the elderly population in order to maintain their health status and cope with global demographic changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Nurses, as professionals in the healthcare system, not only play an important role in the health education of patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], but are also the main providers of long-term care services to patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. It can be argued that a sufficient number of nurses and a high level of quality of care are important for us to cope with demographic changes. However, the number of nurses is in a continuous shortage due to various reasons, such as the COVID-19 epidemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Therefore, how to solve the shortage of nurses has become a hot research topic among scholars. Previous quantitative and qualitative studies have shown that there is a significant negative correlation between nurses&#x02019; job performance and intention to leave [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Wang et al.&#x02019;s study also showed that job performance plays an important role in decreasing nurses&#x02019; intention to leave, that is, job nurses with higher performance tend to have lower turnover intention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In addition, young nurses are more likely to be maladjusted to their nursing roles and thus have turnover intentions than older nurses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Buerhaus et al.&#x02019;s study also showed that the number of nurses under the age of 35 declined by 4% between February 2020 and June 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. There is no doubt that the loss of young nurses will exacerbate the lack of nursing staff. Therefore, it is necessary to study the job performance of young nurses in order to reduce the turnover of nursing personnel and improve the quality of nursing services so as to better cope with demographic changes. (Note: According to China&#x02019;s relevant policies and regulations, young nurses in this study refer to nurses between the ages of 18 and 35)</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Background</title><p id="Par6">The concept of job performance is commonly found in management and refers to the scalable actions, behaviors, and outcomes of employees to achieve organizational goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Nurses&#x02019; job performance refers to the contributions and achievements of nurses in their clinical work using their knowledge and skills [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. A high level of job performance not only implies a high quality of nursing care for nurses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], but is also closely related to patient treatment and recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Therefore, exploring the influencing factors of young nurses&#x02019; job performance is essential to improve the quality of nursing services and reduce the turnover of young nurses. In fact, a large number of studies, both nationally and internationally, have shown that, in addition to general demographic information such as age, gender, job title, and salary level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], leadership style, resilience, job satisfaction, and even the use of social media have a significant impact on job performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">As an important predictor of job performance, organizational justice refers to the extent to which an organization adheres to norms reflecting fairness and appropriateness in its decision-making process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Previous studies have shown that employees with higher levels of perceived organizational justice are more likely to take the initiative to improve their job performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Yu&#x02019;s study showed that there is a significant positive correlation between organizational justice and job performance among nurses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Beatriz&#x02019;s study also showed that the higher level of perceived organizational justice among employees is associated with higher level of job performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. However, there are often unexplained discrepancies between the results of different studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], and most previous studies have focused on hotel employees [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], teachers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], and physician populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], with young nurses&#x02019; research being more limited. Therefore, it is necessary to explore the mediating mechanisms by which perceived organizational justice affects job performance in order to gain a deeper understanding and improve the job performance of young nurses.</p><p id="Par8">Organizational climate refers to a perception or feeling that members of an organization have about the characteristics of the environment in which the organization is located, which usually originates from the individual organization members&#x02019; psychological perceptions of the work environment in which they are located [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Huang pointed out that there is a positive correlation between employees&#x02019; organizational justice and organizational climate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Su&#x02019;s findings also showed that perceived organizational justice is an important influence on the organizational climate of young nurses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In addition, social information processing theory suggests that organizational climate changes employees&#x02019; attitudes, behaviors, and beliefs at work, which in turn has an impact on employee performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Previous studies have shown a significant positive correlation between organizational climate and job performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Hanife Tiryaki Sen and Aytolan Yildirim&#x02019;s study also showed that a supportive organizational climate has a positive effect on the job performance of young nurses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Therefore, this study proposes Hypothesis 1: Organizational climate is a mediating variable between perceived organizational justice and job performance of young nurses.</p><p id="Par9">Job embeddedness refers to the closeness of the network of relationships formed between an individual and all work-related situations, and it encapsulates the organizationally relevant factors that make an employee remain on the job, which causes the employee to be attached or embedded in the job they are in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Nurses&#x02019; job embeddedness, on the other hand, refers to all the positive factors that make nursing managers do their best to keep nursing staff in their nursing positions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Lee&#x02019;s study showed that organizational justice had a significant positive effect on the job embeddedness of clinical young nurses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Kim&#x02019;s study also found that young nurses with higher perceptions of organizational justice usually had higher job embeddedness compared to those with lower perceptions of organizational justice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. In addition, many previous studies have confirmed a significant positive correlation between job embeddedness and job performance among nursing staff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Therefore, we proposed Hypothesis 2: Job embeddedness is a mediating variable between perceived organizational justice and job performance of young nurses.</p><p id="Par10">Resource Conservation Theory suggests that a high degree of job embeddedness is a state of resourcefulness, and employees with a high degree of job embeddedness will not only show greater self-confidence and positive work attitudes in the face of work challenges, but will also improve their job performance by enhancing their critical skill reserves and problem solving abilities through various means [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Similarly, Liu&#x02019;s study found that young nurses with high levels of job embeddedness were more willing to improve their performance for the benefit of the organization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Furthermore, Hashim&#x02019;s study has confirmed a significant positive correlation between organizational climate and job embeddedness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. In light of this, we proposed Hypothesis 3: Job embeddedness is a mediating variable between organizational climate and young nurses&#x02019; job performance.</p><p id="Par11">In conclusion, although there have been studies on the relationship between perceived organizational justice and job performance, there is still a lack of research on the mechanisms between the two relationships, and very limited research on the young nurse population. Therefore, this study aimed to explore the effects of perceived organizational fairness on young nurses&#x02019; job performance and to test the mediating role of organizational climate and job embeddedness, with a view to providing ideas and guidance for research and interventions on job performance management for young nurses. The conceptual framework of this study is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par12">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Conceptual Framework</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12912_2024_1898_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e396"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par13">This study conducted a cross-sectional survey from March to May 2023 to examine the relationship between perceived organizational justice, job embeddedness, organizational climate and job performance among young nurses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Participants</title><p id="Par14">Participants in this study were drawn from nurses in six hospitals in Henan Province, China. Inclusion criteria were (a) aged between 18 and 35 years old; and (b) possessing a certificate of nursing practice. Exclusion criteria were (a) nurses in advanced training; (b) nurses on vacation during the survey period.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Procedure</title><p id="Par15">Convenience sampling method was used. The research team used a paper version of the questionnaire, which was collected face-to-face with the help of the hospital administrators. Prior to the start of the survey, participants were briefed about the purpose and significance of the study and assured that the data collected would be used for research purposes only. Participants were given the option to participate in the survey at their own discretion and to opt out at any time during the survey. We distributed 1,300 questionnaires, and 1,200 were eventually returned, with a return rate of 92.31%. After excluding 64 invalid questionnaires, 1136 valid questionnaires were recovered, with a valid recovery rate of 87.38%.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Measures</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Demographic characteristics</title><p id="Par16">Demographic characteristics include age, gender, marital status, hospital grade (Tertiary, Secondary or below), educational background (Junior college or below, Bachelor&#x02019;s, Master&#x02019;s or above), whether the head nurse (Yes, No), professional title (Nurse, Senior nurse, Nurse-in-charge, Deputy chief nurse or above), And monthly income (&#x0003c;&#x02009;4,000RMB, 4000&#x0223c;7000, 7000&#x0223c;10,000, &#x0003e; 10,000) etc.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Job performance</title><p id="Par17">The Job Performance Scale developed by Van Scotter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] and adapted by Yu De-Cheng (1996) was used to measure the job performance of young nurses. The scale consists of two dimensions, task performance (5 items) and contextual performance (6 items), with a total of 11 items. The Likert 5-point scale was used, with &#x0201c;1&#x0201d; indicating &#x0201c;not at all&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;5&#x0201d; indicating &#x0201c;fully&#x0201d;. The higher the score, the better the performance of young nurses. The Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.918 and in this study the Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.962.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Perceived organizational justice</title><p id="Par18">The perceived organizational justice of young nurses was assessed with organizational justice scale. Which compiled by Colquitt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] and translated by Yu Jingfen in 2022, included four dimensions: distributive justice (4 items), procedural justice (7 items), interpersonal justice (4 items) and informational justice (5 items), a total of 20 items. Likert 5 rating scale was used, ranging from &#x0201c;Completely disagree&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;Completely agree&#x0201d; from 1 to 5. The higher the score, the higher the perceived organizational justice of the young nurses. The Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.910 and in this study the Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.912.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Organizational climate</title><p id="Par19">The Nursing Organizational Climate Scale developed by He [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] was used. The scale consists of 24 items in four dimensions: equitable support behavior (10 items), collegial behavior (5 items), interpersonal climate behavior (4 items), and intimate and aggressive climate behavior (5 items). The Likert 5-point scale was used, with scores ranging from 1 to 5 on a scale from &#x0201c;very non-conforming&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;very conforming&#x0201d;, with higher scores indicating better organizational climate. The Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.927 and in this study the Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.976.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Job embeddedness</title><p id="Par20">The job embeddedness scale developed by Crossley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] and translated by Mei Hua (2014) was used. The scale is unidimensional, with 7 items. A 5-point Likert scale was used, ranging from &#x0201c;1&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;5&#x0201d; for &#x0201c;not at all&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;perfectly&#x0201d;. The question &#x0201c;It is easy for me to leave this organization&#x0201d; was reverse scored. The higher the scale score, the higher the degree of job embeddedness of the young nurses. The Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.890 and in this study the Cronbach&#x02019;s coefficient for this scale was 0.827.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par21">We used SPSS 25.0 and AMOS 26.0 for data analysis. First, descriptive statistics (frequencies, percentages, means, standard deviations, etc.) were used to measure participants&#x02019; demographic characteristics and job performance, perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, and job embeddedness. Second, we used Pearson correlation analysis to examine the relationship between the four variables of job performance, perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, and job embeddedness. Finally, the chained mediation model was tested using AMOS 26.0. Where perceived organizational justice is the independent variable and job performance is the dependent variable, both organizational climate and job embeddedness are mediating variables, and gender is a covariate in this model. In addition, to investigate the effect of perceived organizational justice on job performance, we performed bias-corrected percentile bootstrapping with a 95% confidence interval calculated from a bootstrap sample of 5000. <italic>P</italic> -values were two-tailed and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>The demographic characteristics of the participants</title><p id="Par22">Of the 1136 participants, 73.70% were female, 26.30% were male, more than 50% were aged 18&#x02013;24, and 77.90% of the young nurses were single. More than half of the young nurses have a bachelor&#x02019;s degree (67.30%), most of them work in tertiary hospitals (71.40%), and most of them have worked for less than 5 years (84.25%). Fewer young nurses work in pediatrics (6.90%), emergency departments (7.70%), and intensive care units (5.5%). The title of the participants was mostly &#x02018;nurse&#x02019; (65.50%), and very few young nurses (6.50%) were head nurses. More than half (55.1%) of the young nurses had a contract relationship with the hospital, and more than 80% of the young nurses had a monthly income of less than 7,000 yuan. See Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> for details.</p><p id="Par23">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1136)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variables</th><th align="left"/><th align="left">N</th><th align="left">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Gender</td><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">299</td><td align="left">26.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">837</td><td align="left">73.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Educational background</td><td align="left">Junior college or below</td><td align="left">234</td><td align="left">20.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Bachelor&#x02019;s</td><td align="left">764</td><td align="left">67.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Master&#x02019;s or above</td><td align="left">138</td><td align="left">12.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Years</td><td align="left">18&#x0223c;24</td><td align="left">668</td><td align="left">58.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">25&#x0223c;29</td><td align="left">321</td><td align="left">28.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">30&#x0223c;35</td><td align="left">147</td><td align="left">12.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Marital status</td><td align="left">Single</td><td align="left">885</td><td align="left">77.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Married</td><td align="left">241</td><td align="left">21.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Divorced or widowed</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hospital level</td><td align="left">Tertiary</td><td align="left">811</td><td align="left">71.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Secondary or below</td><td align="left">325</td><td align="left">28.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Head nurse?</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">6.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1062</td><td align="left">93.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Professional title</td><td align="left">Nurse</td><td align="left">744</td><td align="left">65.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Senior nurse</td><td align="left">257</td><td align="left">22.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Nurse-in-charge</td><td align="left">91</td><td align="left">8.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Deputy chief nurse or above</td><td align="left">44</td><td align="left">3.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Departments</td><td align="left">Internal medicine</td><td align="left">329</td><td align="left">29.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Surgery</td><td align="left">264</td><td align="left">23.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Obstetrics and gynecology</td><td align="left">119</td><td align="left">10.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Pediatric</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">6.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Emergency</td><td align="left">88</td><td align="left">7.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Intensive care unit</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">5.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Others</td><td align="left">195</td><td align="left">17.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Labor and personnel relations</td><td align="left">Formal establishment</td><td align="left">237</td><td align="left">20.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Personnel agency</td><td align="left">273</td><td align="left">24.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Contract system</td><td align="left">626</td><td align="left">55.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Years of working</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;1</td><td align="left">474</td><td align="left">41.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">1&#x02013;5</td><td align="left">483</td><td align="left">42.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">6&#x02013;10</td><td align="left">133</td><td align="left">11.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x0003e;&#x02009;10</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">4.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Monthly income</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;4000</td><td align="left">467</td><td align="left">41.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">4000&#x0223c;7000</td><td align="left">448</td><td align="left">39.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">7000&#x0223c;10,000</td><td align="left">140</td><td align="left">12.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x0003e;&#x02009;10,000</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">7.13</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Pearson&#x02019;s correlation analysis</title><p id="Par24">The results of the mean, standard deviation and correlation coefficients of each variable in this study are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. The scores for job performance, perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, and job embeddedness were 41.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.69, 72.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.48, 91.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;16.96, and 23.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.77, respectively. In addition, Pearson&#x02019;s correlation analysis found a positive correlation between job performance and perceived organizational justice (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.477, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), organizational climate (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.500, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) and job embeddedness (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.476, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). There was an association between perceived organizational justice and organizational climate (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.488, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) and job embeddedness (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.425, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). Furthermore, there was a significant positive correlation between organizational climate and work embeddedness (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.699, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01).</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation Analysis of job performance, perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, and job embeddedness (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1136)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">JP</th><th align="left">POJ</th><th align="left">OC</th><th align="left">JE</th><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">Standard deviation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">JP</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">41.12</td><td align="left">9.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left">POJ</td><td align="left">0.477**</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">72.53</td><td align="left">12.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left">OC</td><td align="left">0.500**</td><td align="left">0.488**</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">91.48</td><td align="left">16.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JE</td><td align="left">0.476**</td><td align="left">0.425**</td><td align="left">0.699**</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">23.56</td><td align="left">4.77</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>JP, job performance; POJ, perceived organizational justice; OC, organizational climate; JE, job embeddedness. ** <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (Two tailed).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Mediating effect analysis</title><p id="Par26">In this study, after using AMOS 26.0 to test for mediating effects and incorporating perceived organizational justice, job performance, organizational climate, and job embeddedness into the structural equation model analysis, the model fit indices were &#x003c7;2/df&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.583 (&#x0003c;&#x02009;5.0), GFI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.974 (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.90), CFI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.989 (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.90), AGFI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.959 (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.90), TLI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.985 (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.90), IFI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.989 (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.90), RMSEA&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.048 (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.08), indicating a good model fit.</p><p id="Par27">As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, perceived organizational justice significantly and positively predicted job performance (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.31, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), organizational climate (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.51, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), and job embeddedness (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.11, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) of young nurses. Organizational climate was a significant positive predictor of job performance (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.23, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and job embeddedness (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.65, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). Also, job embeddedness significantly and positively predicted job performance (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.19, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).</p><p id="Par28">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Path analysis diagram of perceived organizational justice, job performance, organizational climate, and job embeddedness. DJ, Distributive justice; PJ, Procedural justice; IntJ, Interpersonal justice; InfJ, Informational justice; POJ, perceived organizational justice; ESB, Equitable Support Behavior; CB, Collegial behavior; ICB, Interpersonal Climate Behavior; IAA, Intimate and Aggressive Atmosphere; OC, organizational climate; JP, job performance; TP, Task performance; CP, Contextual performance; JE, job embeddedness</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12912_2024_1898_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e998"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par29">To verify the mediating effect of organizational climate and job embeddedness between perceived organizational justice and job performance, we used the Bootstrap method with percentile bias correction. The results showed a significant mediating effect of organizational climate and job embeddedness, with a total indirect effect value of 0.202, accounting for 39.38% of the total effect (0.513). Specifically, the mediating effects in this study included three paths. First, the coefficient of the indirect effect path of perceived organizational justice through organizational climate on job performance was 0.119 (Bootstrap 95% CI: 0.081, 0.161). Second, the path of indirect effect of perceived organizational justice on job performance through job embeddedness was 0.021 (Bootstrap 95% CI: 0.010, 0.035). Third, the indirect path of perceived organizational justice through organizational climate, job embeddedness on job performance was 0.062 (Bootstrap 95% CI: 0.036, 0.091). Details are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par30">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Total, direct, and indirect effects of perceived organizational justice on job performance (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1136)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Effects</th><th align="left">Paths</th><th align="left">Effect</th><th align="left">Bootstrap SE</th><th align="left">Bootstrapping 95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Total effect</td><td align="left">POJ &#x02192; JP</td><td align="left">0.513</td><td align="left">0.029</td><td align="left">0.453 to 0.568</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Direct effect</td><td align="left">POJ &#x02192; JP</td><td align="left">0.311</td><td align="left">0.033</td><td align="left">0.248 to 0.375</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indirect effect</td><td align="left">POJ&#x02192;OC&#x02192;JP</td><td align="left">0.119</td><td align="left">0.021</td><td align="left">0.081 to 0.161</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">POJ&#x02192;JE&#x02192;JP</td><td align="left">0.021</td><td align="left">0.006</td><td align="left">0.010 to 0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">POJ&#x02192;OC&#x02192;JE&#x02192;JP</td><td align="left">0.062</td><td align="left">0.014</td><td align="left">0.036 to 0.091</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total indirect effect</td><td align="left">Total indirect effect</td><td align="left">0.202</td><td align="left">0.021</td><td align="left">0.164 to 0.247</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>JP, job performance; POJ, perceived organizational justice; OC, organizational climate; JE, job embeddedness. SE, standard error; CI, confidence interval.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par31">This study investigated the job performance of young nurses. The relationships between perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, job embeddedness, and job performance were explored, and a chain mediation model was constructed.</p><p id="Par32">We found that there is a significant positive relationship between perceived organizational justice and young nurses&#x02019; job performance, and the higher the level of perceived organizational justice of young nurses, the higher the level of their job performance, which is consistent with the results of a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The result also reveals that we should create a fair and just working environment for young nurses, for example, hospital management staff should focus on communication with young nurses to achieve procedural fairness and distributive fairness, etc., in order to improve their sense of organizational fairness.</p><p id="Par33">This study demonstrated that organizational climate is a mediating variable between young nurses&#x02019; perceived organizational justice and job performance, confirming Hypothesis 1. Young nurses with a high level of perceived organizational justice will have a more positive organizational climate, which will not only lead to greater satisfaction with their work but also to a greater willingness to comply with organizational rules and regulations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], resulting in higher motivation and work engagement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], which in turn leads to higher levels of job performance. Therefore, hospitals should consider more from the perspective of young nurses, increase the openness and transparency of management, and provide young nurses with channels to participate in the management of the organization so as to improve their sense of organizational justice. In addition, the head nurses of each department should strengthen the internal communication of the department, carry out diversified group activities to enhance the collective consciousness and organizational identity of young nurses, and create a positive organizational atmosphere, so as to achieve the purpose of improving the job performance of young nurses.</p><p id="Par34">The results of this study confirmed that job embeddedness is a mediating variable between perceived organizational justice and young nurses&#x02019; job performance, validating Hypothesis 2. The level of job embeddedness of young nurses increases with the level of perceived organizational justice, which is consistent with the results of previous studies on other populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. And the higher the level of job embeddedness, the closer the young nurses are connected to their colleagues and the hospital [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], which facilitates the enhancement of their work performance through teamwork. Therefore, hospital management should pay attention to the dual role of perceived organizational justice and job embeddedness, not only to create a fair and just working environment for young nurses but also to pay attention to their career development, provide young nurses with diversified training opportunities and promotion paths, link young nurses&#x02019; individual career development goals with the hospital&#x02019;s development goals, and stimulate their motivation to deepen the young nurses&#x02019; job embedding level.</p><p id="Par35">This study also found that job embeddedness is a mediating variable between organizational climate and job performance among young nurses, and Hypothesis 3 was confirmed. This may be due to the fact that a good organizational climate creates a sense of belonging and irreplaceability within young nurses towards the hospital [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], and these feelings deepen an individual&#x02019;s job embeddedness, which enhances their intrinsic motivation to work and increases their motivation and work efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>], which ultimately manifests itself in high levels of individual job performance. Therefore, it is necessary for hospital administrators to deepen young nurses&#x02019; connection with their colleagues and units, help them set career goals that are consistent with the direction of the hospital, and provide them with appropriate material and psychological rewards.</p><p id="Par36">In addition, this study found that perceived organizational justice can have an impact on young nurses&#x02019; job performance through the chain-mediated effects of organizational climate and job embeddedness. This result suggests that young nurses with high levels of perceived organizational justice have more positive perceptions of the hospital and organizational climate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] and are more inclined to develop stronger ties with their colleagues, leaders, and the hospital [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], which can contribute to enhancing their job satisfaction and work motivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] and improve job performance. On the contrary, young nurses who perceive a low level of organizational justice will be dissatisfied with the atmosphere of the work environment in which they live [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], which may make them resistant to establishing harmonious relationships with other nurses and the organization, which is detrimental to the improvement of job performance.</p><sec id="Sec19"><title>Relevance of clinical practice</title><p id="Par37">As the backbone of the nursing workforce, young nurses are prone to burnout when faced with heavy clinical nursing work, leading to a decline in the quality of nursing services, and in severe cases, even the intention to leave or leave the profession. However, the global demand for nursing services is increasing. Therefore, it is particularly important to improve the job performance of young nurses. In order to improve the job performance of young nurses, we give some suggestions with the results of this study.</p><p id="Par38">First of all, for nursing managers, it is necessary to establish a scientific performance appraisal system to make a scientific and accurate assessment of the performance of young nurses. It is also necessary to develop good communication feedback mechanisms, strengthen communication with young nurses, and focus on their needs. On this basis, managers should strive to ensure that procedures are fair, involve young nurses in the processing process, and empower them to participate more in decision-making. For example, when developing a remuneration or promotion system, the views and recommendations of young nurses should be fully taken into account, and their sense of involvement in the development of procedures should be enhanced, thereby enhancing their perception of organizational justice.</p><p id="Par39">Second, hospitals can provide a supportive working atmosphere for young nurses by improving the working environment and providing employee benefits. Each department should also hold regular group activities to cultivate the spirit of cooperation among young nurses, so that they can obtain positive emotional experiences from group cooperation, which is conducive to making young nurses perceive a more harmonious and positive organizational atmosphere. In addition, hospitals should pay attention to the cultivation of young nurses&#x02019; professional identity, regularly carry out relevant courses and training, and also recognize and encourage the performance of young nurses, help them to make good career planning, so that young nurses can make clear the path of their career development.</p><p id="Par40">Finally, the whole society should give more respect and recognition to nurses and the nursing profession, so as to deepen the job embedded level of young nurses. In a word, in actual clinical management, leaders should assess the perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, and work embeddedness of young nurses in a timely manner, and develop targeted intervention programs to improve the performance of young nurses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par41">This study has some limitations. Firstly, the subjects of this study are all young nurses in Henan Province, so the results may not be generalizable, and in the future, we can select young nurses from different regions to conduct more studies. Secondly, we only used the method of self-filling questionnaires to collect data, and the results are subjective, so there may be common method bias. In the future, we can try to use different data collection methods to reduce bias and make the research results closer to the real situation. Finally, this study only reveals the effect of perceived organizational justice on job performance and the mediating role of organizational climate and job embeddedness, and in the future, the mediating mechanism of other variables between the two can be studied in depth, in order to further enrich the model of perceived organizational justice affecting job performance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par42">This study investigated perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, job embeddedness, and job performance of selected young nurses in Henan Province. In order to explore the process by which perceived organizational justice affects young nurses&#x02019; job performance, a chain mediation model was developed. The results of the study showed that organizational climate and job embeddedness played the role of chain mediators between perceived organizational justice and job performance of young nurses, and the model &#x02018;perceived organizational justice&#x02192;organizational climate&#x02192;job embeddedness&#x02192;job performance of young nurses&#x02019; was verified. Therefore, hospital administrators should take targeted interventions to improve young nurses&#x02019; perceived organizational justice, organizational climate, and job embeddedness to improve young nurses&#x02019; job performance.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Jiamei Song and Xindi Shi share first authorship.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to express our sincere gratitude to Henan University for its financial support and to all the nurses who participated in this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JS, XS: Conceptualization, Data collection, Data analysis, Writing original draft. JS, XS, XZ: Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing original draft. CC, GL: Supervision, Writing review and editing. And all authors approved the final manuscript for submission.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was sponsored by the Key Project of Undergraduate Teaching Reform Research and Practice of Henan University (Grant Number: HDXJJG2020-25), Research on the Status Quo and Cultivation Mechanism of Social and Emotional Ability of Henan Adolescents (Grant Number: SKL-2022-55).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated and analysed during the current study are not publicly available but are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar6"><title>Ethical considerations</title><p id="Par43">We obtained approval from the Ethics Committee of Henan University School of Nursing and Health Sciences (ID Number: HUSOM 2022&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;375).</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par44">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par45">No conflict of interest has been declared by the authors.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. (2022). Ageing and health. Available from: URL: [Accessed 18 March 2023]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/ageing-and-health">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/ageing-and-health</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cacchione</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>World Health Organization leads the 2021 to 2030-Decade of healthy ageing</article-title><source>Clin Nurs Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/10547738211065790</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34872368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34872368</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khazhymurat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paiyzkhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khriyenko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seilova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baisanova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuntuganova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health education competence: an investigation of the health education knowledge, skills and attitudes of nurses in Kazakhstan</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Pract</source><year>2023</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>103586</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nepr.2023.103586</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 36868160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36868160</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Promoting health through nurse-led healthy conversations</article-title><source>Nurs Standard (Royal Coll Nurs (Great Britain): 1987)</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7748/ns.2023.e11912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dass</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Deber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forecasting staffing needs for Ontario&#x02019;s Long-Term Care Sector</article-title><source>Healthc Policy = Politiques de sante</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><issue>SP</issue><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12927/hcpol.2022.26852</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35848558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35848558</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tham</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Danuaji</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating Psychological Differences between Nurses and other Health Care workers from the Asia-Pacific Region during the early phase of COVID-19: machine Learning Approach</article-title><source>JMIR Nurs</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e32647</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/32647</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35648464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35648464</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Work stress and perceived organisational support on young Korean nurses&#x02019; care for COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Collegian</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colegn.2022.05.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35669229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35669229</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen CW, Pao LS, Lei H. The examination of job separation tendency of nursing staff in the first public-private joint-venture hospital in Taiwan: a multiple mediation model of job satisfaction and job performance. Humanit Social Sci Commun. 2022;9(1). 10.1057/s41599-022-01456-2.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yesilyurt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Baykal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Goktepe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nurse managers&#x02019; views on why nurses leave their jobs: a qualitative study</article-title><source>Collegian</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colegn.2021.08.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang C-Y, Lin Y-K, Chen IH, Wang C-S, Peters K, Lin S-H. (2023). Mediating effect of job performance between emotional intelligence and turnover intentions among hospital nurses during the COVID-19 pandemic: a path analysis. <italic>Collegian (Royal College of Nursing, Australia)</italic>. 10.1016/j.colegn.2022.09.006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zheng SF, Yang LL, Zhou N, Zhu HX. New nurses&#x02019; experience during a two year transition period to clinical practice: A phenomenological study. Nurse Educ Today. 2023;121. 10.1016/j.nedt.2022.105682.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buerhaus</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Staiger</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Donelan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nurse employment during the First Fifteen months of the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Health Aff</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2021.01289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viswesvaran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ones</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives on models of job performance</article-title><source>Int J Selection Assess</source><year>2000</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1468-2389.00151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A literature review of job performance of nurses</article-title><source>J Nurs Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between proactive personality and job performance of Chinese nurses: the Mediating Role of Competency and Work Engagement</article-title><source>Front Psychol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>533293</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.533293</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34113274?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34113274</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Professional identity and emotional labour affect the relationship between perceived organisational justice and job performance among Chinese hospital nurses</article-title><source>J Nurs Adm Manag</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1252</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jonm.13608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adamska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosakowska-Berezecka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Konarski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gender perspectives on self-censorship in organizations: the role of management position, procedural justice and organizational climate</article-title><source>Eur J Social Psychol</source><year>2022</year><volume>52</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejsp.2838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu D, Yang X, Zhang CY, Zhang WL, Tang QR, Xie YJ, Shi L. Impact of job satisfaction and Social Support on Job Performance among Primary Care providers in Northeast China: a cross-sectional study. Front Public Health. 2022;10. 10.3389/fpubh.2022.884955.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thu</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Loan</surname><given-names>LTM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quynh</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Employees&#x02019; job satisfaction, job performance and their relationship during the COVID-19 pandemic in Vietnam</article-title><source>Organizatsionnaya Psikologiya</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17323/2312-5942-2022-12-2-38-55</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chi HK, Vu TV, Nguyen HV, Truong TH. How financial and non-financial rewards moderate the relationships between transformational leadership, job satisfaction, and job performance. Cogent Bus Manage. 2023;10(1). 10.1080/23311975.2023.2173850.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of different purposes of social media usage on employees&#x02019; job performance</article-title><source>Acta Physiol Sinica</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1260</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3724/sp.J.1041.2021.01260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruble</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Relationship between Pharmacist Resilience, Burnout, and Job Performance</article-title><source>J Pharm Pract</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/08971900231164886</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 36938593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36938593</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Colquitt JA, Rodell JB. (2015). Measuring Justice and Fairness.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abuelhassan</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>AlGassim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How organizational justice in the hospitality industry influences proactive customer service performance through general self-efficacy</article-title><source>Int J Contemp Hospitality Manage</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2579</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/ijchm-10-2021-1238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sora</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;ge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Caballer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Job insecurity and performance: the mediating role of Organizational Justice in terms of type of contract</article-title><source>Psicothema</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7334/psicothema2020.205</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33453740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33453740</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pattnaik S, Tripathy SK. The effect of organizational justice on employee performance in the Indian Public Sector Units: the role of organizational identification. Benchmarking-an Int J. 10.1108/bij-08-2021-0508.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupp</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Employee idiosyncratic deals (i-deals) and organizational justice: the role of individual job performance and coworkers&#x02019; i-deals</article-title><source>Personnel Rev</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/pr-05-2021-0335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalyzing employee OCBE in Tour companies: Charismatic Leadership, Organizational Justice, and pro-environmental behaviors</article-title><source>J Hospitality Tourism Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1096348018817582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hyder S, Malik MI, Hussain S, Tasneem M, Kaleem M, Saqib A. Organizational justice and employee in-role performance nexus: a dual theory perspective. Cogent Bus Manage. 2022;9(1). 10.1080/23311975.2022.2124602.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zmud</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral intention formation in knowledge sharing: examining the roles of extrinsic motivators, social-psychological forces, and organizational climate</article-title><source>MIS Q</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/25148669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of Organizational Justice on Organizational Climate and Organizational Performance in Ecology Industry</article-title><source>Ekoloji</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><issue>107</issue><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of organizational justice on young nurses&#x02019; turnover intention: the mediating roles of organizational climate and emotional labour</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Pract</source><year>2023</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>103723</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nepr.2023.103723</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 37651958?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37651958</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salancik</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A social information processing approach to job attitudes and task design</article-title><source>Adm Sci Q</source><year>1978</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2392563</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10307892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10307892</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pradoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Haryono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahyuningsih</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of work stress, organizational climate, and improving employee performance in the implementation of work from home</article-title><source>Work-a J Prev Assess Rehabilitation</source><year>2022</year><volume>71</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/wor-210678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang T, Luo KF, Geng ZY, Zhang S. (2022, Aug 03&#x02013;06). <italic>Impact of Organizational Justice on Knowledge Employees&#x02019; Creativity: Mediated by Organizational Commitment</italic> Paper presented at the 16th International Conference on Management Science and Engineering Management (ICMSEM), Ankara, TURKEY.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Yildirim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between nurses&#x02019; perceived organisational, supervisor and co-worker support, psychological well-being and job performance</article-title><source>J Pak Med Assoc</source><year>2023</year><volume>73</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.47391/jpma.6594</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 36932758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36932758</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtom</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sablynski</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Erez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why people stay: using job embeddedness to predict voluntary turnover</article-title><source>Acad Manag J</source><year>2001</year><volume>44</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1102</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3069391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The level and determinants of job embeddedness among nurses in the anesthesiology department</article-title><source>J Nurs Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of nurse practice environment and Organizational Justice on Job Embeddedness in the small and medium Sized Hospital nurses</article-title><source>J Digit Convergence</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14400/jdc.2017.15.12.369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0c774;&#x0c724;&#x0c2e0;</surname></name><name><surname>Heeyoung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of Positive Psychological Capital and Organizational Justice on Job Embeddedness of Clinical nurses</article-title><source>J Korean Acad Nurs Adm</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11111/jkana.2022.28.3.228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakeel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujtaba</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of Psychological Capital on performance of Public Hospital nurses: the mediated role of Job Embeddedness</article-title><source>Public Organ Rev</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11115-021-00521-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influences of Emotional Intelligence, Self-leadership, and job embeddedness on nursing work performance</article-title><source>Korean J Health Service Manage</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12811/kshsm.2018.12.2.051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yom</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of self-leadership and social support in the relationship between Job Embeddedness and Job Performance among General Hospital nurses</article-title><source>J Korean Acad Nurs Adm</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11111/jkana.2015.21.4.375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hobfoll</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation of resources. A new attempt at conceptualizing stress</article-title><source>Am Psychol</source><year>1989</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037//0003-066x.44.3.513</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2648906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2648906</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Job embeddedness: consequences and theoretical explanation</article-title><source>Adv Psychol Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>906</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3724/SP.J.1042.2021.00906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu TT, Wang W, Shan GY, Zhang YJ, Liu J, Li YX. Job Crafting and Nurses&#x02019; Presenteeism: The Effects of Job Embeddedness and Job Irreplaceability. Front Public Health. 2022;10. 10.3389/fpubh.2022.930083.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hashim H, Ishak NA, Hilmi ZAG. (2014, Dec 26&#x02013;28). <italic>Influence of Organizational Climate on Disabled Job Embeddedness</italic> Paper presented at the Annual Serial Landmark International Conference on Quality of Life(ASLI QoL) / ABRA International Conference on Quality of Life (AQoL), Istanbul Tech Univ, Istanbul, TURKEY.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>VanScotter</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Motowidlo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpersonal facilitation and job dedication as separate facets of contextual performance</article-title><source>J Appl Psychol</source><year>1996</year><volume>81</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.81.5.525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colquitt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the dimensionality of organizational justice: a construct validation of a measure</article-title><source>J Appl Psychol</source><year>2001</year><volume>86</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037//0021-9010.86.3.386</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11419799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11419799</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">He Liping LQ, Jing M. (2011). Development of the Nursing Organizational Climate Scale and its reliability and validity test. Chin J Mod Nurs(08), 873&#x02013;5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crossley</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jex</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnfield</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a global measure of job embeddedness and integration into a traditional model of voluntary turnover</article-title><source>J Appl Psychol</source><year>2007</year><volume>92</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.92.4.1031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17638463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17638463</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mediating effects of nursing organizational climate on the relationships between empathy and burnout among clinical nurses</article-title><source>J Adv Nurs</source><year>2020</year><volume>76</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3048</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jan.14525</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32885476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32885476</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myint</surname><given-names>NNS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunaviktikul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A contemporary understanding of organizational climate in healthcare setting: a concept analysis</article-title><source>Nurs Forum</source><year>2021</year><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nuf.12513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020958</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorji</surname><given-names>MAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahebi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaghoubi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherati</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhianfar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating the link between organisational justice, positive organisational behaviour and productivity in emergency nurses</article-title><source>Emerg Nurse: J RCN Accid Emerg Nurs Association</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7748/en.2022.e2134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matagi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baluku</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age, job involvement and job satisfaction as predictors of job performance among local government employees in Uganda</article-title><source>J Organizational Effectiveness-People Perform</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/joepp-06-2020-0099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jongsik</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hee-Sup</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships among organizational justice, job embeddedness, self-efficacy, organization citizenship behavior and turnover intention in a hotel organization</article-title><source>Korean J Hospitality Tourism(KJHT)</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24992/kjht.2017.01.26.01.89</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LDL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do embedded employees voice more?</article-title><source>Personnel Rev</source><year>2019</year><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>824</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/pr-05-2017-0150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>mi</surname><given-names>Hs</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of job embeddedness on turnover intention of nurses in Long Term Care hospitals: the mediating effect of nursing work environment</article-title><source>J Korean Acad Nurs Adm</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11111/jkana.2020.26.5.439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nurses&#x02019; voice behaviour: the influence of humble leadership, affective commitment and job embeddedness in China</article-title><source>J Nurs Adm Manag</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1603</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jonm.13306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al Hassan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Almowallad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Motary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alshmemri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alghabbashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of Organisational Climate on nurses&#x02019; commitment at Public hospitals in Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>J Pharm Res Int</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><issue>55A</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9734/JPRI/2021/v33i55A33807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lu GL, Liang YP, Ding YM, Tang HS, Zhang YM, Huang HT, Chen CR. Nurses&#x02019; feeling trusted and knowledge hiding: The role of psychological safety, felt obligation and traditionality. Front Psychol. 2022;13. 10.3389/fpsyg.2022.1034882.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Funaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in the effects of organisational climate on burnout according to nurses&#x02019; level of experience</article-title><source>J Nurs Adm Manag</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jonm.13137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">El-Gazar HE, Abdelhafez S, Zoromba MA. Effects of the areas of worklife on job embeddedness: a national cross-sectional study among Egyptian nurses. Bmc Nurs. 2022;21(1). 10.1186/s12912-022-01107-6.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bakeer HM, Nassar RA, Sweelam RKM. (2021). Investigating organisational justice and job satisfaction as perceived by nurses, and its relationship to organizational citizenship behaviour. <italic>Nursing management (Harrow, London, England: 1994), 28</italic>(5), 19&#x02013;25. 10.7748/nm.2021.e1973.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Akter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Iktidar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of workplace bullying and burnout on job satisfaction among Bangladeshi nurses: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e13162</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e13162</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 36755612?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36755612</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashish</surname><given-names>EAA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nurses&#x02019; perception of organizational justice and its relationship to their workplace deviance</article-title><source>Nurs Ethics</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0969733019834978</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30982425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30982425</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>