<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-3-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats-oasis2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Justice</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ Justice</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">env</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Justice (Print)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1939-4071</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1937-5174</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Mary Ann Liebert, Inc., publishers</publisher-name><publisher-loc>140 Huguenot Street, 3rd Floor New Rochelle, NY 10801 USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10880503</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1089/env.2022.0048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/env.2022.0048</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Centering Equity in the Nation's Weather, Water, and Climate Services</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">TRIPATI ET AL.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">CENTERING EQUITY IN WEATHER, WATER, AND CLIMATE</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tripati</surname><given-names>Aradhna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="corr1" ref-type="corresp"/><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1695-1754</contrib-id></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>Marshall</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Vernon</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>Kyle Powys</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2689-691X</contrib-id></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>David-Chavez</surname><given-names>Dominique M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hosbey</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trujillo-Falc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Joseph E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>Brandon</given-names></name><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hence</surname><given-names>Deanna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carlis</surname><given-names>DaNa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Vankita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff12" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>William L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff13" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geller</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff14" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name><xref rid="aff15" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Glackin</surname><given-names>Mary</given-names></name><xref rid="aff16" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><aff id="aff1">Dr. Aradhna Tripati is Professor at Department of Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences, Center for Diverse Leadership in Science, Institute of the Environment and Sustainability, UCLA, Los Angeles, California, USA; Department of Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences, American Indian Studies Center, UCLA, Los Angeles, California, USA.</aff><aff id="aff2">Prof. Marshall Shepherd is Professor at Department of Geography, University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia, USA.</aff><aff id="aff3">Prof. Vernon Morris is Professor at New College of School of Mathematical and Natural Sciences in the New College of New College for Interdisciplinary Arts and Sciences, Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona, USA.</aff><aff id="aff4">Dr. Karen Andrade is a Fellow at the Center for Diverse Leadership in Science, UCLA, Los Angeles, California, USA.</aff><aff id="aff5">Dr. Kyle Powys Whyte is Professor at School for Environment and Sustainability, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA.</aff><aff id="aff6">Prof. Dominique M. David-Chavez is an Assistant Professor at Department of Forest and Rangeland Stewardship, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, Colorado, USA.</aff><aff id="aff7">Dr. Justin Hosbey is an Assistant Professor of City and Regional Planning at UC Berkeley, Berkeley, California, USA.</aff><aff id="aff8">Mr. Joseph E. Trujillo-Falc&#x000f3;n is a Graduate Research Assistant at the Cooperative Institute for Severe and High-Impact Weather Research and Operations, NOAA National Severe Storms Laboratory, Norman, Oklahoma, USA.</aff><aff id="aff9">Dr. Brandon Hunter is a Fellow at the Center for Diverse Leadership in Science, UCLA, Los Angeles, California, USA; Postdoctoral Scholar at the Department of Earth and Environmental Engineering, Columbia University, New York City, New York, USA; Center for Rural Enterprise and Environmental Justice, Lowndes County, Alabama, USA.</aff><aff id="aff10">Prof. Deanna Hence is an Assistant Professor at Department of Atmospheric Sciences, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, Illinois, USA.</aff><aff id="aff11">Dr. DaNa Carlis is the Director of the National Severe Storms Laboratory, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, Norman, Oklahoma, USA, USA.</aff><aff id="aff12">Dr. Vankita Brown is a Senior Advisor for Equity at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and a Research Social Scientist at the National Weather Service, Silver Spring, Maryland, USA.</aff><aff id="aff13">Dr. William L. Parker is the Meteorologist in Charge at National Weather Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, Jackson, Mississippi, USA.</aff><aff id="aff14">Dr. Andrew Geller is the Senior Scientist and Executive Lead for Lead (Pb) and Environmental Justice Research at Office of Research and Development, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina, USA.</aff><aff id="aff15">Mr. Alex Reich is a Program Officer at the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, Washington, District of Columbia, USA.</aff><aff id="aff16">Dr. Mary Glackin was the Senior Vice President of Science and Forecast Operations at The Weather Company, IBM, Andover, Massachusetts, USA.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn84" fn-type="other"><p>An earlier draft of this article was posted as a preprint at EarthArXiv (<uri xlink:href="http://eartharxiv.org/repository/object/3332/download/6665/">http://eartharxiv.org/repository/object/3332/download/6665/</uri>).</p></fn><corresp id="corr1">Address correspondence to: Aradhna Tripati, Department of Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences, Institute of the Environment and Sustainability, Department of Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences, American Indian Studies Center, Center for Diverse Leadership in Science, UCLA 595 Charles Young Drive East, Los Angeles, CA 90095-0001, USA <email>atripati@g.ucla.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="fn"><p><sup>i</sup>ORCID ID (<uri xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1695-1754">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1695-1754</uri>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="fn"><p><sup>ii</sup>ORCID ID (<uri xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2689-691X">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2689-691X</uri>).</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year><string-date>February 2024</string-date></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Aradhna Tripati <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Aradhna Tripati et al., </copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons License [CC-BY] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="env.2022.0048.pdf"/><abstract><p>Water, weather, and climate affect everyone. However, their impacts on various communities can be very different based on who has access to essential services and environmental knowledge. Structural discrimination, including racism and other forms of privileging and exclusion, affects people's lives and health, with ripples across all sectors of society. In the United States, the need to equitably provide weather, water, and climate services is uplifted by the Justice40 Initiative (Executive Order 14008), which mandates 40% of the benefits of certain federal climate and clean energy investments flow to disadvantaged communities. To effectively provide such services while centering equity, systemic reform is required. Reform is imperative given increasing weather-related disasters, public health impacts of climate change, and disparities in infrastructure, vulnerabilities, and outcomes. It is imperative that those with positional authority and resources manifest responsibility through (1) recognition, inclusion, and prioritization of community expertise; (2) the development of a stronger and more representative and equitable workforce; (3) communication about climate risk in equitable, relevant, timely, and culturally responsive ways; and (4) the development and implementation of new models of relationships between communities and the academic sector.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Justice40</kwd><kwd>climate justice</kwd><kwd>weather</kwd><kwd>water</kwd><kwd>environmental justice</kwd><kwd>climate change</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s001"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>In an interview at COP26 (26th UN Climate Change Conference of the Parties), when asked what climate change looked and felt like, Brianna Fruean, a young Pacific Islander who advocates for climate justice on behalf of her fellow Samoans, described the smell of thick mud she had to wade through and shovel out of houses after a flood.<sup><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></sup> The multiple human dimensions of climate change are inescapable. <italic toggle="yes">Anthropogenic climate change</italic> is the disruptive response of our planet's weather and water cycles to human activity and development&#x02014;largely emissions and land surface changes&#x02014;that directly and indirectly affect energy balance in the Earth System.</p><p>Yet, what that definition does not name are the tangible and inequitably distributed consequences of this anthropogenic problem. <italic toggle="yes">Climate injustice</italic> refers to the role of structural discrimination in saddling communities of color and low-income communities with disproportionately high burdens of the harmful risks and impacts of climate change.<sup><xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref></sup> In the United States and around the world, when climate disasters occur&#x02014;whether extreme weather leading to floods, tornadoes, hurricanes, fires, or droughts&#x02014;black, Indigenous, and other people of color (BIPOC) and frontline communities are disproportionately vulnerable to environmental and climate injustices.<sup><xref rid="fn3 fn4 fn5 fn6 fn7 fn8 fn9 fn10" ref-type="fn">3&#x02013;10</xref></sup></p><p>Structural racism and segregation are intrinsically linked to this vulnerability.<sup><xref rid="fn11" ref-type="fn">11</xref></sup> Although no one is insulated from the climate crisis, BIPOC communities are most at risk. As equity gaps increase, skewed vulnerabilities and repeated disasters can destabilize families and communities for generations. For example, high concentrations of BIPOC communities live in flood-prone and/or water-poor areas.<sup><xref rid="fn12" ref-type="fn">12</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn13" ref-type="fn">13</xref></sup> Racist U.S. Federal urban planning policies, including redlining, have resulted in a lack of trees and parks in areas of BIPOC communities, contributing to urban heat islands and higher mortality rates during heat waves.<sup><xref rid="fn14" ref-type="fn">14</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn15" ref-type="fn">15</xref></sup></p><p>The nation's weather, water, and climate services, such as disaster risk management, community outreach, water resource assessment, swift and accurate information dissemination, hazard monitoring, education, workforce preparation, and more, play a key role in communities' well-being. Yet BIPOC communities often experience delays in response to climate emergencies and receive fewer resources for recovery,<sup><xref rid="fn4" ref-type="fn">4</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn16" ref-type="fn">16</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn17" ref-type="fn">17</xref></sup> which can cascade into disasters of greater and longer magnitude, and intersect with other crises. For example, in Louisiana's &#x0201c;Cancer Alley,&#x0201d; delayed emergency response in the wake of Hurricane Ida further increased residents' risk of exposure to carcinogenic materials and increased transmission of coronavirus through seeking the same limited shelter accommodations.<sup><xref rid="fn18" ref-type="fn">18</xref></sup></p><p>In the southeast United States, the National Weather Service (NWS) radar networks leave wide swaths of black communities without radar coverage.<sup><xref rid="fn19" ref-type="fn">19</xref></sup> During and after Hurricane Katrina and other events, inequitable and racist policies and practices associated with risk management, service management, disaster response, and redevelopment contributed to reduced community resiliency and entrenching of health and wealth disparities through the loss of home, family, networks, and educational access and reform.<sup><xref rid="fn10" ref-type="fn">10</xref></sup> Loss of relationship to place due to migration and forced displacement can cascade into a loss of culture, sovereignty (particularly for Indigenous communities), and autonomy, and into threats to civil liberties.<sup><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn20" ref-type="fn">20</xref></sup></p><p>Another dimension of this problem is that there is little representation from BIPOC communities in the geosciences.<sup><xref rid="fn21 fn22 fn23" ref-type="fn">21&#x02013;23</xref></sup> Less than 10% of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA's) senior executive service members or NWS employees are from BIPOC communities, and 91% of NWS meteorologists and hydrologists are white based on March 2022 data from the NWS Equal Opportunity and Diversity Management Division. In contrast, over 42% of the U.S. population is nonwhite.<sup><xref rid="fn24" ref-type="fn">24</xref></sup></p><p>This inadequate representation of BIPOC scientists means there is a lack of workers who understand the issues most relevant to BIPOC communities, which cascades into the development of inequitable policies, services, outreach, planning, and resource deployments that devalue and deprioritize the needs of BIPOC communities.<sup><xref rid="fn25 fn26 fn27" ref-type="fn">25&#x02013;27</xref></sup> These concerns are further heightened given the strengths of Indigenous and local knowledges for climate adaptation and resilience, and for safeguarding biodiversity.<sup><xref rid="fn28" ref-type="fn">28</xref></sup> Both the Intergovermental Panel on Climate Change<sup><xref rid="fn29" ref-type="fn">29</xref></sup> and the White House<sup><xref rid="fn30" ref-type="fn">30</xref></sup> have affirmed that Indigenous peoples hold diverse Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) knowledges that can guide natural resources stewardship, water management, fire management, soil and water health, disaster response, and decision making.</p><p>It is critical to center equity if we are going to address intersecting climate, environmental, and social justice crises. Although these topics and related issues have been highlighted for decades, there has been insufficient action. In light of Executive Order 14008 and the Justice40 Initiative,<sup><xref rid="fn31" ref-type="fn">31</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn32" ref-type="fn">32</xref></sup> this comment is intended as a resource and call to action for the services and science community.</p></sec><sec id="s002"><title>&#x0201c;THE FIERCE URGENCY OF NOW&#x0201d;</title><p>Given the current and future importance of the nation's weather, water, and climate services to the well-being of communities, it is imperative to apply an equity and justice framework to ensure these services serve everyone. The moral and public health imperatives of the climate crisis, and the continued human, social, and environmental costs of inaction, drive, to paraphrase Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.,<sup><xref rid="fn33" ref-type="fn">33</xref></sup> a &#x0201c;fierce urgency of now&#x0201d; around equitable and just action. We have a mandate to accelerate society's response to climate change, while simultaneously moving beyond good intentions and toward action.</p><p>The nation's services have an essential role to play in dismantling discriminatory structures and the building of new systems, informed by community knowledge. Without urgent and targeted action in response to the accelerating rate of climate change and extreme weather events, we will continue to see a widening of disparities, and we will continue to see inadequate, unequal, and unjust responses. The <italic toggle="yes">No Time for Silence</italic> call to action<sup><xref rid="fn34" ref-type="fn">34</xref></sup> cast down a gauntlet for change and laid out a road map to move beyond recognizing the injustices, to taking specific actions, and has been endorsed by professional geoscience societies and departments representing &#x0003e;60,000 geoscientists.</p></sec><sec id="s003"><title>CENTERING EQUITY, NOT JUST DIVERSITY OR INCLUSION</title><p>The nation's weather, water, and climate services need equity-minded leaders who have resources, positional authority, and institutional agency to heed and respond to multiple calls for change.<sup><xref rid="fn34 fn35 fn36 fn37" ref-type="fn">34&#x02013;37</xref></sup> Correcting the effects of systemic discrimination requires changing cultures and sharing power, not solely increasing diversity that often results in bringing BIPOC individuals into hostile environments. Equity must be built in from the outset by identifying clear indicators and metrics with which to evaluate justice and equity outcomes<sup><xref rid="fn38 fn39 fn40" ref-type="fn">38&#x02013;40</xref></sup> (i.e., who will benefit and how, who will be included in decision making).</p><p>Environmental justice efforts must go beyond identifying disproportionate impacts, and directly engage with why certain communities were discriminated against.<sup><xref rid="fn41" ref-type="fn">41</xref></sup> Equity in and of itself cannot be adequately addressed without recognizing and addressing systemic racism as a root cause of environmental inequities, and go beyond colorblind ideological frameworks and explicitly address institutionalized racism.<sup><xref rid="fn42" ref-type="fn">42</xref></sup></p><p>Smart and intentional action planning can move levers of change in transformative ways. If the issues are taken to heart by forward-thinking leaders across the policy-making, corporate, academic, philanthropic, and nonprofit sectors, major steps can be taken to address these issues in the geosciences in the next decade. Leaders can drive institutional change now by modifying practices; bylaws; and local, state, and federal policies, to support more inclusive, equitable, and just organizations.</p></sec><sec id="s004"><title>ACTIONS TO ADVANCE EQUITY IN THE NATION'S WEATHER, WATER, AND CLIMATE SERVICES</title><p>Intentional and deliberate progress toward an equity framework will require leaders to prioritize four action areas: (1) recognizing and prioritizing community expertise; (2) building a stronger and more equitable workforce; (3) communicating about climate risk in equitable, timely, and culturally responsive ways; and (4) developing new models of relationship between communities and academia. Our goal is to identify current shortcomings and propose strategies to improve implementation.</p><sec id="s005"><title>Recognizing and prioritizing community expertise</title><p>Communities need to be key partners in how scientists and policy-makers respond and adapt to weather, water, and climate issues, with a seat at the table.<sup><xref rid="fn38" ref-type="fn">38</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn43" ref-type="fn">43</xref></sup> A close and authentic relationship between communities and services will facilitate effective and sustainable solutions that are culturally sensitive, timely, and relevant. Authenticity requires from the outset a sustained commitment to relational accountability and an in-person approach grounded in equity; justice; reciprocity; mutual trust; respect; and sharing of information, resources, and power.</p><p>Effective partnerships should respect the realities of communities, with a social, historical, and present-day trauma-informed context. Services and justice in BIPOC communities have been adversely impacted by institutional barriers and generations of disempowerment, which continue to limit all aspects of physical, mental, ecological, economic, and social health, as well as cultural life and community resilience. Research and engagement with communities need to be reimagined given that many BIPOC individuals, families, and communities&#x02014;including people who are immigrants or undocumented&#x02014;have significant reasons to distrust government or higher education entities,<sup><xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn">3</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn44" ref-type="fn">44</xref></sup> with a desire to avoid continuation of exploitation. This presents a difficult, yet not insurmountable challenge.</p><p>Although Western STEM and policy institutions are increasingly recognizing these exploitative outcomes and pledged to be more equitable and inclusive, much work is needed. Support is needed for communities to have the space, time, and resources to organize the involvement of their knowledge keepers, scientists, and knowledge systems in science and policy. This includes crafting inclusion in ways that reflect what it takes for communities to mobilize.</p><p>Institutions need to recognize the diverse forms of knowledge that communities may choose to invoke in particular circumstances. Indigenous people have used traditional knowledge systems to not only track environmental change over time, but also to take action to address climate change through efforts such as community-based planning for resettlement, the rebuilding of institutions, and actions to engage in self-determination and self-governance.<sup><xref rid="fn40" ref-type="fn">40</xref></sup> In island communities, local and Indigenous knowledge systems serve critical roles in climate resilience, including by providing food security and architectural integrity in the face of increasing hurricane activity.<sup><xref rid="fn45 fn46 fn47" ref-type="fn">45&#x02013;47</xref></sup></p><p>Communities need updated time-relevant information on potential risks and available services to effectively plan and manage impacts, and should be included, nonexploitatively, and in ways that build community capacity, in determining what those services are. Community-based assessments are effective in determining what services are available, what is needed, and how they should be provided.</p><p>Direct payment for community member service on boards and committees are places where relationships can start to form and become long standing, in the same way that scientists' and policy-makers' salaries empower them to serve. Support is needed to ensure there is continuity of relationship, resources to complete the work, and a focus on building community capacity and centering community priorities.</p><p>In addition to providing resources, entities that provide services must update their processes to be more supportive of communities. They must share updates and results through briefings and communications to community members, and create agreements on governance and who holds authority throughout processes (e.g., establishing questions, collecting data, accessing findings, receiving credit, determining intellectual property rights, and guaranteeing meaningful outputs for communities).</p><p>Transparency and accountability mechanisms should be incorporated throughout, to ensure there are opportunities for determining what constitutes healthy and ethical interactions, and shifting course. A central goal should be rebuilding practices, rules, and organizational cultures so that communities are involved nonexploitatively from the outset. For services, this includes planning, education, research, operations, communications, and infrastructure development.</p></sec><sec id="s006"><title>Building a stronger and more equitable workforce</title><p>Equity indicators provide evidence of high rates of discrimination in geoscience training and workforce settings.<sup><xref rid="fn37" ref-type="fn">37</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn48 fn49 fn50 fn51" ref-type="fn">48&#x02013;51</xref></sup> Exclusion from educational opportunities, workforce rights, policy development, and leadership and decision-making roles perpetuates systemic racism, and ultimately protects the exclusionary nature of the status quo. This cycle is fundamental to the entrenchment of systemic racism in the academic and nonacademic workforce, and in individual institutions and organizations. As the climate crisis grows, current deficits in diversity and retention in the workforce and academy will continue to impede the development of effective and relevant weather, water, and climate services, priorities, and policies.</p><sec id="s007"><title>Equity in the workforce</title><p>Professionally, the representation of people of color in the federal STEM workforce lags behind the civilian workforce, which in turn significantly lags behind the nation's demographic profile.<sup><xref rid="fn20" ref-type="fn">20</xref>,<xref rid="fn47" ref-type="fn">47</xref></sup> In the atmospheric science and meteorological workforce, there are &#x0223c;96,000 people working as postsecondary teachers, faculty, and instructors, yet fewer than 10 black full professors in atmospheric sciences and meteorology, and less than 15 in tenure-track positions.<sup><xref rid="fn20" ref-type="fn">20</xref>,<xref rid="fn47" ref-type="fn">47</xref></sup> The private sector represents the fastest segment of growth in the weather, water, and climate enterprise and also has low levels of diversity.<sup><xref rid="fn23" ref-type="fn">23</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn52" ref-type="fn">52</xref></sup></p><p>Thus there is a major need for representation in the nonacademic and academic workforce and in leadership that reflects the nation's demographics. Some companies work to directly recruit in and provide scholarship support to BIPOC students, minority-serving institutions (MSIs), and/or to programs for diverse workforce development at colleges and universities. Others use an equity lens to evaluate human resource policies on hiring and assessment, drawing on rubrics, and to evaluate whether applicants have meaningful engagement and experience with equity work.</p><p>Organizations and companies serious about centering equity and justice work should affirm their rationale for making these and other changes (e.g., to better the institution, to improve services, and/or to correct past unfair practices) and collaborate with community experts, whom they should recruit as employees, advisory board members, and consultants. In addition to necessitating the involvement of community experts, initiatives benefit from federal oversight to ensure data and programs are reliable and adherent to standards.</p><p>A recent RAND Corporation collaboration focused on reducing vulnerability while retaining resilience and involved company scientists partnering on a community-based participatory research project to catalog chemicals in maritime industrial areas and the risk of release in severe weather events. On issues that matter to impacted communities, companies and organizations should support advocacy to policy-makers and translate findings into action.</p><p>Recognizing that centering equity is challenging, strategies and programs should be evaluated to determine whether they are &#x0201c;easy,&#x0201d; or equity-avoidant strategies that are economically expedient, or whether they are in fact meaningful. Planning must address both immediate needs and long-term solutions, and consider cumulative long-term impacts on communities. There are opportunities to draw on principles of Indigeneity and focus on integrative life cycle analyses, which address water, climate, ecological, health, and equity impacts over multiple timescales, instead of only immediate costs.</p></sec><sec id="s008"><title>Equity in education and training</title><p>Youth and students are future planners and climate leaders. From curiosity in the geosciences and STEM, a passion for addressing climate injustice and community engagement, to being a key vector for scientific innovation,<sup><xref rid="fn4" ref-type="fn">4</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn53" ref-type="fn">53</xref></sup> BIPOC youth and students are desperately necessary to tackle the climate crisis. There are opportunities to listen and to include them in designing to build their own capacity, and the capacity of their communities, in ways that are forward looking. There is a pressing need for mentorship from people who share values with and believe in them and are grounded in strengths-based, not deficit-based, models, and a need for diverse pathways to scientific and policy leadership positions.</p><p>However, the geosciences remain persistently segregated due to issues with culture.<sup><xref rid="fn21" ref-type="fn">21</xref>,<xref rid="fn37" ref-type="fn">37</xref>,<xref rid="fn48" ref-type="fn">48</xref>,<xref rid="fn51" ref-type="fn">51</xref></sup> In 2018, only 207 black students from a total pool of 7431 students graduated with undergraduate degrees in earth, atmospheric, and ocean sciences, and this number had barely doubled over the preceding decade.<sup><xref rid="fn21" ref-type="fn">21</xref>,<xref rid="fn23" ref-type="fn">23</xref>,<xref rid="fn30" ref-type="fn">30</xref>,<xref rid="fn50" ref-type="fn">50</xref></sup> The institutions making significant impact are few.<sup><xref rid="fn23" ref-type="fn">23</xref>,<xref rid="fn49" ref-type="fn">49</xref>,<xref rid="fn50" ref-type="fn">50</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn54" ref-type="fn">54</xref></sup> Given the culture of geoscience, trainees and more senior participants from marginalized groups continue to face hostility, isolation, and other barriers.<sup><xref rid="fn55 fn56 fn57 fn58 fn59" ref-type="fn">55&#x02013;59</xref></sup></p><p>Such experiences impact retention and recruitment by causing continual damage to BIPOC people's mental and physical health.<sup><xref rid="fn60" ref-type="fn">60</xref></sup> Higher education needs to replace traditional models that demand that individuals persist in inhospitable or hostile environments, or leave, with redesigned environments and revised policies and practices that make spaces, partnerships, and institutions more welcoming and equitable, so all can thrive. Changes in practices and policies in the academy are also needed, including around admissions, hiring,<sup><xref rid="fn61" ref-type="fn">61</xref></sup> tenure, and promotion, retention, paper reviews,<sup><xref rid="fn62" ref-type="fn">62</xref></sup> funding,<sup><xref rid="fn63" ref-type="fn">63</xref></sup> awards,<sup><xref rid="fn64" ref-type="fn">64</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn65" ref-type="fn">65</xref></sup> social norms, and other aspects of traditional academia. Such changes will have a cascade of downstream effects, given the role of higher education in transmitting culture.</p><p>Geosciences education and research need to focus on redressing colonial relationships that are strongly expressed in science.<sup><xref rid="fn66" ref-type="fn">66</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn67" ref-type="fn">67</xref></sup> Some models show that change is possible.<sup><xref rid="fn37" ref-type="fn">37</xref>,<xref rid="fn54" ref-type="fn">54</xref></sup> MSIs have made headway in equity and access issues that impact undergraduate and graduate education. Howard University in partnership with NOAA produced 60% of all African American atmospheric sciences PhDs in the past decade with 98% in the workforce, whereas top 10 programs produced fewer than 10 in the past 25 years.<sup><xref rid="fn23" ref-type="fn">23</xref>,<xref rid="fn36" ref-type="fn">36</xref>,<xref rid="fn50" ref-type="fn">50</xref>,<xref rid="fn54" ref-type="fn">54</xref></sup></p><p>Other examples of effective geoscience programs include NOAA's Jos&#x000e9; E. Serrano Education Partnership Program with MSIs,<sup><xref rid="fn68" ref-type="fn">68</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn69" ref-type="fn">69</xref></sup> responsible for training graduates who have become 37% of the NOAA minority science hires from 2000 to 2005; the Center for Diverse Leadership in Science at UCLA,<sup><xref rid="fn70 fn71 fn72" ref-type="fn">70&#x02013;72</xref></sup> which takes a human-centered relational approach grounded in equity, and works to build power in marginalized people, groups, and communities, while taking an interdisciplinary, intergenerational, and ecological approach, and has supported &#x0003e;200 fellows including students, community practitioners, and faculty fellows, and is effective at diversifying the geosciences workforce; and the Significant Opportunities in Atmospheric Research and Science program at University Corporation for Atmospheric Research that through effective mentored research experiences is significantly broadening graduate school participation of historically under-represented groups in the geosciences.<sup><xref rid="fn67" ref-type="fn">67</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn73" ref-type="fn">73</xref></sup></p><p>Major increases in investment for effective strategies have recently been proposed to broaden participation in STEM and advance systemic change.<sup><xref rid="fn68" ref-type="fn">68</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn74" ref-type="fn">74</xref></sup> Such an approach could be targeted to develop equity-driven centers focused on basic and applied climate, environment, and sustainability research, education, and partnerships.</p><p>Another key area for higher education reform relates to the development of curricula on climate and environmental justice and ethics, and how they are related to the geosciences. Topics could include resource extraction, land dispossession, settler colonialism, structural racism, pollution, climate change, extreme weather events, and their inter-relationships. Within these materials, emphasizing traditional knowledge systems and sustainability in Western and Indigenous contexts will enable this country's next generation of students and leaders to have broader critical awareness.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s009"><title>Communicating climate risk: equitable, timely, and culturally responsive</title><p>The nation's weather, water, and climate services have the responsibility of providing equitable access to accurate and up-to-date information and resources for all, regardless of language or documentation status, with equitable rules and mechanisms for distributing resources. Greater federal investment is needed to assist communities with climate preparedness and resiliency planning, and to support agencies producing knowledge around equitable and culturally responsive provision of services.</p><p>Government agencies must provide accessible tools and products; to ensure community confidence in these resources, they must also support community expertise and ambassadorship in the design and deployment of climate services, and offer opportunities for community evaluation and feedback. It is critical that agency workforces listen to community leaders and build relationships between different and diverse communities.</p><p>Risk and crisis communication also necessitate connection and partnership with communities. For example, communities may speak different languages, or dialects of a language, which can impact the ability of community members to fully participate&#x02014;including being reached with emergency alerts&#x02014;unless paid translators are provided.<sup><xref rid="fn4" ref-type="fn">4</xref></sup></p><p>Language accessibility cannot be sustained by communities alone: government agencies should fund and develop multilingual centers that not only produce effective translations for life-saving hazards, but also guarantee connections with community partners. Key documents representing community voices and leadership show that current efforts are not enough, such as was highlighted in recent recommendations on environmental and climate justice by the White House Environmental Justice Advisory Council.<sup><xref rid="fn32" ref-type="fn">32</xref></sup></p><p>Poor infrastructure and information availability are major impediments that lead to disproportionate impacts from environmental disasters in underserved communities. To ensure equitable services, harm reduction, mitigation, and adaptation need to be emphasized, with granular information at the level of neighborhoods, localities, communities, and tribal nations. Verification of critical services should be expanded to understand who is impacted, what the impacts are, what languages are relevant, how information is received, and who benefits from existing and new resources. Given fragmentation of existing services across different agencies, new interagency coordination is needed among services, with equity centered from the outset. Additional capacity is severely needed.</p><p>The United States Geological Survey (USGS) Climate Adaptation Science Centers (CASCs), a partnership-driven program wherein scientists collaborate with natural and cultural resource managers to combat climate change, and the NOAA Regional Integrated Sciences and Assessments (RISAs) programs, which supports applied and co-developed research partnerships with communities to combat climate change, are examples. USGS CASCs and NOAA RISAs emphasize transferring science and data to local communities, and additional regional and local weather services capacity such as these models are critical to effectively addressing inequities.</p><p>Collection and assessment of demographic data are needed to understand who becomes ill or dies because of extreme events, climate change, and pollution; what health and warning information they had; and whether they had access to harm mitigation resources (e.g., local cooling centers during extreme heat). When collecting demographic data, strategies in counting marginalized populations should be re-evaluated.<sup><xref rid="fn6" ref-type="fn">6</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn75" ref-type="fn">75</xref></sup> Overall, a joint effort of physical, social, and health scientists is needed to study and understand disparate and inequitable climate change vulnerabilities and impacts.<sup><xref rid="fn70" ref-type="fn">70</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn76" ref-type="fn">76</xref></sup> National and regional climate assessments should more thoroughly present the unequally distributed impacts on different demographics.</p></sec><sec id="s010"><title>Alternative models of relationship: communities and the academic sector</title><p>Educational institutions should revisit what it means to be a geoscientist, what valued education and research look like, and the many roles geoscientists can have with communities and employers. Institutions have the opportunity to reframe and build a professional culture in which working with local communities and a science career are synergistic, not exclusive as traditionally framed in STEM, and can provide deep long-term investments to build and sustain community integration. Departments and universities should support training and practice in applied opportunities, including community-based work.</p><p>One example can be found in Science Shops, crafted in response to concerns raised by the popular education and participatory action research movements in the global south, which coordinates community-engaged research that centers the needs of community-based organizations that brings in university-based scientists and students.<sup><xref rid="fn71" ref-type="fn">71</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="fn77" ref-type="fn">77</xref></sup> In American universities, it has demonstrated both its ability to channel community voice into research agendas and potential for catalyzing institutional culture change.<sup><xref rid="fn78" ref-type="fn">78</xref></sup> Programs such as American Geophysical Union's Thriving Earth Exchange train volunteer scientists to work in authentic ways in support of community environmental projects.<sup><xref rid="fn79" ref-type="fn">79</xref></sup></p><p>Highlighting a breadth of career options and role models, and fostering multiple career pathways, would help future scientists and science fields as a whole. Institutions need to understand the sacrifices most programs ask of students for their training (e.g., separation from home communities, support structures, and relationship to place), which can cause harm to people from structurally excluded groups, particularly Indigenous students. Much can be learned from nontraditional models utilized by academic experts, including extension programs, such as used in the department of environmental science at the University of Arizona by Prof. Karletta Chief,<sup><xref rid="fn80" ref-type="fn">80</xref></sup> and other frameworks such as that developed by Prof. Bryan Brayboy at Arizona State University centered on empowering, engaging, and enhancing communities.<sup><xref rid="fn81 fn82 fn83" ref-type="fn">81&#x02013;83</xref></sup></p><p>Finally, funding opportunities should require that research is framed using an equity lens, with explicitly developed action plans to allow for self-determined rather than exploitative community engagement.<sup><xref rid="fn58" ref-type="fn">58</xref></sup> For community-based work, research planning should include discussions of listening and engagement sessions with partners, and review processes should include information on protocols and consents, in the model of institutional review board protocols and similar structures in many tribal organizations. Social vulnerabilities need to be explicitly incorporated in resilience research, policy, and planning.<sup><xref rid="fn70" ref-type="fn">70</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="s011"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The necessary work of moving from good intentions to sustained action lies ahead. Although past efforts have often been piecemeal, incremental, and not maintainable over time, the intersections of climate change with inequality demand that equity, as well as justice and inclusion, be centered across the board. All status-quo processes, systems, and procedures must be examined and challenged. Institutional leaders must adopt an equity-centered mindset to facilitate the implementation of effective, inclusive, and sustainable solutions that will save lives. The necessary changes are reflected in recent calls to change policy to achieve systemic reform, to share power and information, and to ensure equitable access to networks and resources.</p><p>Leaders with positional authority and resources must manifest responsibility through action in the four areas already described: (1) recognizing, integrating, and prioritizing community expertise; (2) building a stronger and more equitable workforce; (3) communicating about climate risk in equitable, relevant, timely, and culturally responsive ways; and (4) developing new models of relationship between communities and the academic sector. Collectively, these actions will help to ensure there is equity in the nation's weather, climate, and water services, for current and future generations.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We are grateful to the staff who convened the meeting of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine's Board on Atmospheric Sciences and Climate that led to this article, as well as to NSF, NOAA, and NASA for their support of the board. We thank Jeana Drake, Amy Myrbo, and Tom Rudin for edits.</p><p>Although the preparations for and discussions at the meeting were the impetus for this article, the views presented here are those of the authors, and do not reflect the consensus views of the National Academies or of the federal agencies of individual authors, unless specifically cited as such. This study has been reviewed by the U.S. EPA and approved for publication; the views expressed are those of the authors' and do not necessarily reflect the views or policies of the U.S. EPA.</p></ack><sec id="s012"><title>AUTHORs' CONTRIBUTIONS</title><p>All coauthors contributed to the article. This article came from discussion at a meeting of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine's Board on Atmospheric Sciences and Climate (BASC) on June 4, 2021, a recording of which can be found at <uri xlink:href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/06-03-2021/basc-spring-2021-meeting">https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/06-03-2021/basc-spring-2021-meeting</uri>. The meeting was organized by A. Tripati, with support from former BASC member V. Morris, BASC board chair M. Glackin, and BASC staff A. Reich. Speakers at the meeting included A. Tripati, M. Shepherd, K. Whyte, D. David-Chavez, J. Trujillo-Falcon, D. Hence, W. Parker, and A. Geller.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s013"><title>AUTHOR DISCLOSURE STATEMENT</title><p>No competing financial interests exist.</p></sec><sec id="s014"><title>FUNDING INFORMATION</title><p>A.T., K.A., and B.H. were supported by NSF, the Packard Foundation, and the Sloan Foundation. J.E.T.F.'s funding was provided by NOAA/Office of Oceanic and Atmospheric Research under NOAA-University of Oklahoma Cooperative Agreement No. NA21OAR4320204, U.S. Department of Commerce.</p></sec><sec id="s015"><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label><p>National Public Radio. 2021. &#x0003c;<uri xlink:href="https://www.npr.org/transcripts/1054655933">https://www.npr.org/transcripts/1054655933</uri>&#x0003e;. (Last accessed on October 10, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label><p>Marshall Shepherd. &#x0201c;The Curious Relationship Between COVID-19 Lockdowns and Urban Heat Islands.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Geophysical Research Letters</italic> 49 (2022): e2022GL098198.</p></fn><fn id="fn3" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label><p>Angel Hsu, Glenn Sheriff, Tirthankar Chakraborty, and Diego Manya. &#x0201c;Disproportionate Exposure to Urban Heat Island Intensity Across Major US Cities.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Nature Communications</italic> 12 (2021): 1&#x02013;11.</p></fn><fn id="fn4" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>4</sup>
</label><p>Joseph E. Trujillo-Falc&#x000f3;n, Orlando Berm&#x000fa;dez, Krizia Negr&#x000f3;n-Hern&#x000e1;ndez, John Lipski, Elizabeth Leitman, and Kodi Berry. &#x0201c;Hazardous Weather Communication En Espa&#x000f1;ol: Challenges, Current Resources, and Future Practices.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</italic> 102 (2021): E765&#x02013;E773.</p></fn><fn id="fn5" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>5</sup>
</label><p>Neil Debbage. &#x0201c;Multiscalar Spatial Analysis of Urban Flood Risk and Environmental Justice in the Charlanta Megaregion, USA.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Anthropocene</italic> 28 (2019): 100226.</p></fn><fn id="fn6" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>6</sup>
</label><p>Robert D. Bullard. <italic toggle="yes">Dumping in Dixie: Race, Class, and Environmental Quality</italic>. (Routledge, 2018).</p></fn><fn id="fn7" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>7</sup>
</label><p>Michael M&#x000e9;ndez, Genevieve Flores-Haro, and Lucas Zucker. &#x0201c;The (In)visible Victims of Disaster: Understanding the Vulnerability of Undocumented Latino/a and Indigenous Immigrants.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Geoforum</italic> 116 (2020): 50&#x02013;62.</p></fn><fn id="fn8" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>8</sup>
</label><p>Robert Bullard. &#x0201c;Addressing Environmental Racism.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of International Affairs</italic> 73 (2019): 237&#x02013;242.</p></fn><fn id="fn9" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>9</sup>
</label><p>Marshall Shepherd and K.C. Binita. &#x0201c;Climate Change and African Americans in the USA.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Geography Compass</italic> 9 (2015): 579&#x02013;591.</p></fn><fn id="fn10" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>10</sup>
</label><p>Justin Hosbey. &#x0201c;Refusing Unliveable Destinies: Toward a Future for Black Life in New Orleans.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Fire!!!</italic> 5 (2018): 35&#x02013;47.</p></fn><fn id="fn11" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>11</sup>
</label><p>Fayola Jacobs. &#x0201c;Black Feminism and Radical Planning: New Directions for Disaster Planning Research.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Planning Theory</italic> 18 (2019): 24&#x02013;39.</p></fn><fn id="fn12" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>12</sup>
</label><p>Eliot M. Tretter and Melissa Adams. &#x0201c;The Privilege of Staying Dry: The Impact of Flooding and Racism on the Emergence of.&#x0201d; In: <italic toggle="yes">Cities, Nature and Development: The Politics and Production of Urban Vulnerabilities.</italic> (Routledge, 2012), 187.</p></fn><fn id="fn13" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>13</sup>
</label><p>Joel E. Correia. &#x0201c;Between Flood and Drought: Environmental Racism, Settler Waterscapes, and Indigenous Water Justice in South America's Chaco.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Annals of the American Association of Geographers</italic> 112 (2022): 1890&#x02013;1910.</p></fn><fn id="fn14" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>14</sup>
</label><p>Jeremy S. Hoffman, Vivek Shandas, and Nicholas Pendleton. &#x0201c;The Effects of Historical Housing Policies on Resident Exposure to Intra-Urban Heat: A Study of 108 US Urban Areas.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Climate</italic> 8 (2020): 12.</p></fn><fn id="fn15" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>15</sup>
</label><p>Richard Rothstein. <italic toggle="yes">The Color of Law</italic>. (Liveright Publishing, 2017).</p></fn><fn id="fn16" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>16</sup>
</label><p>Carlos E. Rodr&#x000ed;guez-D&#x000ed;az. &#x0201c;Maria in Puerto Rico: Natural Disaster in a Colonial Archipelago.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">American Journal of Public Health</italic> 108 (2018): 30&#x02013;32.</p></fn><fn id="fn17" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>17</sup>
</label><p>Christopher Flavelle. &#x0201c;Why Does Disaster Aid Often Favor White People?&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">New York Times</italic> (2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn18" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>18</sup>
</label><p>Rachel Ramirez and Nicquel Terry Ellis. &#x0201c;What a Hurricane Means When You Live in Louisiana's &#x02018;Cancer Alley&#x02019;.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">CNN</italic> (2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn19" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>19</sup>
</label><p>Marshall Shepherd. &#x0201c;Are Black and Rural Residents in the South More Vulnerable to Tornadoes Due to Radar Gaps?&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Forbes</italic> (2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn20" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>20</sup>
</label><p>Julie Koppel Maldonado, Christine Shearer, Robin Bronen, Kristina Peterson, and Heather Lazrus. &#x0201c;The Impact of Climate Change on Tribal Communities in the US: Displacement, Relocation, and Human Rights.&#x0201d; In: <italic toggle="yes">Climate Change and Indigenous Peoples in the United States</italic>. (Springer, 2013), 93&#x02013;106.</p></fn><fn id="fn21" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>21</sup>
</label><p>National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics (NCSES). <italic toggle="yes">Women, Minorities, and Persons with Disabilities in Science and Engineering</italic>. (National Science Foundation, 2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn22" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>22</sup>
</label><p>Suzanne Van Cooten. &#x0201c;Where Are the Indigenous Scientific Leaders? Examining the Participation of Native American/Alaska Natives in Weather and Water Academic Programs and the Federal Workforce.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</italic> 95 (2014): 1725&#x02013;1740.</p></fn><fn id="fn23" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>23</sup>
</label><p>Vernon Morris, Solomon Bililign, and Belay Demoz. &#x0201c;The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly: Sobering Statistics on Black Atmospheric Scientists in the Academy.&#x0201d; In: <italic toggle="yes">101st American Meteorological Society Annual Meeting</italic>. (AMS, 2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn24" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>24</sup>
</label><p>United States Census Bureau. <italic toggle="yes">Census Bureau Releases Estimates of Undercount and Overcount in the 2020 Census</italic>. (United States Census Bureau, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn25" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>25</sup>
</label><p>Kristin E. Henkel, John F. Dovidio, and Samuel L. Gaertner. &#x0201c;Institutional Discrimination, Individual Racism, and Hurricane Katrina.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Analyses of Social Issues and Public Policy</italic> 6 (2006): 99&#x02013;124.</p></fn><fn id="fn26" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>26</sup>
</label><p>Catherine Coleman Flowers. <italic toggle="yes">Waste: One Woman's Fight Against America's Dirty Secret</italic>. (The New Press, 2020).</p></fn><fn id="fn27" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>27</sup>
</label><p>Jennie C. Stephens. <italic toggle="yes">Diversifying Power: Why We Need Antiracist, Feminist Leadership on Climate and Energy</italic>. (Island Press, 2020).</p></fn><fn id="fn28" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>28</sup>
</label><p>&#x000c1;lvaro Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Llamazares, Dana Lepofsky, Ken Lertzman, Chelsey Geralda Armstrong, Eduardo S. Brondizio, Michael C. Gavin, Phil O'B. Lyver, George P. Nicholas, Pua'ala Pascua, Nicholas J. Reo, Victoria Reyes-Garc&#x000ed;a, Nancy J. Turner, Johanna Yletyinen, E.N. Anderson, William Bal&#x000e9;e, Joji Cari&#x000f1;o, Dominique M. David-Chavez, Christopher P. Dunn, Stephen C. Garnett, Spencer Greening, Shain Jackson, Harriet Kuhnlein, Zsolt Moln&#x000e1;r, Guillaume Odonne, Gunn-Britt Retter, William J. Ripple, L&#x000e1;szl&#x000f3; S&#x000e1;fi&#x000e1;n, Abolfazl Sharifian Bahraman, Miquel Torrents-Tic&#x000f3;, and Mehana Blaich Vaughan &#x0201c;Scientists' Warning to Humanity on Threats to Indigenous and Local Knowledge Systems.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Ethnobiology</italic> 41 (2021): 144&#x02013;169.</p></fn><fn id="fn29" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>29</sup>
</label><p>W. Neil Adger, Juan M. Pulhin, Jon Barnett, Geoffrey D. Dabelko, Grete K. Hovelsrud, Marc Levy, Ursula Oswald Spring, and Coleen H. Vogel, IPCC Climate. &#x0201c;Impacts, Adaptation, and Vulnerability.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Part A: Global and Sectoral Aspects. Contribution of Working Group II to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic> 1132 (2014).</p></fn><fn id="fn30" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>30</sup>
</label><p>Memorandum on Indigenous Traditional Ecological Knowledge and Federal Decision Making. 2021. &#x0003c;<uri xlink:href="http://Whitehouse.gov">Whitehouse.gov</uri>&#x0003e;. (Last accessed on October 10, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn31" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>31</sup>
</label><p>Joseph Biden Jr. &#x0201c;Executive Order on Tackling the Climate Crisis at Home and Abroad.&#x0201d; Executive Order 14008, White House (2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn32" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>32</sup>
</label><p>White House Environmental Justice Advisory Council Final Recommendations: Justice40 Climate and Economic Justice Screening Tool &#x00026; Executive Order 12898 Revisions (2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn33" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>33</sup>
</label><p>Martin Luther King Jr. &#x0201c;Speech at the March on Washington&#x0201d; (1963).</p></fn><fn id="fn34" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>34</sup>
</label><p>Vernon Morris, Lisa White, Jose Fuentes, Christopher Atchison, Wendy Smythe, Melissa Burt, Leticia Williams, Aradhna Tripati, Belay Demoz, and Roy Armstrong, &#x0201c;No Time For Silence: A Call to Action for an Anti-Racist Science Community from Geoscientists of Color: Listen, Act, Lead.&#x0201d; 2020. &#x0003c;<uri xlink:href="https://notimeforsilence.org/">https://notimeforsilence.org/</uri>&#x0003e;. (Last accessed on October 10, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn35" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>35</sup>
</label><p>Hendratta Ali. &#x0201c;Call for a Robust Anti-Racism Plan for the Geosciences.&#x0201d; 2020. &#x0003c;<uri xlink:href="http://Change.org">Change.org</uri>&#x0003e;. (Last accessed on October 10, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn36" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>36</sup>
</label><p>Hendratta N. Ali, Sarah L. Sheffield, Jennifer E. Bauer, Roc&#x000ed;o P. Caballero-Gill, Nicole M. Gasparini, Julie Libarkin, Kalynda K. Gonzales, Jane Willenbring, Erika Amir-Lin, Julia Cisneros, Dipa Desai, Maitri Erwin, Elisabeth Gallant, Kiara Jeannelle Gomez, Benjamin A. Keisling, Robert Mahon, Erika Mar&#x000ed;n-Spiotta, Leiaka Welcome, and Blair Schneider. &#x0201c;An Actionable Anti-Racism Plan for Geoscience Organizations.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Nature Communications</italic> 12 (2021): 1&#x02013;6.</p></fn><fn id="fn37" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>37</sup>
</label><p>Vernon R. Morris. &#x0201c;Combating Racism in the Geosciences: Reflections from a Black Professor.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">AGU Advances</italic> 2 (2021): e2020AV000358.</p></fn><fn id="fn38" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>38</sup>
</label><p>Linda Shi, Eric Chu, Isabelle Anguelovski, Alexander Aylett, Jessica Debats, Kian Goh, Todd Schenk, Karen C. Seto, David Dodman, Debra Roberts, J. Timmons Roberts, and Stacy D. VanDeveer. &#x0201c;Roadmap Towards Justice in Urban Climate Adaptation Research.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Nature Climate Change</italic> 6 (2016): 131&#x02013;137.</p></fn><fn id="fn39" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>39</sup>
</label><p>Heather Lazrus, Julie Maldonado, Paulette Blanchard, M. Kalani Souza, Bill Thomas, and Danial Wildcat. &#x0201c;Culture Change to Address Climate Change: Collaborations with Indigenous and Earth Sciences for More Just, Equitable, and Sustainable Responses to Our Climate Crisis.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">PLoS Climate</italic> 1 (2022): e0000005.</p></fn><fn id="fn40" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>40</sup>
</label><p>Dominique M. David-Chavez and Michael C. Gavin. &#x0201c;A Global Assessment of Indigenous Community Engagement in Climate Research.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Environmental Research Letters</italic> 13 (2018): 123005.</p></fn><fn id="fn41" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>41</sup>
</label><p>David Schlosberg. &#x0201c;Theorising Environmental Justice: The Expanding Sphere of a Discourse.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Environmental Politics</italic> 22 (2013): 37&#x02013;55.</p></fn><fn id="fn42" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>42</sup>
</label><p>J.L. Harrison. &#x0201c;Bureaucrats' Tacit Understandings and Social Movement Policy Implementation: Unpacking the Deviation of Agency Environmental Justice Programs from EJ Movement Priorities.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Social Problems</italic> 63 (2016): 534&#x02013;553.</p></fn><fn id="fn43" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>43</sup>
</label><p>Isabelle Anguelovski, Linda Shi, Eric Chu, Daniel Gallagher, Kian Goh, Zachary Lamb, Kara Reeve, and Hannah Teicher. &#x0201c;Towards Critical Studies of Climate Adaptation Planning: Uncovering the Equity Impacts of Urban Land Use Planning.&#x0201d; (2016).</p></fn><fn id="fn44" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>44</sup>
</label><p>Elizabeth Fussell, Linda Delp, Kevin Riley, Sergio Ch&#x000e1;vez, and Abel Valenzuela Jr. &#x0201c;Implications of Social and Legal Status on Immigrants' Health in Disaster Zones.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">American Journal of Public Health</italic> 108 (2018): 1617&#x02013;1620.</p></fn><fn id="fn45" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>45</sup>
</label><p>Status of Tribes and Climate Change Working Group (STACCWG). &#x0201c;Status of Tribes and Climate Change Report,&#x0201d; Institute for Tribal Environmental Professionals, Northern Arizona University, Flagstaff, AZ. [Marks-Marino, D. (ed.)]. 2021. &#x0003c;<uri xlink:href="http://nau.edu/stacc2021">http://nau.edu/stacc2021</uri>&#x0003e;. (Last accessed on October 10, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn46" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>46</sup>
</label><p>Dominique David-Chavez and Norma Ortiz. &#x0201c;Strengthening Climate Resilience in the Caribbean Through an Indigenous Community-Based Participatory Research Model.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts</italic> (2018).</p></fn><fn id="fn47" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>47</sup>
</label><p>UNESCO. <italic toggle="yes">Mobilizing Indigenous and Local Knowledge Solutions: Addressing Climate Impacts and Vulnerabilities A Perspective from the Caribbean Region. [Workshop Report]</italic>. (United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, 2020).</p></fn><fn id="fn48" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>48</sup>
</label><p>Rachel E. Bernard and Emily H.G. Cooperdock. &#x0201c;No Progress on Diversity in 40 Years.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Nature Geoscience</italic> 115 (2018): 292&#x02013;295.</p></fn><fn id="fn49" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>49</sup>
</label><p>Vernon R. Morris and Talitha M. Washington. &#x0201c;The Role of Professional Societies in STEM Diversity.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Not Am Math Soc</italic> 65 (2017).</p></fn><fn id="fn50" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>50</sup>
</label><p>Rachel J. Beane, Eric Baer, Rowan Lockwood, R. Heather Macdonald, John R. McDaris, Vernon R. Morris, I. Joshua Villalobos, and Lisa D. White. &#x0201c;Uneven Increases in Racial Diversity of US Geoscience Undergraduates.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Communications Earth &#x00026; Environment</italic> 2 (2021): 1&#x02013;4.</p></fn><fn id="fn51" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>51</sup>
</label><p>Steve Boss. <italic toggle="yes">Modeling the Demographic Dynamics of the Geosciences Workforce</italic>. (MSU Colloqium, 2021) (slides in possession of lead author).</p></fn><fn id="fn52" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>52</sup>
</label><p>United States Bureau of Labor Statistics. &#x0003c;<uri xlink:href="https://www.bls.gov/opub/mlr/2020/">https://www.bls.gov/opub/mlr/2020/</uri>&#x0003e;. (Last accessed on October 10, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn53" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>53</sup>
</label><p>Bas Hofstra, Vivek V. Kulkarni, Sebastian Munoz-Najar Galvez, Bryan He, Dan Jurafsky, and Daniel A. McFarland. &#x0201c;The Diversity&#x02013;Innovation Paradox in Science.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences United States of America</italic> 117 (2020): 9284&#x02013;9291.</p></fn><fn id="fn54" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>54</sup>
</label><p>Vernon R. Morris, Everette Joseph, Sonya Smith, and Tsann-wang Yu. &#x0201c;The Howard University Program in Atmospheric Sciences (HUPAS): A Program Exemplifying Diversity and Opportunity.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Geoscience Education</italic> 60 (2012): 45&#x02013;53.</p></fn><fn id="fn55" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>55</sup>
</label><p>Barbara Flores, Patricia Tefft Cousin, and Esteban Diaz. &#x0201c;Transforming Deficit Myths About Learning, Language, and Culture.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Language Arts</italic> 68 (1991): 369&#x02013;379.</p></fn><fn id="fn56" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>56</sup>
</label><p>Chester M. Pierce, Jean V. Carew, Diane Pierce-Gonzalez, and Deborah Wills. &#x0201c;An Experiment in Racism: TV Commercials.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Education and Urban Society</italic> 10 (1977): 61&#x02013;87.</p></fn><fn id="fn57" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>57</sup>
</label><p>Daniel Solorzano, Miguel Ceja, and Tara Yosso. &#x0201c;Critical Race Theory, Racial Microaggressions, and Campus Racial Climate: The Experiences of African American College Students.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Negro Education</italic> (2000): 60&#x02013;73.</p></fn><fn id="fn58" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>58</sup>
</label><p>Claude M. Steele and Joshua Aronson. &#x0201c;Stereotype Threat and the Intellectual Test Performance of African Americans.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</italic> 69 (1995): 797.</p></fn><fn id="fn59" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>59</sup>
</label><p>Asmeret Berhe. &#x0201c;Amplifying Black Voices: The Convenient Narratives That Perpetuate Racism. 2020. &#x0003c;<uri xlink:href="https://www.springernature.com/gp/researchers/the-source/blog/blogposts-life-in-research/amplifying-black-voices-the-convenient-narratives-of-racism-pt1/18415774">https://www.springernature.com/gp/researchers/the-source/blog/blogposts-life-in-research/amplifying-black-voices-the-convenient-narratives-of-racism-pt1/18415774</uri>&#x0003e;. (Last accessed on October 10, 2022).</p></fn><fn id="fn60" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>60</sup>
</label><p>Juanita C. Limas, Linda C. Corcoran, Alexander N. Baker, Ana E. Cartaya, and Zo&#x000eb; J. Ayres. &#x0201c;The Impact of Research Culture on Mental Health &#x00026; Diversity in STEM.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Chemistry&#x02013;A European Journal</italic> (2022): e202102957.</p></fn><fn id="fn61" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>61</sup>
</label><p>&#x000d6;zlem Sensoy and Robin DiAngelo. &#x0201c;&#x0201c;We Are All for Diversity, But&#x02026;&#x0201d;: How Faculty Hiring Committees Reproduce Whiteness and Practical Suggestions for How They Can Change.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Harvard Educational Review</italic> 87 (2017): 557&#x02013;580.</p></fn><fn id="fn62" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>62</sup>
</label><p>Kyle Powys Whyte. <italic toggle="yes">Systematic Discrimination in Peer Review: Some Reflections</italic>. (Daily Nous, 2017).</p></fn><fn id="fn63" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>63</sup>
</label><p>Diamond Tachera. <italic toggle="yes">Reframing Funding Strategies to Build Reciprocity</italic>. (Eos, 2021), 102.</p></fn><fn id="fn64" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>64</sup>
</label><p>Mary Anne Holmes, LaToya Myles, and Blair Schneider. &#x0201c;Diversity and Equality in Honours and Awards Programs&#x02013;Steps Towards a Fair Representation of Membership.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Advances in Geosciences</italic> 53 (2020): 41&#x02013;51.</p></fn><fn id="fn65" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>65</sup>
</label><p>Olivier Pourret, Pallavi Anand, Sandra Arndt, Pieter Bots, Anthony Dosseto, Zimin Li, Johanna Marin Carbonne, Jennifer Middleton, Bryne Ngwenya, and Amy J.V. Riches. &#x0201c;Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion: Tackling Under-Representation and Recognition of Talents in Geochemistry and Cosmochemistry.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</italic> 310 (2021): 363&#x02013;371.</p></fn><fn id="fn66" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>66</sup>
</label><p>Max Liboiron. &#x0201c;Decolonizing Geoscience Requires More Than Equity and Inclusion.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Nature Geoscience</italic> 14 (2021): 876&#x02013;877.</p></fn><fn id="fn67" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>67</sup>
</label><p>Kathryn Yusoff. <italic toggle="yes">A Billion Black Anthropocenes or None.</italic> (University of Minnesota Press, 2018).</p></fn><fn id="fn68" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>68</sup>
</label><p>Larry Robinson, Jacqueline Rousseau, Delicia Mapp, Vernon Morris, and Meka Laster. &#x0201c;An Educational Partnership Program with Minority Serving Institutions: A Framework for Producing Minority Scientists in NOAA-Related Disciplines.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Geoscience Education</italic> 55 (2007): 486&#x02013;492.</p></fn><fn id="fn69" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>69</sup>
</label><p>Vernon Morris, T.-W. Yu, E. Joseph, R. Armstrong, R. Fitzgerald, R. Karim, X-Z. Liang, and Q. Min. &#x0201c;THE NOAA CENTER FOR ATMOSPHERIC SCIENCES (NCAS) Programs and Achievements.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</italic> 88 (2007): 141&#x02013;145.</p></fn><fn id="fn70" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>70</sup>
</label><p>Aradhna Tripati. &#x0201c;Transforming Geoscience and Environmental Science: Advancing Systemic Change Through Faculty and Early Career Development to Support Retention and Improved Institutional Climates.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts</italic> (2019).</p></fn><fn id="fn71" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>71</sup>
</label><p>Aradhna Tripati, Vernon Morris, Catalina Martinez, and Kendall Moore. &#x0201c;Human-Centered, Relational Geoscience.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts</italic> (2019).</p></fn><fn id="fn72" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>72</sup>
</label><p>Aradhna Tripati, Shanna Shaked, Krystle Cobian, Sylvia Hurtado, Marilyn Raphael, Ashley Kruythoff, Steve Dunwoody, Ingrid Maradiaga, Al Courey, Kristina Larsen. &#x0201c;Transforming Geoscience: Changing the Culture and Widening the Pathways.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts</italic> (2018).</p></fn><fn id="fn73" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>73</sup>
</label><p>Rajul E. Pandya, Sandra Henderson, Richard A. Anthes, and Roberta M. Johnson. &#x0201c;BEST Practices for Broadening Participation in the Geosciences: Strategies from the UCAR Significant Opportunities in Atmospheric Research and Science (SOARS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>) Program.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Geoscience Education</italic> 55 (2007): 500&#x02013;506.</p></fn><fn id="fn74" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>74</sup>
</label><p>Freeman A. Hrabowski III and Peter H. Henderson. &#x0201c;Nothing Succeeds Like Success.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Issues in Science and Technology</italic> (2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn75" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>75</sup>
</label><p>Trujillo-Falc&#x000f3;n, Joseph E., Am&#x000e9;rica R. Gaviria Pab&#x000f3;n, Joseph T. Ripberger, Abby Bitterman, Jonathan B. Thornton, Makenzie J. Krocak, Searn R. Ernst, Estilita Cassiani Obeso, and John Lipski. &#x0201c;&#x000bf;Aviso o Alerta? Developing Effective, Inclusive, and Consistent Watch and Warning Translations for U.S. Spanish Speakers.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</italic> 103 (2022): E2791&#x02013;E2803.</p></fn><fn id="fn76" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>76</sup>
</label><p>Susan L. Cutter, Jerry T. Mitchell, and Michael S. Scott. &#x0201c;Revealing the Vulnerability of People and Places: A Case Study of Georgetown County, South Carolina.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Annals of the Association of American Geographers</italic> 90 (2000): 713&#x02013;737.</p></fn><fn id="fn77" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>77</sup>
</label><p>Michael S&#x000f8;gaard J&#x000f8;rgensen and Merete Hende. &#x0201c;Science Shops-a Concept for Community Based Learning.&#x0201d; In: <italic toggle="yes">New Engineering Competencies-Changing the Paradigm</italic>. (SEFI: European Association for Engineering Education, 2001).</p></fn><fn id="fn78" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>78</sup>
</label><p>Karen Andrade, Lara Cushing, and Ashton Wesner. &#x0201c;Science Shops and the US Research University: A Path for Community-Engaged Scholarship and Disruption of the Power Dynamics of Knowledge Production.&#x0201d; In: <italic toggle="yes">Educating for Citizenship and Social Justice</italic>. (Palgrave Macmillan, 2018), 149&#x02013;165.</p></fn><fn id="fn79" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>79</sup>
</label><p>Veera Mitzner, Rajul Pandya, Natasha Udu-gama, Judit Ungvari, and Eleanor Robson. &#x0201c;Thriving Earth Exchange and Future Earth: Strengthening Transdisciplinary and Community Science Around the World.&#x0201d; In: <italic toggle="yes">AGU Fall Meeting 2021</italic>. (AGU, 2021).</p></fn><fn id="fn80" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>80</sup>
</label><p>Karletta Chief. &#x0201c;Emerging Voices of Tribal Perspectives in Water Resources.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Contemporary Water Research &#x00026; Education</italic> 163 (2018): 1&#x02013;15.</p></fn><fn id="fn81" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>81</sup>
</label><p>B.M.J. Brayboy and Megan Bang. &#x0201c;Societal Issues Facing Indigenous Education: Introduction.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Handbook of Indigenous Education</italic> (2019): 567&#x02013;574.</p></fn><fn id="fn82" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>82</sup>
</label><p>Bryn McKinley Jones Brayboy. <italic toggle="yes">A Study of Indigenous Boys and Men</italic>. (RISE for Boys and Men of Color, 2017).</p></fn><fn id="fn83" fn-type="other"><label>
<sup>83</sup>
</label><p>Jessica A. Solyom, Jeremiah A. Chin, Bryan McKinley, Jones Brayboy, Amber Poleviyuma, Sarah Abuwandi, Alexus Richmond, Amanda Tachine, Colin Ben, and Megan Bang. &#x0201c;Systems of Support: What Institutions of Higher Education Can Do for Indigenous Communities.&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">Handbook of Indigenous Education</italic> (2019): 605.</p></fn></fn-group></sec></back></article>