<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11518485</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckae144.146</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckae144.146</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Parallel Programme</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>3.G. Scientific session: Making WHO European Region the Healthiest Online Environment for children: Restrict harmful marketing</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>3.G. Scientific session: Making WHO European Region the Healthiest Online Environment for children: Restrict harmful marketing</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>Organised by: WHO/Europe, EUPHA, Joint Action Prevent Non-Communicable Diseases and Cancer</collab></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><collab>Chair persons: Kremlin Wickramasinghe (Denmark), Amandine Garde (EUPHA-LAW)</collab><xref rid="ckae144.146-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--wickramasinghek@who.int--></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckae144.146-cor1">Contact: <email>wickramasinghek@who.int</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-10-28"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><issue-title>17th European Public Health Conference 2024 Sailing the Waves of European Public Health: Exploring a Sea of Innovation Lisbon, Portugal 12&#x02013;15 November 2024</issue-title><elocation-id>ckae144.146</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ckae144.146.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s394"><title>&#x02002;</title><p>Children spend a significant amount of their time daily on digital devices using online services. While this can bring many advantages and benefits, it also entails dangers if not the online environment is not effectively regulated. Exposure to marketing of harmful products and services, particularly towards children, remains a pervasive challenge, despite the extensive evidence base documenting its negative impacts. This session will give an overview of integrating behavioural sciences with public health which suggested promising avenues for addressing the complexities of harmful digital marketing to children. Additionally, current tools developed by WHO Regional Office for Europe and Joint Actions, which Member States can use to address novel challenges like brand marketing will be presented. The tools help to map, monitor and regulate the digital marketing exposure of unhealthy foods and brands to children in their country. One focus will be on the need to objective monitoring of marketing exposure to inform policies and ensure that they are fit for purpose. This is particularly challenging, as traditional monitoring tools struggle to keep up with automated, targeted and personalized advertisements. Due to the complexity to successfully restrict marketing exposure to children, strong collaborations are needed. Collaborative efforts of the Joint Action PreventNCD and the WHO Europe will be presented. Specific goals set by the Joint Action, as well as the importance of a sustainable approach will be highlighted. A discussion on the way forward will focus on how tangible impact can be created in the WHO European Region.</p></sec><sec id="s395"><title>Key messages</title><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Need for effective tools to address novel challenges and successfully monitor and regulate harmful marketing to children.</p><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Need for integration of behavioural science and strong collaborations to create real impact.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>