<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11436986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">52111</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-52111-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exposing disparities in flood adaptation for equitable future interventions in the USA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9018-0241</contrib-id><name><surname>Cano Pecharroman</surname><given-names>Lidia</given-names></name><address><email>LCano@mit.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>ChangHoon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/042nb2s44</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.116068.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2341 2786</institution-id><institution>Department of Urban Studies and Planning, </institution><institution>Massachusetts Institute of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Cambridge, MA USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00hx57361</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16750.35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2097 5006</institution-id><institution>Department of Astrophysical Sciences, </institution><institution>Princeton University, </institution></institution-wrap>Princeton, NJ USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>8333</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">As governments race to implement new climate adaptation solutions that prepare for more frequent flooding, they must seek policies that are effective for all communities and uphold climate justice. This requires evaluating policies not only on their overall effectiveness but also on whether they benefit all communities. Using the USA as an example, we illustrate the importance of considering such disparities for flood adaptation through a FEMA dataset of &#x000a0;~&#x000a0;2.5 million flood insurance claims. We use C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc>, a causal inference method based on deep generative models, to estimate the treatment effect of flood adaptation interventions based on a community&#x02019;s income, racial demographics, population, flood risk, educational attainment, and precipitation. We find that the program saves communities $5,000&#x02013;15,000 per household. However, these savings are not evenly spread across communities. For example, for low-income communities savings sharply decline as flood-risk increases in contrast to their high-income counterparts. Even among low-income communities, savings are &#x0003e;$6,000 per household higher in predominantly white communities. Future flood adaptation efforts should go beyond reducing losses overall and aim to equitably support communities in the race for climate adaptation.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Flood adaptation policies are effective at reducing overall losses from flooding. By leveraging deep generative models, this work reveals new evidence from the US that the benefits are spread disproportionately across communities.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Governance</kwd><kwd>Economics</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Flooding constitutes nearly a third of all losses from natural disasters worldwide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. In the US alone, flooding causes more damage than any other severe weather-related event, with annual losses averaging over $5 billion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. These losses are only expected to multiply as climate change raises the sea level and increases the frequency of extreme weather events<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. By the end of the century, rising sea levels and coastal flooding are estimated to cost the global economy $14.2 trillion, a fifth of the global GDP, in damaged assets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. In response, communities are rapidly enacting flood adaptation measures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. As these measures have emerged so has evidence of their success<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. However, there is still a gap in understanding whether and how the effectiveness varies across different communities.</p><p id="Par4">A better understanding of the effectiveness of flood adaptation policies and their connections to the communities implementing them can ensure that they have the intended effect. It can also ensure that flood adaptation investments deliver on the desired goals and effectively allocate limited resources for climate adaptation. Furthermore, it can prevent climate interventions from unknowingly replicating historical patterns of discrimination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. This is especially critical in light of recent evidence highlighting patterns of inequality in flood preparedness and recovery processes in the US<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">In 1990, FEMA initiated the National Flood Insurance Program (NFIP) Community Rating System (CRS) in order to improve community flood adaptation and resilience. The program is based on a set of prescriptive activities recognized as best practices for flood risk reduction. These constitute flood adaptation recommendations that are prevalent in flood planning across the world. To join the CRS, communities must implement a series of flood adaptation activities: e.g., floodplain mapping, open space preservation, stormwater management activities, or public information and participation programs. In exchange, residents of the community receive a discount on their flood insurance premium rates. More than 1500 out of roughly 20,000 communities in the NFIP are currently part of the CRS program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">In 2019, FEMA released the NFIP Redacted Claims data set that contains roughly 2.5 million flood insurance claims. It contains claims from communities participating in the CRS as well as claims from communities who did not participate in the CRS, but were eligible for insurance coverage because they complied with minimum floodplain regulation requirements. Thus, the Redacted Claims data set provides an ideal quasi-experimental setup (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Insurance claims from flood&#x000a0;losses, which can be used as a proxy for flood loss, can be compared between CRS participants and non-participants to quantitatively assess the effectiveness of the CRS flood adaptation activities.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>We compile our dataset from the FEMA FIMA NFIP Redacted Claims dataset with additional information on community geo-demographic characteristics (precipitation, flood risk, income, population, renter fraction, educational attainment, and racial and ethnic minority fraction) from additional datasets (Section III A).</title><p>Communities that participated in the CRS are part of the treated group (orange), while the communities that did not are part of control group (blue).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e228"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">Capitalizing on this quasi-experimental setup, past literature has examined whether the CRS led to a reduction in flood claims<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Despite some studies finding the contrary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, the overall consensus is that flood losses are reduced by the CRS. There has been, however, little investigation on whether the program&#x02019;s effectiveness varies across different types of communities. There is also a lack of systematic analyses on the disparities in flood adaptation initiatives across communities in the broader international literature.</p><p id="Par8">Beyond the CRS, past work has shown that low-income communities respond to risks differently to safeguard their livelihoods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and deploy flood-coping mechanisms in the absence of flood protection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Studies have also highlighted the need to promote pro-poor climate adaptation initiatives and to strengthen low-income household&#x02019;s asset base to improve their adaptation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Furthermore, some studies have predicted flood losses and vulnerabilities for different types of communities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, no work so far quantifies how the benefits/savings of flood adaptation activities are distributed across different communities. That is the main goal of this paper.</p><p id="Par9">In this work, we reexamine the effectiveness of flood adaptation interventions through the CRS. We evaluate whether they are effective and also identify the types of communities that benefit the most from their implementation. We use C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc> to measure the effectiveness of the CRS as a function of key community characteristics such as population, income, race, and educational attainment at high-resolution on a zip code level over the entire continental US. C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc> is a novel data-driven method that leverages deep generative models and accurately measures the causal effect of flood adaptation policies while accounting for its non-linear, complex, and correlated dependence on community characteristics. Our results shed light on the community characteristics most associated with the effectiveness of flood adaptation interventions and provide key insight for how communities should tailor such interventions. They also provide a path forward to re-envisioning flood adaptation in ways that can benefit a broader spectrum of communities in the face of climate change.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>The effectiveness of flood adaptation measures</title><p id="Par10">With C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc>, we can estimate the impact of the CRS flood adaptation activities on the total insurance claims paid per policy for any set of community (zip code) characteristics. In other words, we can measure the &#x0201c;treatment effect&#x0201d; of implementing CRS activities and quantify how much a policyholder saves on average thanks to the program. In order to systematize our results, we define 27 distinct community typologies by population, income, and racial composition. For each community property, we identify three bins (low, medium, and high) corresponding to the 16, 50, and 84th percentiles of the full data set (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Then the typologies are defined by distinct combinations of the three bins of the three different properties. For further detail see Section&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">D</xref> in Supplementary Information. Then, we compute their CATE&#x02019; for different values of average precipitation, flood risk, renter fraction, and educational attainment.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Income, population, and racial and ethnic minority fraction values used to define the 27 community typologies for which we examine the CRS savings</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Low</th><th>Mid</th><th>High</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Median Income (USD)</td><td>40,000</td><td>60,000</td><td>90,000</td></tr><tr><td>Population</td><td>2500</td><td>12,000</td><td>30,000</td></tr><tr><td>Racial and Ethnic Minority Fraction</td><td>0.05</td><td>0.15</td><td>0.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>For the typologies, we use all possible permutations of the low, mid, and high values.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par11">In Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, we present the CATE&#x02019; of all 27 community typologies as a function of (a) average precipitation, (b) educational attainment, and (c) FSF flood risk score. In each panel, we vary a single characteristic while keeping all others fixed. We do this for each typology, represented by a single line. This enables us to isolate and examine the effect of a specific characteristic on the CATE&#x02019;. We represent the uncertainties on CATE&#x02019;, derived using standard error of the mean, in one of the high income communities in panel (c). The uncertainties on CATE&#x02019; for the communities do not vary significantly and range between $180 to $300. Overall, we find that the CRS saving for policyholders can range from $5000 to $15,000 per policy. For certain communities, the savings can exceed $20,000. Our findings are consistent with previous evidence, which found that the CRS led to a 40 percent reduction in losses at the county level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> and a $2.8&#x02013;$5.5 million reduction in damages for a particular flood event<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Flood loss savings from the CRS program (CATE&#x02019;) for 27 community typologies with different population, income, and racial composition.</title><p>In each panel, we vary a single community characteristic to highlight its impact on CRS savings: (<bold>a</bold>) average monthly precipitation, (<bold>b</bold>) educational attainment, and (<bold>c</bold>) flood risk score. All other characteristics are fixed to fiducial values. For reference, we include the uncertainties on CATE' for one of the high income communities in (<bold>c</bold>). In (<bold>a</bold>), we highlight predominantly racial and ethnic minority communities with high population and mid to high income (black dotted), which are mostly in urban areas. In (<bold>c</bold>), we mark the communities with high and low income in teal and cyan, respectively. The CRS saves policyholders an average of <italic>$</italic>5000&#x02013;<italic>$</italic>15,000 per policy. However, the efficacy of flood adaption depends significantly on income, population, race, precipitation, educational attainment, and flood risk.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e399"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Beyond estimating the overall savings on flood losses, we can also assess the CRS by examining the effect of average precipitation on savings. Flood losses are typically worsened by compounded water runoff from higher precipitation [e.g., refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>]. Yet in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, we find that for nearly all of the community typologies (&#x0003e;95%), the CRS savings increase with higher average precipitation. Our results firmly illustrate the CRS program&#x02019;s effectiveness in mitigating flood losses.</p><p id="Par13">The program&#x02019;s overall success, however, does not paint the full story. Our results show that while the CRS is effective, the benefits are not felt evenly across different communities. This serves as critical evidence for rethinking and reimagining future flood adaptation policies that aim to equitably reduce flood losses for all communities. In the following, we present two lines of action in designing and evaluating future strategies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Tailored Requirements and Resources</title><p id="Par14">Community characteristics play a major role in the effectiveness of current flood adaptation measures. To increase flood savings for <italic>all</italic> communities will require tailoring such measures. For example, while the CRS is effective at reducing flood losses at higher precipitation, certain communities go against this trend. In particular, communities with high percentages of racial and ethnic minorities, with high population and mid to high income (black dotted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a), see their savings steeply decrease with higher precipitation&#x02014;i.e., flood adaptation measures are less effective. A geospatial analysis of these communities indicates that nearly all of them are in urban areas (see Section&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">E</xref> in Supplementary Information). Urbanized areas have higher percentages of impervious surfaces that increase water runoff and can cause or worsen flooding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. For these urban communities, flood adaptation programs should require activities geared towards e.g., decreasing surface imperviousness.</p><p id="Par15">We also find a significant population dependence. In Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, we present the CRS savings for the 27 community typologies as a function of precipitation, flood risk score, and educational attainment, same as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. We highlight the communities with a high population in orange and a low population in blue. Overall, flood adaptation measures are more effective for high population communities. They save &#x000a0;~$4000 per policy more than less populated communities. Combined with previous work, which found that highly populated communities are also more likely to adopt CRS activities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, our results suggest that flood adaptation programs favor populous communities.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>The population dependence on the CRS savings.</title><p>We present the CRS savings for the 27 community typologies, same as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, highlighting the high population (orange) and low population (blue) communities. The rest of the communities, with mid population, are marked in gray. Flood adaptation measures are more effective for high population communities, who save &#x000a0;~$4&#x000a0;000 per policy more than low population communities.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e454"/></fig></p><p id="Par16">Less populated communities may not have the personpower required to implement the prescribed activities, e.g., lacking access to public servants and workers with a wide range of technical expertise. The smaller tax base may also limit the resources available to implement flood adaptation. In field interviews, we found that the acquisition or relocation of flood-prone buildings was limited by the lack of resources available at the local level (Section III C). The implementation of some CRS activities may also require the types of public services or resources that are not economically feasible for small communities. For instance, the implementation of a flood mapping exercise may prove resource-intensive. Hence, future programs should provide the necessary technical support and incentivize collaboration among adjacent communities. Although not explored in this study, population density, beyond population alone, could also play a role in the effectiveness of programs like the CRS.</p><p id="Par17">Finally, we find that the effectiveness of the CRS depends on the communities&#x02019; educational attainment. In Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, we present the CRS savings for the 27 community typologies as a function of educational attainment, which we define as the fraction of inhabitants with a Bachelor&#x02019;s or higher degree. Past evidence already suggests that there is an initial barrier to joining the CRS related to education, where communities with higher educational attainment are more likely to participate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Our results show that even after communities join, the effectiveness hinges on their education. The dependence on education translates into a gap of up to &#x000a0;~$2&#x000a0;000 per policy in savings.</p><p id="Par18">Out of the 19 creditable activities that communities can implement, many require capacity building and technical expertise: e.g., the establishment of flood warning systems and the building and inspection of levees. Communities with lower educational attainment may find barriers to access the required resources or, as suggested in past literature community buy-in for flood management may be more difficult. In response, future programs should include interventions that reduce the educational/technical barriers and provide the necessary technical assistance along with tailored community outreach resources.</p><p id="Par19">The trends presented in this section make it clear that future flood adaptation programs should tailor their required adaptation measures. This is particularly important when there are rewards or incentives for implementing the measures, such as the lowering of insurance premiums in the CRS. If programs reward a community&#x02019;s adaptation, then not all &#x0201c;low-hanging fruit&#x0201d; interventions should qualify for the reward. Instead, communities should be required to implement the types of flood adaptation interventions that are most effective for their needs. At the same time, future programs must furnish communities with the necessary resources to overcome any financial/technical/educational barriers in complying with such requirements. Only then we can expect a just and equitable distribution of the benefits of climate adaptation. Next, we illustrate the importance of considering the inequities and disparities of flood adaptation programs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Climate justice</title><p id="Par20">An effective and far-reaching flood adaptation strategy requires embedding climate justice at its core. Our results show that the effectiveness of a program is tied to economic disparities and disparities between predominantly white communities, and predominantly racial and ethnic minority communities. For example, although flood adaptation is effective overall for low-income communities, it is less effective when they are located in high flood-risk zones. The trend is reversed for affluent communities. We highlight this in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, where we show CRS savings as a function of flood risk for low (light blue) and high-income (dark blue) communities. Our results suggest that the most economical CRS activities may only be effective at lower risk. Meanwhile, interventions that fare well at higher risk can only be afforded by high-income communities. Evidently, flood adaptation cannot be left to a community&#x02019;s resources alone, especially since average annual flood losses are disproportionately borne by poorer communities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par21">Furthermore, we find that even within low-income communities, there is a systematic gap in the CRS savings between predominantly white and racial and ethnic minority communities. In Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, we present the CRS savings for predominantly white (dotted) and racial and ethnic minority (solid) communities with low income. Since the highlighted communities have the same low income, the comparison between the solid and dotted lines illustrates the sole effect of race. Overall, the program is significantly less effective for racial and ethnic minority communities. In some cases, the gap exceeds $6000 per policy. This points to the program&#x02019;s inability to breach existing patterns of discrimination and racial inequality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>CRS savings for predominantly racial and ethnic minority (predom. non-white; solid) and white (predom. white; dotted) communities with low income as a function of precipitation (left), educational attainment (center), and flood risk (right).</title><p>We include the other community typologies for reference (gray). Although both communities have the same income level, highly diverse communities have significantly lower flood loss savings. The gap between white and racial and ethnic minority communities exists for low (blue; top), mid (green; middle), and high (orange; bottom) populations (pop.). This racial gap exceeds $6000 per policy in certain cases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e503"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">This gap is consistent with patterns of inequality found in flood preparedness and recovery more broadly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Reference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> exposed inequalities in the delineation of flood zones in FEMA maps, where &#x0201c;Black and Asian neighborhoods experience disproportionate risk in federally overlooked pluvial and fluvial flood zones&#x0201d; (p.1). Other works have shown that the type of flood adaptation measures employed correlate with racial diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Measures like &#x0201c;retreat&#x0201d; correlate with high racial diversity while measures like &#x0201c;shoreline armoring&#x0201d; correlate with low racial diversity. Such differences reflect the real choices that historically disenfranchised communities make based on the accessibility of certain types of solutions.</p><p id="Par23">We show that flood adaptation programs can perpetuate institutional racism, through tangible effects on savings, or lack thereof. Future programs should re-examine the processes, structures, and existing assumptions of flood adaptation prescriptions and incentives under the lens of equity, race, and inclusion. This will be particularly salient as the evidence overwhelmingly shows that the most disadvantaged communities are projected to suffer the most from the consequences of climate change. Embedding these priorities at the core of future programs will be crucial to close existing gaps and support all communities in mitigating flood losses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Considerations moving forward</title><p id="Par24">In this work, we find clear trends between flood loss savings and community characteristics. This provides strong evidence that the success of future flood adaptation interventions should not only be measured based on whether they reduce losses, but also on whether the benefits are equitably distributed. Below, we discuss some of the caveats and limitations of our work and outline future research.</p><p id="Par25">First, we note that our results are measured using data from households with access to flood insurance. Hence, our results do not reflect the communities without flood insurance. Even though the threshold to access it is relatively low, it is not negligible. While some of the communities without insurance face no significant flood risks, those that do disproportionately include households without access.</p><p id="Par26"><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> found that income of policyholders was higher than of non-policyholders: a quarter of policyholders are classified as lower income, while the fraction is over a half for non-policyholders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The income disparity between policyholders and non-policyholders is also found in special flood hazard areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, thus suggesting that affordability is a significant barrier to access insurance. While we cannot quantify flood losses for uninsured communities using our dataset, given the gaps in savings that we find between high income and low income communities, we expect including the losses of uninsured communities would only further widen the gaps.</p><p id="Par27">We also note that the savings estimates in this work are conservative. In calculating the CRS savings, we correct for the outreach component, where communities receive information on how to successfully file their claims (<italic>&#x00394;</italic><italic>Y</italic> in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>)). This correction is estimated by comparing non-CRS communities to CRS communities that participated in activities for public information and scored below 10% on all other activities. The ideal comparison would be to compare non-participants to CRS communities that only participated in public information activities. However, this includes very few communities, so we relax this selection. This likely leads to an underestimate of <italic>&#x00394;</italic><italic>Y</italic> and, thus, the CRS savings. Furthermore, our control group consists of communities that did not participate in the CRS but have access to the NFIP, which requires them to regulate floodplain development. Although the requirements are minimal, they may already have a slight effect in reducing losses, which would also make our savings estimate conservative. Subsequent work explores the impact of the outreach component in further detail by examining the proportion of successful payments before and after the implementation of the CRS. Along these lines, we also find signs that the outreach component could be driving elite capture. Savings on flood losses decline for communities with the highest levels of educational attainment (&#x0003e;50%; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). Field interviews support the possibility that some households are learning to &#x0201c;game the system&#x0201d; in order to refurbish their homes after a flooding event. Further research, however, is necessary for a more systematic understanding.</p><p id="Par28">Our estimate of flood loss savings is also conservative because preventing damage to homes mitigates further ripple effects in the livelihoods and well-being of communities. Exposure to flood-damaged homes is linked to an increase in mental and health disorders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, death and injury risk, disease outbreaks [e.g., gastroenteritis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>], trauma, anxiety<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, and work disruption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. For every dollar saved in flood losses in our results, we can expect a far larger reduction in the true loss.</p><p id="Par29">This study underscores the importance of accounting for complex dependencies when evaluating the effectiveness of adaptation efforts and designing future ones. The CRS, as a program that prescribes a wide range of flood adaptation interventions, serves as an ideal example to showcase the importance of evaluating these efforts from a climate justice lens.</p><p id="Par30">In subsequent work, we will extend this analysis to go beyond assessing the impact of simply participating in the CRS. We will examine the impact of CRS activities and provide specific insights on how communities can capitalize on different solutions depending on their characteristics.</p><p id="Par31">The complex dynamics of climate change require a granular understanding of its effect as well as the impact of interventions aimed to combat it. In this regard, the rapid development of deep generative models presents a unique opportunity to move beyond current causal inference approaches. Together with increased investment in data generation, C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc> and similar approaches will be capable of addressing previously intractable causal inference queries that are crucial in designing future policy interventions.</p><p id="Par32">In summary, this study shows that even though current flood adaptation practices reduce flood losses, the savings vary greatly across communities. Future adaptation pathways need to consider key community characteristics in providing the necessary solutions and resources. They must also embed equity priorities at their core to break existing patterns of inequality and discrimination so that <italic>all</italic> communities can benefit from climate adaptation investment into the future.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data</title><p id="Par33">For this work, we compile a dataset based on the FEMA Flood Insurance Mitigation Administration NFIP Redacted Claims data with additional information on community characteristics. We use the publicly available NFIP dataset at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fema.gov/openfema-data-page/fima-nfip-redacted-claims-v1">https://www.fema.gov/openfema-data-page/fima-nfip-redacted-claims-v1</ext-link>. From this dataset, we use data on CRS participation, the date of flood loss, the total claims paid on building damages and content from the loss, and the number of policies per claim. Each zip code is labeled as either a CRS participant or nonparticipant. CRS participation takes place at the jurisdictional level (municipality, city, borough, and sometimes county). If a zip code is embedded within a participating jurisdiction, it is considered a participant. We combine all the entries for a zip code and calculate the average amount paid per policy for each claim.</p><p id="Par34">For each zip code, which we refer to as a community, we quantify its flood risk using scores compiled in the First Street Foundation (FSF) dataset, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://firststreet.org/data-access/getting-started-with-first-street-data/">https://firststreet.org/data-access/getting-started-with-first-street-data/</ext-link>. The risk scores are computed based on factors including risk of flooding from high-intensity rainfall, overflowing rivers and streams, high tides, and coastal storm surges. They are also based on hydrological models at the watershed scale, which considers geographic characteristics. While the consideration of risk at the zip code level is not reflective of the exact flood risk of a particular property, it provides the overall flood risk surrounding the property. We further supplement the dataset with census data from the US Census Bureau American Community Survey: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/acs/news/data-releases.html">https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/acs/news/data-releases.html</ext-link>. The census is compiled in 4 year intervals: 2008&#x02013;2012, 2012&#x02013;2016, and 2016&#x02013;2020. We assign median income and number of residents (population) of the communities based on their zip code and date of loss. We also calculate the fraction of residents that rent, have a Bachelor&#x02019;s degree or more advanced degrees, and do not identify as only white. We refer to each of the characteristics as the renter fraction, educational attainment, and fraction of racial and ethnic minorities, respectively.</p><p id="Par35">Lastly, we include average precipitation in millimeters during the month of the flood loss, as in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. This considers the average precipitation over the entire month of the flooding event and, thus, accounts for the potential impact of compound rainfall. This data was extracted by splitting the PRISM climate group data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://prism.oregonstate.edu/">https://prism.oregonstate.edu/</ext-link>) compiled by the Northwest Alliance for Computational Science and Engineering using US zip code boundaries from 2020. The use of the average precipitation in mm during the month of loss aims at capturing the potential effects of compounded precipitation as a factor that may influence the effects of flooding and the effectiveness of flood prevention measures.</p><p id="Par36">In total, our dataset includes 14,729 unique communities. In Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, we plot the communities that are included in our dataset (blue and orange) on a map of the US. Our final dataset is publicly available at 10.5281/zenodo.13135690.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc></title><p id="Par37">One of the main goals of causal inference is to measure the treatment effect of a policy, like the CRS. For heterogeneous treatments, the effect is quantified using the conditional average treatment effect (CATE), the ATE as a function of covariates. By revealing the dependence of the treatment effect on covariates, CATE provides a more detailed understanding of the causal path. Given outcome <italic>Y</italic>, covariates <italic>X</italic>, and variable <italic>T</italic> that indicates the control (<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) or treated (<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) groups, CATE is estimated as:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{{{\rm{CATE}}}}}=E[\,Y\,| \,X,T=1\,]-E[\,Y\,| \,X,T=0\,].$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CATE</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><italic>E</italic>[<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;&#x02009;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0,&#x000a0;1] represents the expected value of <italic>Y</italic> given <italic>X</italic> for the control and treated groups, respectively.</p><p id="Par38">Typically, CATE is estimated using either matching or linear regression. In matching, samples in the treated group are matched to ones in the control based on their <italic>X</italic> values. CATE is then estimated by comparing the outcomes of the matched samples. Even prevalent methods, such as synthetic control<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> or propensity score matching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, match samples based on some finite volume in covariate space, which can lead to incorrect estimates of the CATE.</p><p id="Par39">The other approach is regression, most commonly with linear models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. A model of <italic>Y</italic> as a linear function of <italic>X</italic> is fit to the data and then used to estimate CATE. In many scenarios, assuming a linear model is incorrect. For instance, there is no reason to expect flood losses to depend linearly on its population, or median household income. Furthermore, there is often no a priori knowledge of the functional form that should be adopted for a model of <italic>Y</italic>.</p><p id="Par40">We can instead estimate the CATE without any of these assumptions. We rewrite Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) as<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{{{\rm{CATE}}}}}=\int\,Yp(Y| X,T=1)\,{{{{\rm{d}}}}}Y-\int\,Yp(Y| X,T=0)\,{{{{\rm{d}}}}}Y,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CATE</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>p</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) and <italic>p</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) are the conditional probability distribution of <italic>Y</italic> given <italic>X</italic> for the treated and control groups. If we can estimate <italic>p</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1)&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;<italic>q</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>) and <italic>p</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0)&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;<italic>q</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>) and sample from them, <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${Y}_{T,i}^{{\prime} } \sim {q}_{T}(Y| X)\,{{{{\rm{and}}}}}\,{Y}_{C,\, j}^{{\prime} } \sim {q}_{C}(Y| X)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, we can estimate CATE using Monte Carlo integration:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{{{\rm{CATE}}}}}=\frac{1}{{N}_{T}}\sum\limits_{i=1}^{{N}_{T}}{Y}_{T,i}^{{\prime} }-\frac{1}{{N}_{C}}\sum\limits_{j=1}^{{N}_{C}}{Y}_{C,\, j}^{{\prime} }.$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CATE</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par41">Deep generative models from machine learning (e.g., ChatGPT, Dall-E) enable us to accurately estimate and sample from <italic>p</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0,&#x000a0;1). In this work, we use normalizing flow models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, which use a bijective transformation, <italic>f</italic>&#x02009;:&#x000a0;<italic>z</italic>&#x000a0;&#x021a6;&#x000a0;<italic>x</italic>, that maps a complex target distribution, <italic>p</italic>(<italic>x</italic>), to a simple base distribution, <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>(<italic>z</italic>), in our case a Gaussian. <italic>f</italic> is defined to be invertible and to have a tractable Jacobian so that target distribution can be evaluated from the base distribution: <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p(x)=\pi (z)| \det {\frac{\partial f}{\partial x}}^{-1}|$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. A neural network is used for <italic>f</italic> to provide an extremely flexible mapping that can estimate complex distributions. This neural density estimation approach has been used extensively in a variety of fields spanning neuroscience [e.g., ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>] to astrophysics [e.g., refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>]</p><p id="Par42">Using normalizing flows, in particular the Masked Autoregressive Flow [MAF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>] models implemented by<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>, we estimate <italic>p</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1)&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;<italic>q</italic><sub>T</sub>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;&#x02009;<italic>X</italic>) and <italic>p</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0)&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;<italic>q</italic><sub>C</sub>(<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;&#x02223;<italic>X</italic>) for the treated and control groups separately. We describe the training and validation of our normalizing flows <italic>q</italic><sub>T</sub> and <italic>q</italic><sub>C</sub> in Section&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">A</xref> of Supplementary Information. Our outcome, <italic>Y</italic>, is the total insurance claims payments per policy in dollars. We use seven covariates, <italic>X</italic>: precipitation, flood risk, income, population, renter fraction, educational attainment, and fraction of racial and ethnic minorities (Section III A). The treated group consists of communities participating in the CRS, while the control group consists of non-participants. In Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, we mark the communities in the treated (orange) and control (blue) groups of our dataset.</p><p id="Par43">Once trained, we can evaluate CATE at <italic>any</italic> given value of the covariates using <italic>q</italic><sub>T</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>C</sub>, and Eq. (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>), as long as it is within the support of the covariates in our data. We detail how we ensure this in Section&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">B</xref> of Supplementary Information. Our approach, which we call C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc>, relaxes the strong assumptions made in standard causal inference methods. It learns the detailed relationship between <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> from the data to provide an accurate and robust estimate of the treatment effect. C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc> was specifically developed for this work. However, it is designed more broadly to answer causal inference questions that involve high-dimensional and nuanced relations between outcome and covariates. We emphasize that C<sc>ausal</sc>F<sc>low</sc> can be applied to other quasi- experimental setups across the social sciences. The software is publicly available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/changhoonhahn/causalCRS">https://github.com/changhoonhahn/causalCRS</ext-link>.</p><p id="Par44">Lastly, we introduce a correction, <italic>&#x00394;</italic><italic>Y</italic>, to the CATE to account for the outreach component of the CRS program:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{{{{\rm{CATE}}}}}}^{{\prime} }={{{{\rm{CATE}}}}}+\Delta Y.$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CATE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CATE</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Communities in the treated group are informed of how to successfully file their claims. The outreach component alone increases the total insurance claims paid per policy by <italic>&#x00394;</italic><italic>Y</italic>&#x000a0;~&#x000a0;$9,&#x000a0;780 (see Section&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">C</xref> of Supplementary Information for details). Since this increase is not a reflection of any change in flood losses, the CATE in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>) underestimates the impact of the CRS. Thus, we include <italic>&#x00394;</italic><italic>Y</italic> and correct for the effect of outreach to more accurately quantify the treatment effect on flood loss. Throughout this work, we refer to <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{{{{\rm{CATE}}}}}}^{{\prime} }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CATE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> as the CRS savings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Interviews</title><p id="Par45">To provide additional insight and intrepretation of the analysis in the paper, we conducted 15 elite interviews with academics and government employees from FEMA, Massachusetts Emergency Management Agency, National Aeronautics and Space Administration, and the National Academy of Sciences. We also conducted 21 semi-structured interviews across two CRS communities to government officials, civil society, business owners, and community members. Stratified sampling was used to select interviewees according to the following categories: government officials, civil society, first responders, and business owners. The questionnaires used in the interviews were submitted to the MIT Committee on the Use of Humans as Experimental Subjects (COUHES). Due to the subject and content of the study, Institutional Review Board (IRB) approval was waived via Protocol ID: E-2829 - PhD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="Par46">Further information on research design is available in the&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">Nature Portfolio Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41467_2024_52111_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41467-024-52111-0.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>It&#x02019;s a pleasure to thank Mariana Arcaya, Peter Melchior, A.R Siders, and Lawrence Susskind for valuable discussions&#x000a0;at different stages of this research. L.C.P. was supported by the La Caixa Foundation and by the Martin Family Society of Fellows. C.H. was supported by the AI Accelerator program of the Schmidt Futures Foundation.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>L.C.P. and C.H. designed research, performed the data analysis, and wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="peer-review"><title>Peer review</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Peer review information</title><p id="Par47"><italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks James R Elliott and the other, anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work. A peer review file is available.</p></sec></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All of the data generated in this study have been deposited in the Zenodo database under the accession code: 10.5281/zenodo.13135690. Restrictions apply to the availability of First Street Foundation data, which were used under license for the current study and are not publicly available. Interview data are not publicly available as per compliance of IRB protocol to remain anonymous.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p>All of the code used in this paper is publicly available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/changhoonhahn/causalCRS">https://github.com/changhoonhahn/causalCRS</ext-link>.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par48">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dickie, G. Global Flood losses hit <italic>$</italic>82 bln last year, as study highlights UK risk <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.reuters.com/business/environment/global-flood-losses-hit-82-bln-last-year-study-highlights-uk-risk-2022-03-30/">https://www.reuters.com/business/environment/global-flood-losses-hit-82-bln-last-year-study-highlights-uk-risk-2022-03-30/</ext-link> (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. Flood FAQ <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nssl.noaa.gov/education/svrwx101/floods/faq/">https://www.nssl.noaa.gov/education/svrwx101/floods/faq/</ext-link> (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing intensity of hydroclimatic extreme events revealed by GRACE and GRACE-FO</article-title><source>Nat. Water</source><year>2023</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s44221-023-00040-5</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Rodell, M. &#x00026; Li, B. Changing intensity of hydroclimatic extreme events revealed by GRACE and GRACE-FO. <italic>Nat. Water</italic><bold>1</bold>, 241&#x02013;248 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirezci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Projections of global-scale extreme sea levels and resulting episodic coastal flooding over the 21st Century</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>11629</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-67736-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32732976?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32732976</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Kirezci, E. et al. Projections of global-scale extreme sea levels and resulting episodic coastal flooding over the 21st Century. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 11629 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32732976</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jongman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increasing stress on disaster-risk finance due to large floods</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate2124</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Jongman, B. et al. Increasing stress on disaster-risk finance due to large floods. <italic>Nat. Clim. Change</italic><bold>4</bold>, 264&#x02013;268 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Luther</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing risk of compound flooding from storm surge and rainfall for major US cities</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Chang.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1097</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate2736</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Wahl, T., Jain, S., Bender, J., Meyers, S. D. &#x00026; Luther, M. E. Increasing risk of compound flooding from storm surge and rainfall for major US cities. <italic>Nat. Clim. Chang.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 1093&#x02013;1097 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feyen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Baldassarre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing flood risk under climate change: a pan-European assessment of the benefits of four adaptation strategies</article-title><source>Clim. Chang.</source><year>2016</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-016-1641-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Alfieri, L., Feyen, L. &#x00026; Di Baldassarre, G. Increasing flood risk under climate change: a pan-European assessment of the benefits of four adaptation strategies. <italic>Clim. Chang.</italic><bold>136</bold>, 507&#x02013;521 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Deegan, M. <italic>Exploring U.S. Flood Mitigation Policies: A Feedback View of System Behaviour</italic> Vol. 25, 76 (Rockefeller College of Public Affairs &#x00026; Policy, Department of Public Administration Policy, 2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Highfield</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determining the effects of the FEMA Community Rating System program on flood losses in the United States</article-title><source>Int. J. Disaster Risk Reduct.</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2017.01.013</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Highfield, W. E. &#x00026; Brody, S. D. Determining the effects of the FEMA Community Rating System program on flood losses in the United States. <italic>Int. J. Disaster Risk Reduct.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 396&#x02013;404 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Asche, E. A. <italic>The Effect of Flood Risk on Housing Choices and Community Hazard Mitigation</italic>. Ph.D. thesis, University of California, Santa Barbara (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Highfield</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhardt</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedlitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Policy learning for flood mitigation: a longitudinal assessment of the community rating system in Florida</article-title><source>Risk Anal.</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>912</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1539-6924.2009.01210.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19302277?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19302277</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Brody, S. D., Zahran, S., Highfield, W. E., Bernhardt, S. P. &#x00026; Vedlitz, A. Policy learning for flood mitigation: a longitudinal assessment of the community rating system in Florida. <italic>Risk Anal.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 912&#x02013;929 (2009).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19302277</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davlasheridze, M., Fisher-Vanden, K. &#x00026; Klaiber, H. A. The higher order impacts of hurricane: evidence from county level analysis. 2013 Annual Meeting, August 4&#x02013;6, 2013, Washington, D.C. 150196, Agricultural and Applied Economics Association <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ideas.repec.org/p/ags/aaea13/150196.html">https://ideas.repec.org/p/ags/aaea13/150196.html</ext-link> (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kousky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel-Kerjan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining flood insurance claims in the United States: six key findings</article-title><source>J. Risk Insur.</source><year>2017</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jori.12106</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Kousky, C. &#x00026; Michel-Kerjan, E. Examining flood insurance claims in the United States: six key findings. <italic>J. Risk Insur.</italic><bold>84</bold>, 819&#x02013;850 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Who benefits from environmental policy? An environmental justice analysis of air quality change in Britain, 2001&#x02013;2011</article-title><source>Environ. Res. Lett.</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>105009</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/10/10/105009</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Mitchell, G., Norman, P. &#x00026; Mullin, K. Who benefits from environmental policy? An environmental justice analysis of air quality change in Britain, 2001&#x02013;2011. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 105009 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decolonizing climate change&#x02013;heritage research</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41558-022-01279-8</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Simpson, N. P. et al. Decolonizing climate change&#x02013;heritage research. <italic>Nat. Clim. Change</italic><bold>12</bold>, 210&#x02013;213 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranganathan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bratman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From urban resilience to abolitionist climate justice in Washington, DC</article-title><source>Antipode</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/anti.12555</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Ranganathan, M. &#x00026; Bratman, E. From urban resilience to abolitionist climate justice in Washington, DC. <italic>Antipode</italic><bold>53</bold>, 115&#x02013;137 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal and spatial changes in social vulnerability to natural hazards</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>2301</fpage><lpage>2306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0710375105</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18268336?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18268336</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Cutter, S. L. &#x00026; Finch, C. Temporal and spatial changes in social vulnerability to natural hazards. <italic>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>105</bold>, 2301&#x02013;2306 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18268336</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emrich</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring social equity in flood recovery funding</article-title><source>Environ. Hazards</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17477891.2019.1675578</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Emrich, C. T., Tate, E., Larson, S. E. &#x00026; Zhou, Y. Measuring social equity in flood recovery funding. <italic>Environ. Hazards</italic><bold>19</bold>, 228&#x02013;250 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Emrich</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flood exposure and social vulnerability in the United States</article-title><source>Nat. Hazards</source><year>2021</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11069-020-04470-2</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Tate, E., Rahman, M. A., Emrich, C. T. &#x00026; Sampson, C. C. Flood exposure and social vulnerability in the United States. <italic>Nat. Hazards</italic><bold>106</bold>, 435&#x02013;457 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>OEJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inequitable patterns of US flood risk in the Anthropocene</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Chang.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41558-021-01265-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Wing, O. E. J. et al. Inequitable patterns of US flood risk in the Anthropocene. <italic>Nat. Clim. Chang.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 156&#x02013;162 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Federally overlooked flood risk inequities in Houston, Texas: novel insights based on dasymetric mapping and state-of-the-art flood modeling</article-title><source>Ann. Am. Assoc. Geogr.</source><year>2023</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>260</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Flores, A. B. et al. Federally overlooked flood risk inequities in Houston, Texas: novel insights based on dasymetric mapping and state-of-the-art flood modeling. <italic>Ann. Am. Assoc. Geogr.</italic><bold>113</bold>, 240&#x02013;260 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Federal Emergency Management Agency. Community Rating System &#x02223; FEMA.gov <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fema.gov/fact-sheet/community-rating-system">https://www.fema.gov/fact-sheet/community-rating-system</ext-link> (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel-Kerjan</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kousky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Come rain or shine: evidence on flood insurance purchases in Florida</article-title><source>J. Risk Insur.</source><year>2010</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1539-6975.2009.01349.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Michel-Kerjan, E. O. &#x00026; Kousky, C. Come rain or shine: evidence on flood insurance purchases in Florida. <italic>J. Risk Insur.</italic><bold>77</bold>, 369&#x02013;397 (2010).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gourevitch, J. &#x00026; Pinter, N. Federal incentives for community-level climate adaptation: an evaluation of FEMA&#x02019;s community rating system. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 034037 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate risk responses and the urban poor in the global South: the case of Dhaka&#x02019;s flood risk in the low-income settlements</article-title><source>Int. J. Disaster Risk Reduct.</source><year>2021</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>102534</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2021.102534</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Haque, A. N. Climate risk responses and the urban poor in the global South: the case of Dhaka&#x02019;s flood risk in the low-income settlements. <italic>Int. J. Disaster Risk Reduct.</italic><bold>64</bold>, 102534 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Akter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brander</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic vulnerability and adaptation to environmental risk: a case study of climate change and flooding in Bangladesh</article-title><source>Risk Anal.</source><year>2007</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1539-6924.2007.00884.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17511700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17511700</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Brouwer, R., Akter, S., Brander, L. &#x00026; Haque, E. Socioeconomic vulnerability and adaptation to environmental risk: a case study of climate change and flooding in Bangladesh. <italic>Risk Anal.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 313&#x02013;326 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17511700</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mearns, R. &#x00026; Norton, A. <italic>Social Dimensions of Climate Change : Equity and Vulnerability in a Warming World</italic> (World Bank, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knighton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting flood insurance claims with hydrologic and socioeconomic demographics via machine learning: exploring the roles of topography, minority populations, and political dissimilarity</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manag.</source><year>2020</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>111051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2020.111051</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Knighton, J. et al. Predicting flood insurance claims with hydrologic and socioeconomic demographics via machine learning: exploring the roles of topography, minority populations, and political dissimilarity. <italic>J. Environ. Manag.</italic><bold>272</bold>, 111051 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>OEJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kousky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into US flood vulnerability revealed from flood insurance big data</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1444</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-15264-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32193386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32193386</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Wing, O. E. J., Pinter, N., Bates, P. D. &#x00026; Kousky, C. New insights into US flood vulnerability revealed from flood insurance big data. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 1444 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32193386</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting flood property insurance claims over conus, fusing big earth observation data</article-title><source>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</source><year>2022</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>E791 &#x02013; E809</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/BAMS-D-21-0082.A</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Yang, Q. et al. Predicting flood property insurance claims over conus, fusing big earth observation data. <italic>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>103</bold>, E791 &#x02013; E809 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bevacqua, E. et al. Higher probability of compound flooding from precipitation and storm surge in Europe under anthropogenic climate change. <italic>Sci. Adv.</italic><bold>5</bold> eaaw5531 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>T-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flood risk estimation under the compound influence of rainfall and tide</article-title><source>J. Hydrol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>606</volume><fpage>127446</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2022.127446</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Jang, J.-H. &#x00026; Chang, T.-H. Flood risk estimation under the compound influence of rainfall and tide. <italic>J. Hydrol.</italic><bold>606</bold>, 127446 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact assessment of climate change on compound flooding in a coastal city</article-title><source>J. Hydrol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>617</volume><fpage>129166</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2023.129166</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Xu, K., Zhuang, Y., Bin, L., Wang, C. &#x00026; Tian, F. Impact assessment of climate change on compound flooding in a coastal city. <italic>J. Hydrol.</italic><bold>617</bold>, 129166 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pasquier</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Vahmani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the city-scale impacts of impervious surfaces on groundwater recharge potential: an urban application of WRF&#x02013;Hydro</article-title><source>Water</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3143</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/w14193143</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Pasquier, U., Vahmani, P. &#x00026; Jones, A. D. Quantifying the city-scale impacts of impervious surfaces on groundwater recharge potential: an urban application of WRF&#x02013;Hydro. <italic>Water</italic><bold>14</bold>, 3143 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Posey, J.<italic>Coping with Climate Change: Toward a Theory of Adaptive Capacity</italic>. Ph.D. thesis, Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, School of Graduate Studies (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, J. <italic>Community Flood Hazard Mitigation and the Community Rating System of National Flood Insurance Program</italic>. Ph.D. thesis, East Carolina University (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fan, Q. &#x00026; Davlasheridze, M. <italic>Evaluating the Effectiveness of Flood Mitigation Policies in the U.S. 2014 Annual Meeting, July 27-29, 2014, Minneapolis, Minnesota</italic> (Agricultural and Applied Economics Association, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siders</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Keenan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variables shaping coastal adaptation decisions to armor, nourish, and retreat in North Carolina</article-title><source>Ocean Coast. Manag.</source><year>2020</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>105023</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2019.105023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Siders, A. R. &#x00026; Keenan, J. M. Variables shaping coastal adaptation decisions to armor, nourish, and retreat in North Carolina. <italic>Ocean Coast. Manag.</italic><bold>183</bold>, 105023 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kousky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunreuther</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>LaCour-Little</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flood risk and the U.S. housing market</article-title><source>J. Hous. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>S3</fpage><lpage>S24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10527001.2020.1836915</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Kousky, C., Kunreuther, H., LaCour-Little, M. &#x00026; Wachter, S. Flood risk and the U.S. housing market. <italic>J. Hous. Res.</italic><bold>29</bold>, S3&#x02013;S24 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Federal Emergency Management Agency. An affordability framework for the National Flood Insurance Program <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.preventionweb.net/publication/affordability-framework-national-flood-insurance-program">https://www.preventionweb.net/publication/affordability-framework-national-flood-insurance-program</ext-link> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">US Department of Homeland Security. An affordability framework for the national flood insurance program <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fema.gov/sites/default/files/2020-05/Affordability_april_2018.pdf">https://www.fema.gov/sites/default/files/2020-05/Affordability_april_2018.pdf</ext-link> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flood- and weather-damaged homes and mental health: an analysis using England&#x02019;s Mental Health Survey</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3256</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph16183256</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31491859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31491859</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Graham, H., White, P., Cotton, J. &#x00026; McManus, S. Flood- and weather-damaged homes and mental health: an analysis using England&#x02019;s Mental Health Survey. <italic>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</italic><bold>16</bold>, 3256 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31491859</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alderman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Floods and human health: a systematic review</article-title><source>Environ. Int.</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2012.06.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22750033?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22750033</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Alderman, K., Turner, L. R. &#x00026; Tong, S. Floods and human health: a systematic review. <italic>Environ. Int.</italic><bold>47</bold>, 37&#x02013;47 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22750033</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker-Springett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Adger</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wellbeing in the aftermath of floods</article-title><source>Health Place</source><year>2017</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.healthplace.2016.11.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27898313?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27898313</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Walker-Springett, K., Butler, C. &#x00026; Adger, W. N. Wellbeing in the aftermath of floods. <italic>Health Place</italic><bold>43</bold>, 66&#x02013;74 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27898313</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peek-Asa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flood-related work disruption and poor health outcomes among university students</article-title><source>Prehosp. Disaster Med.</source><year>2012</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1049023X1200129X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23031409?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23031409</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Peek-Asa, C., Ramirez, M., Young, T. &#x00026; Cao, Y. Flood-related work disruption and poor health outcomes among university students. <italic>Prehosp. Disaster Med.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 503&#x02013;508 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23031409</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davenport, F. V., Burke, M. &#x00026; Diffenbaugh, N. S. Contribution of historical precipitation change to us flood damages. <italic>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>118</bold> e2017524118 (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abadie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardeazabal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The economic costs of conflict: a case study of the Basque country</article-title><source>Am. Econ. Rev.</source><year>2003</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1257/000282803321455188</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Abadie, A. &#x00026; Gardeazabal, J. The economic costs of conflict: a case study of the Basque country. <italic>Am. Econ. Rev.</italic><bold>93</bold>, 113&#x02013;132 (2003).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abadie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hainmueller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthetic control methods for comparative case studies: estimating the effect of California&#x02019;s tobacco control program</article-title><source>J. Am. Stat. Assoc.</source><year>2010</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1198/jasa.2009.ap08746</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Abadie, A., Diamond, A. &#x00026; Hainmueller, J. Synthetic control methods for comparative case studies: estimating the effect of California&#x02019;s tobacco control program. <italic>J. Am. Stat. Assoc.</italic><bold>105</bold>, 493&#x02013;505 (2010).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenbaum</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects</article-title><source>Biometrika</source><year>1983</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biomet/70.1.41</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Rosenbaum, P. R. &#x00026; Rubin, D. B. The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects. <italic>Biometrika</italic><bold>70</bold>, 41&#x02013;55 (1983).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angrist</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lifetime earnings and the vietnam era draft lottery: evidence from social security administrative records</article-title><source>Am. Econ. Rev.</source><year>1990</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>336</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Angrist, J. D. Lifetime earnings and the vietnam era draft lottery: evidence from social security administrative records. <italic>Am. Econ. Rev.</italic><bold>80</bold>, 313&#x02013;336 (1990).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worms: identifying impacts on education and health in the presence of treatment externalities</article-title><source>Econometrica</source><year>2004</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-0262.2004.00481.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Miguel, E. &#x00026; Kremer, M. Worms: identifying impacts on education and health in the presence of treatment externalities. <italic>Econometrica</italic><bold>72</bold>, 159&#x02013;217 (2004).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanden-Eijnden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Density estimation by dual ascent of the log-likelihood</article-title><source>Commun. Math. Sci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4310/CMS.2010.v8.n1.a11</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Tabak, E. G. &#x00026; Vanden-Eijnden, E. Density estimation by dual ascent of the log-likelihood. <italic>Commun. Math. Sci.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 217&#x02013;233 (2010).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A family of nonparametric density estimation algorithms</article-title><source>Commun. Pure Appl. Math.</source><year>2013</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpa.21423</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Tabak, E. G. &#x00026; Turner, C. V. A family of nonparametric density estimation algorithms. <italic>Commun. Pure Appl. Math.</italic><bold>66</bold>, 145&#x02013;164 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rippel, O. &#x00026; Prescott Adams, R. High-dimensional probability estimation with deep density models. <italic>arXiv e-prints</italic> arXiv:1302.5125 (2013). 1302.5125.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jimenez Rezende, D. &#x00026; Mohamed, S. Variational inference with normalizing flows. <italic>arXiv e-prints</italic> arXiv:1505.05770 (2015). 1505.05770.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Training deep neural density estimators to identify mechanistic models of neural dynamics</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e56261</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.56261</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32940606?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32940606</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Gon&#x000e7;alves, P. J. et al. Training deep neural density estimators to identify mechanistic models of neural dynamics. <italic>eLife</italic><bold>9</bold>, e56261 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32940606</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alsing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Charnock</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wandelt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast likelihood-free cosmology with neural density estimators and active learning</article-title><source>Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc.</source><year>2019</year><volume>488</volume><fpage>4440</fpage><lpage>4458</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Alsing, J., Charnock, T., Feeney, S. &#x00026; Wandelt, B. Fast likelihood-free cosmology with neural density estimators and active learning. <italic>Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc.</italic><bold>488</bold>, 4440&#x02013;4458 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Melchior</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerated Bayesian SED modeling using amortized neural posterior estimation</article-title><source>Astrophys. J.</source><year>2022</year><volume>938</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3847/1538-4357/ac7b84</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Hahn, C. &#x00026; Melchior, P. Accelerated Bayesian SED modeling using amortized neural posterior estimation. <italic>Astrophys. J.</italic><bold>938</bold>, 11 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Papamakarios, G., Pavlakou, T. &#x00026; Murray, I. Masked autoregressive flow for density estimation. In <italic>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</italic>, Vol. 30 (eds Guyon, I. et al.) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper_files/paper/2017/file/6c1da886822c67822bcf3679d04369fa-Paper.pdf">https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper_files/paper/2017/file/6c1da886822c67822bcf3679d04369fa-Paper.pdf</ext-link> (Curran Associates, Inc., 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Greenberg, D. S., Nonnenmacher, M. &#x00026; Macke, J. H. Automatic posterior transformation for likelihood-free inference. <italic>arXiv e-prints</italic> arXiv:1905.07488 (2019). 1905.07488.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tejero-Cantero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sbi: a toolkit for simulation-based inference</article-title><source>J. Open Source Softw.</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2505</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02505</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Tejero-Cantero, A. et al. Sbi: a toolkit for simulation-based inference. <italic>J. Open Source Softw.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 2505 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>