<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nlm2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-0640</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11461323</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1494503</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Vulnerability and resilience in small island developing states</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>Michael H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1132020"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Emmanuel</surname><given-names>Maisha K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2231448"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>Natalie S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2233622"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lashley</surname><given-names>Myrna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2230918"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Faculty of Medical Sciences, The University of the West Indies</institution>, <addr-line>Bridgetown</addr-line>, <country>Barbados</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Division of Trans-Cultural Psychiatry, Faculty of Medicine, McGill University</institution>, <addr-line>Montreal, QC</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and Reviewed by: Wulf R&#x000f6;ssler, Charit&#x000e9; University Medicine Berlin, Germany</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Michael H. Campbell, <email xlink:href="mailto:michael.campbell@cavehill.uwi.edu">michael.campbell@cavehill.uwi.edu</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>1494503</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024 Campbell, Emmanuel, Greaves and Lashley</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Campbell, Emmanuel, Greaves and Lashley</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/53383/vulnerability-and-resilience-in-small-island-developing-states/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>Vulnerability and resilience in small island developing states</article-title>
</related-article><kwd-group><kwd>mental health</kwd><kwd>climate change</kwd><kwd>resilience</kwd><kwd>small island developing states</kwd><kwd>Caribbean</kwd><kwd>Oceania</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="11"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="885"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Public Mental Health</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Small island developing states (SIDS) experience myriad geographic and socioeconomic vulnerabilities that affect the wellbeing of their communities. Although SIDS are not monolithic, commonly shared vulnerabilities include remoteness, small populations, disproportionate reliance on marine resources and imports, financial constraints and debt burden&#x02014;and vulnerability to climate threat, which both exacerbates and is exacerbated by these existing pressures (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Although climate researchers have acknowledged the disproportionate mental health impacts of acute (e.g., weather) and creeping (e.g., temperature and sea level increases) climate threats in SIDS (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), studies focused on mental health outcomes and interventions in SIDS are lacking. However, significant research efforts are now emerging (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Indeed, since the inception of this Research Topic, the <italic>Connecting Climate Minds</italic> project has disseminated collaborative global and regional climate mental health research agendas, including for Oceania and Latin America and the Caribbean (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>We appreciate the challenges faced by mental health researchers and clinicians in SIDS, who themselves are part of affected communities, subject to many of the same vulnerabilities as their neighbors&#x02014;and who contribute to community resilience in their professional and personal roles. Further, many academic and healthcare institutions in SIDS operate in resource-limited settings that constrain production and dissemination of scholarship. Given those realities, providing a venue to feature the expertise and experiences of our SIDS colleagues was a principal motivation for organizing this collection of work, and we are pleased that the contributors are mostly mental health leaders from the Caribbean and Pacific regions, including researchers and clinicians from a broad range of relevant specialties and practice settings. The contributions themselves are similarly diverse, including empirical work, commentary, and a review paper. Taken together, the papers demonstrate the value of transdisciplinary and ecological approaches for conceptualizing and addressing mental health needs in SIDS.</p><p>The Research Topic presents qualitative findings from two recent Caribbean studies in the Commonwealth of Dominica and Republic of Trinidad &#x00026; Tobago. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1372971" ext-link-type="uri">LeBlanc et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> explore middle-aged Dominicans&#x02019; experiences and perceptions of severe weather events, explicating a range of negative physical and mental health outcomes, especially anxiety and burnout, as well the faith-based connections, community-based support, and individual coping behaviors that undergird resilience. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1285399" ext-link-type="uri">Murphy et al.</ext-link> describe the lived experiences of youth in Trinidad &#x00026; Tobago during COVID-19 lockdown restrictions. Their work situates the psychological stress experienced by young people navigating extraordinary disruption in broader context, connecting mental health outcomes with uncertain timelines for public health interventions, conflictual family dynamics in some households, separation from youth culture and social connections, educational fatigue, and anxieties about employment prospects. Both papers are useful for readers wishing to broaden their understanding of the psychological sequelae of recent public health crises in Caribbean SIDS. Importantly, they address a critical need to provide regionally relevant evidence to enhance public health preparedness as SIDS confront escalating climate threats (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1385525" ext-link-type="uri">Knight et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> provide a comprehensive review of attitudes and beliefs regarding psychosis among the Caribbean diaspora. Their valuable coverage provides a needed update of the literature and draws out key considerations for responsive research and practice with Caribbean people. The complex interrelationships of colonialism, global movement of populations, mistrust of mental health services, and cultural collectivism contextualize the experience of Caribbean people living with psychosis, as well as their families and communities. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1207103" ext-link-type="uri">Dale et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> describe a study protocol that operationalizes a similar perspective to develop, implement, and assess a model of services for Aboriginal and Torres Strait islander youth in the Australian justice system. With an emphasis on co-design and community governance, they elaborate a research plan that is responsive in design and provision of services to support social and emotional wellbeing of young people in the cultural and geographic contexts of Melanesia and Australia. Finally, conceptual articles by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1322831" ext-link-type="uri">Holdsworth et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> and <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1325292" ext-link-type="uri">Orb&#x000e1;n</ext-link> present geographically and culturally informed recommendations for future climate health research in the Caribbean and Pacific regions, respectively. These pieces consider the vulnerabilities of SIDS in concert with the resilient aspects of cultures and local systems in framing the understanding and response to mental health impacts of climate change. Further, they recognize that the health impacts of climate change are embedded in dynamic socioeconomic and political systems that further affect public mental health outcomes (e.g., urbanization processes in South Pacific societies). Together, these contributions advocate for a broad approach to future climate mental health models for SIDS, grounded in a sense of place, informed by and responsive to local cultures, and inclusive of larger-scale geopolitical, social, and economic dynamics.</p><p>We are pleased that this Research Topic amplifies the voices of our researcher and practitioner colleagues in SIDS, whose scholarship demonstrates the importance of transdisciplinary and ecological frameworks for understanding the interrelationships among climate phenomena, socioeconomic factors, place, and mental health outcomes. This broader conceptualization is reflected in the emerging field of geopsychiatry, which emphasizes the intersections of mental health, economics, geography, climate change, migration, and geopolitics (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). These themes feature heavily in this Research Topic, and we suggest that this integrated lens is useful for operationalizing future research as SIDS confront complex and escalating threats to physical and mental health. Future research should sharpen regional focus and expand scope of inquiry to promote the resilience of individuals and communities of SIDS, which are among the most vulnerable regions to global climate change.</p></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to thank our colleagues who served as reviewers for this Research Topic.</p></ack><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MC: Conceptualization, Project administration, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. ME: Conceptualization, Project administration, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. NG: Conceptualization, Project administration, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. ML: Conceptualization, Project administration, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s2"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s3"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<source>Small island developing states are on the frontlines of climate change &#x02013; here&#x02019;s why</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>United Nations Development Program</publisher-name> (<year>2021</year>). Available at: <uri xlink:href="https://climatepromise.undp.org/news-and-stories/small-island-developing-states-are-frontlines-climate-change-heres-why">https://climatepromise.undp.org/news-and-stories/small-island-developing-states-are-frontlines-climate-change-heres-why</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayeb-Karlsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose-Clarke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Prost</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronneberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A review of mental health and wellbeing under climate change in small island developing states (SIDS)</article-title>. <source>Environ Res Lett</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>033007</fpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/abe57d</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34149865</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Caribbean mental health professionals support climate resilience through community engagement, disaster response, and research</article-title>. <source>Int Rev Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<page-range>516&#x02013;9</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09540261.2022.2093101</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The mental health impacts of climate change: Findings from a Pacific Island atoll nation</article-title>. <source>J Anxiety Disord</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<elocation-id>102237</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2020.102237</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32485590</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seon</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exploratory empirical model of combined effects of COVID-19 and climate change on youth mental health</article-title>. <source>Nat Ment Health</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<page-range>218&#x02013;27</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s44220-023-00197-8</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawrance</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Massazza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantelidou</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Newberry Le Vay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>El Omrani</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><collab>Connecting Climate Minds Core Team Imperial College London</collab><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Connecting Climate Minds: a shared vision for the climate change and mental health field</article-title>. <source>Nat Ment Health</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<page-range>121&#x02013;5</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s44220-023-00196-9</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jankie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bristol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandeville</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Climate and mental health regional research and action agenda: Latin American &#x00026; the Caribbean. Connecting Climate Minds Project</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Imperial College London</publisher-name> (<year>2024</year>). Available at: <uri xlink:href="https://nbswmzwquzluimyqnfsf.supabase.co/storage/v1/object/public/documents/LAC%20(summary)_compressed.pdf?t=2024-03-19T10%3A47%3A21.344Z">https://nbswmzwquzluimyqnfsf.supabase.co/storage/v1/object/public/documents/LAC%20(summary)_compressed.pdf?t=2024-03-19T10%3A47%3A21.344Z</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercammen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pizzino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiatia-Siau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarnai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Climate and mental health regional research and action agenda: Oceania. Connecting Climate Minds Project</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Imperial College London</publisher-name> (<year>2024</year>). Available at: <uri xlink:href="https://nbswmzwquzluimyqnfsf.supabase.co/storage/v1/object/public/documents/Oceania%20(summary)_compressed.pdf?t=2024-03-19T11%3A03%3A57.032Z">https://nbswmzwquzluimyqnfsf.supabase.co/storage/v1/object/public/documents/Oceania%20(summary)_compressed.pdf?t=2024-03-19T11%3A03%3A57.032Z</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cort&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Rivera</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Caribbean Strong Summit: building resilience with equity</article-title>. <source>Disaster Med Public Health Prep</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<page-range>155&#x02013;7</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/dmp.2020.18</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anantapong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Udomratn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Persaud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Geopsychiatry: Climate change, migration, and mental health</article-title>. <source>Ind Psychiatry J</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<page-range>S257&#x02013;60</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ipj.ipj_33_24</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valsraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Persaud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhavsar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Geopsychiatry and social psychiatry</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bhugra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moussaoui</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Oxford textbook of social psychiatry</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford UK</publisher-loc> (<year>2022</year>). p. <page-range>111&#x02013;6</page-range>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>