<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Estuaries Coast</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Estuaries Coast</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Estuaries and Coasts</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1559-2723</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1559-2731</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11488480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1425</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12237-024-01425-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Functional Assessments of Living Shorelines</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Future Shorelines: A Living Shoreline Site Selection and Design Decision Support Tool that Incorporates Future Conditions Induced by Sea Level Rise</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4341-5807</contrib-id><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>Randall W.</given-names></name><address><email>rparkins@fiu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juhasz</surname><given-names>Levente</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jinwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Zhaohui Jennifer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02gz6gg07</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.65456.34</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2110 1845</institution-id><institution>Institute of Environment, </institution><institution>Florida International University, </institution></institution-wrap>Miami, FL 33199 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02gz6gg07</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.65456.34</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2110 1845</institution-id><institution>Geographic Information Systems Center, </institution><institution>Florida International University, </institution></institution-wrap>Miami, FL 33199 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.47840.3f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2181 7878</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Institute of Transportation Studies, </institution><institution>University of California, </institution></institution-wrap>Berkeley, CA 94720 USA </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by Holly Greening</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>47</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2641</fpage><lpage>2654</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Most living shoreline site selection and design decision support tools are based upon existing environmental conditions. We developed a web-based, geospatial tool called Future Shorelines that integrates high-resolution landscape elevation data and a matrix of locally derived NOAA Interagency Sea Level Rise Scenarios to characterize future conditions of submergence and shoreline translation induced by sea level rise. Once the practitioner selects a location of interest, sea level rise scenario (e.g., high), and target year (e.g., 2050), the tool will generate plan view and cross-sectional informational graphics specific to their choices. This information can then be paired with other menu options, like parcel ownership, to facilitate the planning and construction of nature-based shoreline stabilization solutions that (1) are located where opportunities for horizontal migration are optimized, (2) remain accessible for monitoring and maintenance, and (3) perform as intended over the design life of the installation. The tool&#x02019;s menu options and the user interface were informed by project partner input solicited during numerous workshops convened over the duration of the 2-year project. This coproduction created a product that was familiar to the end user and therefore increased the likelihood that it would be utilized by them during the planning and design of living shoreline projects. Although developed for use in the Indian River Lagoon, located along the east-central Florida coast, it can be seamlessly replicated for application in other coastal regions of the USA where the requisite data are available.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Climate change</kwd><kwd>Coastal resiliency</kwd><kwd>Environmental justice</kwd><kwd>Florida</kwd><kwd>Living shorelines</kwd><kwd>Indian River Lagoon</kwd><kwd>Nature-based solutions</kwd><kwd>Sea level rise</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>United States Environmental Protection Agency</institution></funding-source><award-id>02D16822</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>Randall W.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Coastal and Estuarine Research Federation 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Over the last century, there has been a proliferation of shoreline stabilization projects constructed along the developed coastlines of the USA to mitigate the effects of coastal erosion and flooding (Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2016</xref>). Initially, these consisted of bulkheads, seawalls, and revetments collectively described as hard structures (Swann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2008</xref>; NOAA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2015</xref>). Within the past several decades however, it became evermore apparent to coastal practitioners that the cumulative effect of their construction was a substantial loss of natural habitat and the ecosystem services they provided (Broome, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1992</xref>; Currin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2010</xref>; Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2016</xref>). As a result, a new strategy emerged that advocated for the use of natural materials or nature-based solutions (e.g., living shorelines) as a means of mitigating erosion (National Research Council <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2007</xref>; Mitsova and Bergh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2016</xref>; Bilkovic and Mitchell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2017</xref>; Reguero et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2018</xref>; Gijsman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2021</xref>; van Hespen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2022</xref>; Temmerman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2023</xref>). As the use of living shorelines (aka soft or green structures) expanded, so too did the need for the development of technical guidelines to facilitate effective (1) site selection, (2) installation design, and (3) performance monitoring (Restore America&#x02019;s Estuaries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">To date, most living shoreline site selection and design decision support tools are based upon existing environmental conditions (e.g., shoreline type, presence of structures, habitat, wind/wave exposure) (Berman and Rudnicky <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>; Mitsova and Bergh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2016</xref>; Zylberman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2016</xref>; Kibler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020</xref>; Nunez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2022</xref>; Boyd et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2024</xref>). However, these conditions will change in response to the effects of a warming climate and concomitant sea level rise. Along the Florida coast, for example, sea level is expected to rise&#x02009;~&#x02009;0.3&#x000a0;m above present (2020) by 2050 (NOAA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2022</xref>). This will result in coastal flooding and shoreline translation. Yet very few living shoreline site suitability models consider future conditions in their analysis (cf. Balasubramanyam and Howard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2019</xref>) and none utilize locally derived sea level scenarios or parcel-specific data.</p><p id="Par4">The goal of this project was to create a user-friendly, web-based geospatial living shoreline decision support tool for coastal practitioners that models future conditions (e.g., submergence, shoreline change) induced by sea level rise (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This information can then be paired with other menu options (e.g., parcel ownership and value) to facilitate the planning and construction of nature-based shoreline stabilization solutions that (1) are located where opportunities for horizontal migration are optimized, (2) remain accessible for monitoring and maintenance, and (3) perform as intended over the design life of the installation. To demonstrate the tool&#x02019;s functionality and utility, four examples of its output are described.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Summary of living shoreline site suitability decision support attributes considered in existing models and those included in this study (novel). Also shown are next generation attributes requested by project partners to facilitate compliance with state statutes and permitting</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Approach</th><th align="left">Status</th><th align="left">Attribute</th><th align="left">Rationale</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Existing</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">Shoreline type, presence of structures</td><td align="left" rowspan="4">Assessment of existing environmental conditions</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Shoreline/nearshore slope</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Habitat/substrate type</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Wave climate</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Novel</td><td align="left">This study</td><td align="left">Shoreline transgression</td><td align="left">Assessment of future conditions</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Upland topographic slope</td><td align="left">Assessment of capacity to migrate landward</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Future land use/ownership</td><td align="left">Assessment of recruitment capacity</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Demographics</td><td align="left">Assessment of group representation</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Shoreline/upland characteristics</td><td align="left">Assessment of capacity to migrate landward</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Next generation</td><td align="left">State of Florida sea level rise scenarios</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">Requested by project partners</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Alternate demographic indices</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Bathymetry</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Muck deposits</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Sea grass distribution</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Stormwater outfalls</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Impoundment culverts</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Alternate tidal datums</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Other shoreline or environmental data</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Area of Study and Background</title><p id="Par5">This project focused on the Indian River Lagoon (IRL) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), a 250-km-long shore-parallel micro-tidal estuary located within the east-central Florida barrier island complex. It covers an area of 353 km<sup>2</sup> and is composed of three distinct and connected water bodies: the Indian River, Banana River, and Mosquito Lagoon. Water depths average about 2&#x000a0;m and historically the bottom was covered by extensive seagrass that has since declined within all three basins as a consequence of the deterioration of water clarity (Steward et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2005</xref>). Most of the IRL&#x02019;s tidal wetlands were filled, ditched, or impounded over the past century (Brockmeyer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2021</xref>). Those that remain are located primarily in land conservation areas (e.g., Merritt Island National Wildlife Refuge) or mosquito control impoundments. In the southern and central portion of the IRL, the wetlands consist of mangrove-dominated plant communities that transition northward into salt marsh. Its 2284 km<sup>2</sup> humid subtropical watershed sprawls over five coastal counties. The lagoon&#x02019;s total annual economic contribution to the region is estimated to be about ten billion dollars and generated in part by the ecosystem services it provides, including recreational fishing and ecotourism (East Central Florida Regional Planning Council and Treasure Coast Regional Planning Council <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2016</xref>). Hence, there is keen interest in restoring and sustaining the ecological value and function of the IRL.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Regional location map and approximate geographic boundaries of the study domain (Indian River Lagoon). Also shown are the counties located within the watershed and other figure locations referenced in text</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">The IRL was recognized by the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) as an Estuary of National Significance in 1990 and is one of 28 National Estuary Programs (NEP). Since then, a growing body of scientific evidence revealed that the ecological and biological integrity of the lagoon had degraded over historical times due to a decline in water quality (Sigua et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2000</xref>; Lapointe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>) caused by watershed urbanization (e.g., stormwater runoff, septic systems). The IRL NEP and all coastal counties within the watershed now have extensive programs designed to mitigate water quality impairment, including (1) septic-to-sewer conversions, (2) stormwater retrofits (e.g., baffle boxes and retention-detention basins), and (3) living shorelines (cf. Tetra Tech, Inc. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2022</xref>). Because living shorelines benefit from broad public support and are perceived as a cost-effect means of improving the health of the lagoon (Parkinson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2023</xref>), a large and rapidly growing number of projects have been completed or are planned within the watershed and throughout the Florida coastal zone (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) using funds provided by numerous federal (e.g., NOAA, EPA, NPS), state (e.g., Florida Fish and Wildlife Commission), and local (e.g., Brevard County Save our Indian River Lagoon) resource regulatory and management agencies.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Screen grab of the NOAA Restoration Atlas (NOAA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2024</xref>) indicating location of more than 200 nature-based coastal restoration projects within the State of Florida. Black boxed inset is the study domain of this project. Inset is Future Shorelines QR code</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">Two recent studies (Parkinson and Seidel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2018</xref>; Parkinson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2020</xref>) conducted on behalf of the IRL NEP determined increasing impairment of water quality is highly likely under conditions of future climate change and concomitant sea level rise. Specific to living shorelines, the logical questions to ask given this prognosis are as follows: (1) how will the ecosystem services (e.g., nutrient uptake, shoreline stabilization, and a reduction in sediment pollution) of living shorelines change in response to sea level rise and (2) can a priori knowledge of shoreline changes induced by rising seas be utilized during the process of site selection and design to enhance their resilience? This project was designed to bolster the capacity to answer question 2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data Collection and Processing</title><p id="Par8">The full suite of data used to model future conditions along the IRL shoreline is summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Four NOAA (Sweet et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2022</xref>) scenario-based sea level rise trajectories (i.e., intermediate-low, intermediate, intermediate-high, and high) and time steps (2030, 2040, 2050, and 2100) were considered in this project. The NOAA trajectories are bounded by a simple linear extrapolation of sea level rise since the early 1990s (low; not considered in this study) to a rise representing extreme ice-sheet melting and discharge (high). We extracted the median values corresponding to each scenario as calculated at the Trident Pier (Port Canaveral, FL) station using the NASA Interagency Sea Level Rise Scenario Tool (NOAA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2022</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Summary of the source and application of the datasets utilized in the Future Shorelines tool to model future conditions along the IRL shoreline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Dataset</th><th align="left">Source</th><th align="left">Application</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sea level rise scenarios</td><td align="left">NOAA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2022</xref>)</td><td align="left"><p>Inundation mapping</p><p>Future shoreline location</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Digital elevation model</td><td align="left"><p>Florida Peninsular LiDAR Survey 2018&#x02013;2020</p><p>Florida Div. of Emerg. Mgmt. (OMC Partners <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2024</xref>)</p></td><td align="left"><p>Inundation mapping</p><p>Elevation profile</p><p>Future shoreline location</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tidal surface (MHHW)</td><td align="left">NOAA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2023</xref>)</td><td align="left"><p>Inundation mapping</p><p>Future shoreline location</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Parcel data</td><td align="left">County property appraiser offices</td><td align="left"><p>Property/shoreline ownership</p><p>Parcel details</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Shoreline characteristics</td><td align="left">University of Central Florida (Donnelly et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2018</xref>)</td><td align="left">Shoreline characteristics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Demographic Index</td><td align="left">EJScreen (US EPA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2024</xref>)</td><td align="left">Group representation</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par9">To map sea level inundation, we developed an approach based on free and open-source geospatial software. The approach follows the passive inundation mapping processes developed by NOAA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>) and as described in detail by Juhasz et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2023</xref>). The land elevation data and corresponding digital elevation model (DEM) were obtained from the most recent LiDAR survey commissioned by the Florida Division of Emergency Management. The DEM has a horizontal resolution of 0.76&#x000a0;m and vertical accuracy of&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;m (Stoker and Miller <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2022</xref>). In this study, inundation was defined as a land surface located below the mean higher-high water (MHHW) level and hydrologically connected to the estuary. While it is a generally accepted practice in inundation mapping to use a constant value to approximate the MHHW surface, this is not accurate over larger areas since MHHW is spatially variable, especially in estuarine environments. To support accurate, parcel-specific planning, we used VDatum Transformations developed by NOAA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2023</xref>) to approximate this variation as described by Juhasz et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2023</xref>). All horizontal data are referenced to the North American Datum 1983 (NAD83), Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) zone 17N coordinate system, and resampled to 3&#x000a0;m pixel resolution. All elevation values are expressed in the NAVD88 vertical datum.</p><p id="Par10">The intersection of the MHHW surface and the DEM was defined as the shoreline. The location of future shorelines was mapped using the same DEM and the MHHW surface corresponding to the sea level rise scenario and time step selected by the user. This approach preserves the spatial variability of the MHHW surface but assumes no future change in that variability nor in the topography of the land surface being inundated. For the purposes of this pilot project, only shoreline segments longer than 1500 ft (457&#x000a0;m) were considered. This was done to optimize computational and storage efficiency while minimizing the extent of omitted shoreline segments. In addition to the plan view maps of inundation, a transect attribute option was also created to facilitate visualizations of the extent and location of upland flooding along a shore-normal topographic profile corresponding to the sea level trajectory and time step selected by the user. The elevation along each transect line is based upon the underlying DEM and sampled at 15 ft (5&#x000a0;m) intervals. The slope between adjacent elevation points is automatically calculated and included in the graphical output.</p><p id="Par11">Parcel data were incorporated into the decision support tool as a map menu option to delineate the ownership and boundaries of properties located along the IRL shoreline. The demographics of people residing in the study domain were also integrated into the model at the census block group level using the EPA Environmental Justice Screening Tool (US EPA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2024</xref>). This attribute was included because federally funded coastal zone management programs now generally require applicants who are soliciting support include outputs and outcomes that address social justice inequities. A summary of the tool&#x02019;s decision framework and outputs is provided in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram summarizing the decision framework of the Future Shorelines tool. User selected conditions are combined with input data to generate a novel suite of application outputs that can be used to identify nature-based shoreline stabilization locations that are climate resilient</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Project Design and Implementation</title><p id="Par12">Central to the success of this project was the incorporation of feedback from our partners and other practitioners based upon a philosophy that prioritized end user input and a user-centered design (Pratt and Nunes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2012</xref>). This coproduction (Beier et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2017</xref>) allowed for the refinement of the methodologies and outputs using an iterative process that incorporated end-user feedback and suggestions throughout the development of the application (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). More than 40 virtual workshops were held throughout the duration of the 2-year project. The initial workshops focused on presenting an overview of the project and methodological approach, while explicitly seeking feedback on key points in real time, follow-up correspondence, and polling. Subsequent workshops featured prototypes or beta versions of the application that allowed our partners to provide more targeted feedback based upon their experience. As a result, numerous modifications to elements of the project&#x02019;s original scope and design, including changes related to data, application functionality, and the user experience, were made as summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and described in the following sections. The use of a coproduction framework yielded a project deliverable that aligns with the needs of the practitioners for whom it was intended and therefore elevated the probability of its use.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Flowchart illustrating the collaborative, user-centric coproduction process employed during the development and implementation of the Future Shorelines tool</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Future Shorelines data and functionality issues resolved by coproduction with project partners</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Topic</th><th align="left">Issue</th><th align="left">Resolution</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Units of measure</td><td align="left">What unit of measure should be used?</td><td align="left">US customary (SAE)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Shoreline profiles</td><td align="left">What should be the distance between transects?</td><td align="left">100 feet&#x000a0;(30 m)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">How far should a transect extend inland?</td><td align="left">500 feet&#x000a0;(152 m)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Shoreline characteristics</td><td align="left">Addition of shoreline characterization data would be helpful</td><td align="left">County partners provided shoreline characterization geospatial files</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Parcel data</td><td align="left">Some of the Florida Department of Revenue ownership and taxed assessed value data were inaccurate</td><td align="left">County partners provided parcel data from their property appraisers office</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Parcel search</td><td align="left">Can parameters other than the parcel ID be used to navigate to a location of interest?</td><td align="left">Added physical address and geographic coordinates to the menu of search parameter options</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Polygon features</td><td align="left">Shoreline ownership designations obscure details of underlying aerial imagery</td><td align="left">Created a slide bar so user can adjust the transparency of shoreline ownership designations</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec6"><title>Changes Related to Data Elements</title><p id="Par13">On-line partner polling at the onset of project development indicated a preference for the use of US customary units of measure to express distance and height because these were more easily integrated into their day-to-day operations. Upon the introduction of the shoreline elevation profile attribute, the project partners were again polled regarding the preferred profile length and alongshore distance between them. Results indicated a preference for a length of 500 ft (152&#x000a0;m) inland from the present shoreline on 100 ft (30&#x000a0;m) center points. A beta version of the application was presented to the project partners during the second workshop that utilized statewide parcel data compiled by the Florida Department of Revenue. They noted that some federal properties were erroneously marked as &#x0201c;land with no value or ownership.&#x0201d; As a result, the statewide dataset was replaced with data collected by each county&#x02019;s property appraiser and subsequently provided to the project team by them. The ownership categories (i.e., private, public) and other metadata (e.g., parcel ID, class, value) were extracted from these files using a rule-based approach. The project partners also expressed interest in the addition of a point dataset of shoreline characteristics (e.g., seawall, riprap, natural) that had been recently compiled for southern Volusia and all of Brevard County. This dataset was generated by the University of Central Florida (Donnelly et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2018</xref>) and provided by both counties for integration into the application as an additional mapping attribute.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Changes Related to Functionality</title><p id="Par14">The beta version of the application allowed users to search for specific parcels based on their unique identification number (i.e., parcel ID). While useful, the project partners expressed a desire to search for sites using geographic coordinates or a street address. The interactive functionality of the web application was upgraded to include both in the menu of search options.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Visual and Contextual Changes</title><p id="Par15">In a Geographic Information System (GIS) framework, visual hierarchy is crucial since spatially overlapping features can obscure information from the user&#x02019;s view. During the third workshop, our partners noted that the shoreline ownership polylines overlapped the base map and shoreline characteristics dataset, thus obscuring that information. In response, the shoreline ownership feature was modified so that its transparency could be manually adjusted.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Additional Details on the Methodology</title><p id="Par16">Methodological details about sea level rise inundation modeling, geospatial processing, and development of the technology platform used in this project can be found in Juhasz et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2023</xref>). Additional methodological information (e.g., digital elevation model, MHHW tidal surface) can be found on the publicly available project landing page (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://futureshorelines.fiu.edu">https://futureshorelines.fiu.edu</ext-link>) by selecting the &#x0201c;Publications &#x00026; Data&#x0201d; tab.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><p id="Par17">In the following sections, three examples are presented describing how the living shoreline site selection and design decision support tool (hereafter Future Shorelines) can be used by practitioners to optimize the performance and resiliency of projects subjected to sea level rise in the coming decades. A fourth example is also provided in which the tool&#x02019;s application to topographic recontouring, an emerging nature-based solution designed to restore wetland habitat in areas impacted by the historical placement of spoil or fill, is described. In all cases, NOAA&#x02019;s high scenario-based sea level rise trajectory was utilized because twenty-first-century rates of rise along the southeast US coast are currently tracking with the intermediate high and high trajectories and expected to continue accelerating in the decades ahead (Parkinson and Wdowinski <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2023a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2023b</xref>).</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Changes in Land Ownership</title><p id="Par18">Most of the existing living shoreline installations within the study domain are located adjacent to public land. This association was not unexpected because it is generally easier to negotiate an agreement to construct, monitor, and maintain them at these locations.&#x000a0;Hence, in this first example (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), a potential installation location was identified wherein the current ownership of an undeveloped shoreline and adjacent upland parcel is within the public domain. However, as the sea level rises, the shoreline at this location will migrate landward, and by 2050, it will abut private land. This may confound the ability to sustain a performance monitoring or maintenance program should the installation still be functional at that time. With this knowledge in hand, the practitioners have the option to resume their search using the Future Shorelines tool to identify alternate locations where this change in ownership is not likely to occur.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Time series illustrating selected parcel boundary (yellow polygon) and Indian River Lagoon shoreline at present (2020, left) and in 2050 (right). Over the duration of this 30-year interval, sea level rises 1.51 ft (~&#x02009;0.5&#x000a0;m) under the High NOAA trajectory. This results in upland submergence and shoreline transgression onto a parcel that is not publicly owned. This may complicate the ability of practitioners to access the site for the purpose of monitoring and maintenance over the design life of the installation. Color legend as follows: blue, water; red line and infill, private shoreline and land ownership; green line and infill, public shoreline and land ownership. See Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> for location within the study domain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Installation Resilience and Allocation of Practitioner Resources</title><p id="Par19">In this example, a location was identified where a living shoreline project was recently constructed along a narrow, publicly owned shoreline parcel (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> left panel). It consists of oyster breakwater and mangrove plantings located adjacent to a hardened shoreline of riprap that ascends steeply (i.e.,&#x02009;~&#x02009;16&#x000b0;) to an inland elevation of 6 ft (1.8&#x000a0;m). The intended ecosystem services of this installation are not expected to persist under conditions of sea level rise because the shoreline is too steep. This expectation is based on observations that indicate the most extensive and persistent coastal wetlands in Florida are located in areas where the landscape slope is&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;5&#x000b0; (e.g., Everglades, Big Bend). In these areas, wetlands have survived for centuries to millennia under conditions of sea level rise by (1) migrating inland at the same rate as the transgressing shoreline and (2) vertically accumulating soil to remain within the intertidal zone (cf. Parkinson and Wdowinski <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2022</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2023a</xref>). Because the slope of the shoreline at this location is&#x02009;~&#x02009;16&#x000b0;, sea level rise will create relatively limited horizontal accommodation space into which the existing wetlands can migrate. In 2050, for example, sea level will have risen 1.51 ft (0.46&#x000a0;m) relative to 2020 and the shoreline will have migrated 5.5 ft (1.7&#x000a0;m) upslope. By contrast, if the slope was 5&#x000b0;, the shoreline would have migrated inland about 17 ft (5&#x000a0;m), creating a much broader area into which the installation&#x02019;s mangrove plant community could migrate. Given the limited capacity to migrate inland at this location, the resiliency of this living shoreline is therefore primarily dependent upon its capacity to aggrade vertically at the same pace as the rising seas. These observations are informative because they underscore the value in selecting installation construction locations that are adjacent to low-relief shorelines and upland areas. The Future Shorelines tool provides a graphical depiction of the shoreline slope along the topographic profile selected by the user (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> right panel). The slopes are subdivided into two categories based upon the 5&#x000b0; threshold value (see also Mitsova and Bergh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2016</xref>) and can be used to quickly assess the resiliency of a nature-based installation at any location of interest in the context of the availability of horizontal accommodation space.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Left panel. Time series illustrating location of shoreline and submerged lands at present (2020, top) and in 2100 (bottom). Also shown are shoreline characterization observations provided by the University of Central Florida (Top, 1) and the location of an existing oyster reef installation or breakwater (Top, 2). Right panel. Output of time steps corresponding to the high NOAA sea level rise scenario at present (Top, 3) and in 2100 (Bottom). Corresponding to each time step are paired elevation (4, land; 5, MHHW) and land slope (6) values generated along the selected 500 ft elevation transect (left panel yellow line). Slope values organized into two categories to distinguish upland areas considered too steep for the successful landward migration of a living shoreline (&#x0003e;&#x02009;5&#x000b0;, blue histogram bars) and those more favorable (&#x0003c;&#x02009;5&#x000b0;). See text for details. Options to download the raw elevation data in a KML or CSV format or the transect image as a png file are also available (7). Color legend for left panel as follows: blue, water; yellow polygon, parcel boundary; red line and infill, private shoreline and land ownership; green line and infill, public shoreline and land ownership. See Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> for location within the study domain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">The resiliency prognosis of this installation can also be used as an additional means of decision support in the context of resource allocation. Practitioners responsible for the monitoring and maintenance of living shorelines are typically constrained by the availability of human and financial capital (cf. Kirschke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2020</xref>). The Future Shorelines tool provides a platform in which the practitioner can conduct a systematic evaluation of the installations they manage to gauge the extent to which rising seas will yield a contraction or expansion of intertidal substrate into which the wetlands can migrate. The outcome of that exercise can then be used to prioritize monitoring and maintenance efforts at living shoreline installation locations where the conditions favorable to tidal wetland colonization will not diminish as sea level rises.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Environmental Justice</title><p id="Par21">The US government now requires grant applicants soliciting federal funds to mitigate or restore the coastal environment include an environmental justice component in their proposed scope of work (e.g., outputs or outcomes). Our application utilizes a demographic index (DI) attribute to assist practitioners in meeting this requirement. The index was obtained from the EPA&#x02019;s on-line EJScreening Mapping Tool (US EPA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2024</xref>) and is graphically displayed as a mosaic of census block group layers distinguished by their DI score. The score ranges from zero to one and is calculated based on the percentage of the population self-identified as people of color and low-income census block score (i.e., [% people of color&#x02009;+&#x02009;% low income]/2). In the example provided (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), two coastal parcels were selected that are similar in land area, value, and elevation. However, the DI scores are significantly different at 13% (parcel 1) and 76% (parcel 2). Construction of a living shoreline project along the shoreline of parcel 2 would be preferable if an intended outcome includes consideration of underserved communities who may not otherwise benefit from the ecosystem services they provide. This could be facilitated by soliciting local resident participation in pre-construction meetings and assistance during the construction, monitoring, and maintenance phases of the project.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Example of Future Shorelines model output to address issues of environmental justice. Parcels 1 and 2 are similar with respect to ownership, land value and size, and elevation. The two are distinguished by the EPA Demographic Index (DI) census block score. Parcel 1 is scored at 13% and parcel 2 at 76%. A project constructed along the shoreline of parcel 2 would be preferable if the intended project outcomes include the desire to address environmental justice inequities. Color legend as follows: blue, water; yellow polygon, parcel boundary; red infill, private shoreline and land ownership; green infill, public shoreline and land ownership. See Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> for location within the study domain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Shoreline Recontouring</title><p id="Par22">An emerging element of coastal restoration is the targeting of areas where fill or spoil was placed during historical times (e.g., construction of the Intracoastal Waterway) for topographic recontouring to elevations conductive to wetland restoration (cf. Robison et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2020</xref>). The Marine Discovery Center (New Smyrna Beach, Florida) recently completed a spoil recontouring project on their property to create an intertidal surface that now hosts wetland plant communities (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> left panel) and they are currently considering a second recontouring project. Depending on the scale of the proposed shoreline restoration project, the tool provides as many as 10 elevation profiles that can be used during the preliminary design phase to evaluate potential topographic recontouring options with respect to shoreline slope and the beneficial use of on-site materials. In this example, the elevation profile was created along one of the transects using the Future Shoreline&#x02019;s data download option and graphed as a line extending from the present shoreline to the MHHW elevation in 2050 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> right panel). The slope of the recontoured shoreline is 1.2&#x000b0;. The slope may later be adjusted, so long as it remains&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;5&#x000b0; for reasons described previously, to balance the volume of on-site excavation and infill requirements. This beneficial use of spoil is encouraged by the US Army Corps of Engineers (Wilber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1992</xref>; Ray <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2007</xref>). The restored shoreline could then be populated by native wetland and upland plants that would over time migrate up-slope and onto areas that were not targeted for recontouring.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>Left panel. The Marine Discovery Center (MDC) has successfully recontoured the topography of an area of fill to elevations that now support the full assemblage of wetland plant communities (1) and is currently considering a second project (2). Color legend as follows: red line, shoreline privately owned; green line, shoreline is publicly owned; yellow line, location of elevation profile. Right panel. Elevation profile of the existing landscape and MHHW level in year 2100 constructed using data downloaded from Future Shorelines tool in support of a preliminary design analysis of a proposed topographic recontouring project. In this example, the hypothetical goal was to achieve an acceptable shoreline grade and optimize the beneficial use on on-site spoil to create a restoration site with a design life of 80&#x000a0;years (i.e., 2020&#x02013;2100). The existing 1.2&#x000b0; slope could be modified to create conditions in which the volume of fill excavated is equal to the volume of fill needed. See Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> for location within the study domain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12237_2024_1425_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par23">It is important to note that living shorelines are built for a wide variety of reasons, including (1) demonstration projects designed to foster public interest, education, and outreach, (2) projects constructed at the request of a landowner who is interested in nature-based solutions as an alternative to traditional hard structures, and (3) as a soft structural alternative to the repair or replacement of an existing seawall, bulkhead, or riprap shoreline protection feature. In these instances, the intended output is the construction of a nature-based shoreline stabilization feature and the outcome enhanced ecosystem services. Considerations regarding the long-term viability or resilience of these types of projects to sea level rise are of secondary importance or may not have been considered at all. For example, many of the existing IRL living shorelines were constructed as demonstration projects in front of a vertical seawall or steeply aggrading riprap (cf. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). These are unlikely to keep up with sea level rise in the coming decades as previously described. However, in these examples, the expected output and outcome were achieved immediately upon completion of the project. Therefore, these types of projects are considered successful because they performed as intended. But if the goal of nature-based solutions in general, and living shorelines in particular, is to mitigate historical losses in ecosystem function, habitat value, and water quality impairment, coastal practitioners must begin to consider their longevity or resilience under conditions of climate change and concomitant sea level rise. It was in this context that the Future Shorelines tool was developed. As demonstrated, it provides a suite of menu options that can be used to facilitate the planning and construction of nature-based shoreline stabilization solutions that (1) are located where opportunities for horizontal migration are optimized, (2) remain accessible for monitoring and maintenance, and (3) perform as intended over the design life of the installation. Future Shorelines was constructed using a flexible framework that can be readily populated with other geospatial data or attributes as may be requested by the practitioner (e.g., stormwater outfalls, MHW vertical datum). It can also be seamlessly customized for use in other regions where the requisite data are available.</p><p id="Par24">During the last quarter of the project, our partners were asked to suggest additional data or attributes that could be incorporated to enhance the utility and use of the Future Shorelines tool. These generally fell into two groups, those that facilitated (1) compliance with State (i.e., FDEP) or Federal (i.e., USACE) statutory/regulatory requirements (e.g., alternate sea level rise scenarios and time steps) and (2) project permitting (e.g., alternate elevation datum, bathymetry, seagrass maps). Many of these are included in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> under the category &#x0201c;next generation&#x0201d; and the project team is currently working to acquire funding to incorporate them into the current version of Future Shorelines.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par25">This paper summarizes the rationale and function of a novel living shoreline site selection and design decision support tool that was developed for coastal practitioners interested in constructing nature-based solutions that are climate resilient. The product, termed Future Shorelines, models sea level rise, coastal submergence, and shoreline translation. When this information is considered in tandem with the parcel data (one of several map menu options), the output provides a novel basis for evaluating potential changes in ownership that may hamper efforts to monitor and maintain an installation. The tool also provides a means of selecting installation locations where rising seas will not contract, but rather expand intertidal areas suitable for wetland colonization as sea level rises. A demographic menu option is available to provide the practitioner with information relevant to site selection in the context of environmental justice. Finally, the tool&#x02019;s elevation and shoreline profile features can be used to assist in the design of topographic recontouring projects undertaken to restore shorelines and coastal habitats degraded by historical fill or spoil deposition. Future Shorelines benefited greatly from coproduction with the project&#x02019;s partners, who have recommended additional data and attributes that could be incorporated to further enhance its utility and use during the design, permitting, and construction of nature-based solutions that are climate resilient. These are currently being evaluated by the project team.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This project could not have been completed without the active participation of our project partners. We therefore recognize the following persons for their sustained involvement and input: Holly Abeels (Florida Sea Grant, FSG), Annie Roddenberry (Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission, FWC), Virginia Barker (Brevard County), Logan Benedict (FWC), Savanna Berry (FSG), Duane DeFreese (Indian River Lagoon National Estuary Program), Scott Eastman (Florida Department of Environmental Protection), Vincent Encomio (FSG), Jessica Garland (Martin County), Kurtis Greg (National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration), Amy Griffin (St. Lucie County), Charles Jacoby (St. Johns River Water Management District), Melissa Meisenburg (Indian River County), Brandon Smith (Brevard County), and Samantha West (Volusia County). Our heartfelt appreciation is also expressed to Melinda Donnelly (University of Central Florida) who provided shoreline characterization geospatial data.</p></ack><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded by grant #02D16822 from the United States Environmental Protection Agency Region 4 Wetland Development Program. This is contribution #1759 from the Institute of Environment at Florida International University.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par26">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Balasubramanyam, V., and K. Howard. 2019. <italic>New Hampshire living shoreline site suitability assessment</italic>. Technical Report R-WD-19&#x02013;19. Portsmouth, NH: New Hampshire Department of Environmental Services Coastal Program.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Helbrecht</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A how-to guide for coproduction of actionable science</article-title><source>Conservation Letters</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/conl.12300</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Beier, P., L.J. Hansen, L. Helbrecht, and D. Behar. 2017. A how-to guide for coproduction of actionable science. <italic>Conservation Letters</italic> 10: 288&#x02013;296. 10.1111/conl.12300.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berman, M., and T. Rudnicky. 2008. <italic>Living shoreline suitability model, Worcester County, Maryland</italic>. Final Report. Gloucester Point, Virginia: Virginia Institute of Marine Science, College of William and Mary.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bilkovic, D. M., and M. M. Mitchell. 2017. Designing living shoreline salt marsh ecosystems to promote coastal resilience. In <italic>Living shorelines: the science and management of nature-based coastal protection</italic>, ed. D. M. Bilkovic, M. Mitchell, M. LaPeyre, and J. Toft, 1st Edition, 293&#x02013;316. Boca Raton, Florida: CRC Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boyd, C., X. Niu, S. Jones, L. A., Wilde, and M. Berman. 2024. Living shoreline site suitability model transfer for selected water bodies within the Gulf of Mexico: a GIS and remote sensing-based approach.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://restoreactscienceprogram.noaa.gov/projects/living-shoreline-tool">https://restoreactscienceprogram.noaa.gov/projects/living-shoreline-tool</ext-link>. Accessed 8 Mar 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brockmeyer</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manipulating, managing and rehabilitating mangrove-dominated wetlands along Florida&#x02019;s east coast (USA): Balancing mosquito control and ecological values</article-title><source>Wetlands Ecology and Management</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11273-021-09843-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Brockmeyer, R.E., M. Donnelly, J.R. Rey, and D.B. Carlson. 2021. Manipulating, managing and rehabilitating mangrove-dominated wetlands along Florida&#x02019;s east coast (USA): Balancing mosquito control and ecological values. <italic>Wetlands Ecology and Management</italic>. 10.1007/s11273-021-09843-3.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Broome, S. W., S. M. Rogers, and E. D. Seneca. 1992. <italic>Shoreline erosion control using marsh vegetation and low-cost structures</italic>. UNC-SG-92&#x02013;12. Raleigh, N.C: North Carolina Sea Grant.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Currin, C. A., W. S. Chappell, and A. Deaton. 2010. Developing alternative shoreline armoring strategies: the living shoreline approach in North Carolina. In <italic>Puget Sound shorelines and the impacts of armoring - proceedings of a State of the Science Workshop, May 2009</italic>,&#x000a0;ed.&#x000a0;Shipman, H., Dethier, M. N., Gelfenbaum, G., Fresh, K. L., Dinicola, R. S, 91&#x02013;102. Scientific Investigations Report 2010&#x02013;5254. US Geological Survey.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Donnelly, M., Shaffer, M., Connor, S., and Walters, L. 2018. Shoreline Characterization in the northern Indian River&#x000a0;Lagoon [WWW Document]. CEELAB Research Data, University of Central Florida, Orlando. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://stars.library.ucf.edu/ceelab-researchdata/2">https://stars.library.ucf.edu/ceelab-researchdata/2</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">East Central Florida Regional Planning Council, and Treasure Coast Regional Planning Council. 2016. <italic>Indian River Lagoon economic valuation update 2016</italic>. Final 08&#x02013;26&#x02013;2016. Tallahassee, Florida: Florida Department of Economic Opportunity.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gijsman, R., E. M. Horstman, D. van der Wal, D. A. Friess, A. Swales, and K. M. Wijnberg. 2021. Nature-based engineering: a review on reducing coastal flood risk with mangroves.&#x000a0;<italic>Frontiers in Marine Science</italic> 8:702412</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">van Hespen, R., Z. Hu, B. Borsje, M. De Dominicis, D.A. Friess, S. Jevrejeva, M.G. Kleinhans, et al. 2022. Mangrove forests as a nature-based solution for coastal flood protection: biophysical and ecological considerations. <italic>Water Science and Engineering</italic> S1674237022000874. 10.1016/j.wse.2022.10.004.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juhasz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond the tide: A comprehensive guide to sea level rise inundation mapping using FOSS4G</article-title><source>Geomatics</source><year>2023</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/geomatics3040028</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Juhasz, L., J. Xu, and R.W. Parkinson. 2023. Beyond the tide: A comprehensive guide to sea level rise inundation mapping using FOSS4G. <italic>Geomatics</italic> 3: 522&#x02013;540.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kibler, K. M., M. Donnelly, D. Cannon, L. Walters, J. Phagan, G. McClenachan, and A. Roddenberry. 2020. <italic>Developing a shoreline restoration suitability model for North Indian River and Mosquito Lagoon, Phase II</italic>. IRL2018&#x02013;017. Sebastian, Florida: Indian River Lagoon National Estuary Program.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirschke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Avell&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;rlund</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogardi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickens</surname><given-names>CWS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Capacity challenges in water quality monitoring: Understanding the role of human development</article-title><source>Environmental Monitoring and Assessment</source><year>2020</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>298</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-020-8224-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32307607</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Kirschke, S., T. Avell&#x000e1;n, I. B&#x000e4;rlund, J.J. Bogardi, L. Carvalho, D. Chapman, C.W.S. Dickens, et al. 2020. Capacity challenges in water quality monitoring: Understanding the role of human development. <italic>Environmental Monitoring and Assessment</italic> 192: 298. 10.1007/s10661-020-8224-3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32307607</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lapointe</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Herren</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Debortoli</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence of sewage-driven eutrophication and harmful algal blooms in Florida&#x02019;s Indian River Lagoon</article-title><source>Harmful Algae</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hal.2015.01.004</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Lapointe, B.E., L.W. Herren, D.D. Debortoli, and M.A. Vogel. 2015. Evidence of sewage-driven eutrophication and harmful algal blooms in Florida&#x02019;s Indian River Lagoon. <italic>Harmful Algae</italic> 43: 82&#x02013;102. 10.1016/j.hal.2015.01.004.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Miller, J. K., A. Rella, A. Williams, and E. Sproule. 2016. <italic>Living shorelines engineering guidelines</italic>. New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection, Report No.&#x000a0;SIT-DL-14&#x02013;2942.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mitsova, D., and C. Bergh. 2016. <italic>Suitability analysis for living shorelines development in southeast Florida&#x02019;s estuarine systems</italic>. Technical Report. Boca Raton, Florida: Florida Atlantic University.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Research Council. 2007. <italic>Mitigating shore erosion along sheltered coasts</italic>. Washington, D.C.: National Academies Press. 10.17226/11764.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NOAA. 2015. <italic>Guidance for considering the use of living shorelines</italic>.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.habitatblueprint.noaa.gov/wpcontent/uploads/2018/01/NOAA-Guidance-for-Considering-the-Use-of-Living-Shorelines_2015.pdf">https://www.habitatblueprint.noaa.gov/wpcontent/uploads/2018/01/NOAA-Guidance-for-Considering-the-Use-of-Living-Shorelines_2015.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NOAA. 2017. <italic>Detailed method for mapping sea level rise inundation</italic>.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://coast.noaa.gov/data/digitalcoast/pdf/slr-inundation-methods.pdf">https://coast.noaa.gov/data/digitalcoast/pdf/slr-inundation-methods.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NOAA. 2022. <italic>2022 Sea Level Rise Technical Report: Data and Tools</italic>.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/hazards/sealevelrise/sealevelrise-data.html">https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/hazards/sealevelrise/sealevelrise-data.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NOAA. 2023. Online vertical datum transformation. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://vdatum.noaa.gov/vdatumweb/">https://vdatum.noaa.gov/vdatumweb/</ext-link>. Accessed 27 Feb 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NOAA. 2024. Restoration Atlas. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.habitat.noaa.gov/apps/restoration-atlas/">https://www.habitat.noaa.gov/apps/restoration-atlas/</ext-link>.&#x000a0;Accessed 29 Feb 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudnicky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tombleson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A geospatial modeling approach to assess site suitability of living shorelines and emphasize best shoreline management practices</article-title><source>Ecological Engineering</source><year>2022</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>106617</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoleng.2022.106617</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Nunez, K., T. Rudnicky, P. Mason, C. Tombleson, and M. Berman. 2022. A geospatial modeling approach to assess site suitability of living shorelines and emphasize best shoreline management practices. <italic>Ecological Engineering</italic> 179: 106617. 10.1016/j.ecoleng.2022.106617.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">OMC Partners. 2024. 2018 - 2020 FDEM Lidar: Florida Peninsular.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/inport/item/64526">https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/inport/item/64526</ext-link>. Accessed 2 May 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parkinson, R., V. Seidel, and C. Henderson. 2020. <italic>Ensuring resiliency of the Indian River Lagoon to climate change stressors</italic>. Final Report. Sebastian, Florida: Indian River Lagoon National Estuary Program.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relevance of ongoing mitigation efforts to reduce Indian River Lagoon water quality impairment and restore ecosystem function under conditions of a changing climate</article-title><source>Florida Scientist</source><year>2023</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>210</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Parkinson, R.W. 2023. Relevance of ongoing mitigation efforts to reduce Indian River Lagoon water quality impairment and restore ecosystem function under conditions of a changing climate. <italic>Florida Scientist</italic> 86: 199&#x02013;210.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parkinson, R. W., and V. Seidel. 2018. <italic>Climate change vulnerability assessment of the Indian River Lagoon National Estuary Program&#x02019;s comprehensive conservation and management plan</italic>. Final Report. Sebastian, Florida: Indian River Lagoon National Estuary Program.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wdowinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerating sea-level rise and the fate of mangrove plant communities in South Florida, U.S.A</article-title><source>Geomorphology</source><year>2022</year><volume>412</volume><fpage>108329</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geomorph.2022.108329</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Parkinson, R.W., and S. Wdowinski. 2022. Accelerating sea-level rise and the fate of mangrove plant communities in South Florida, U.S.A. <italic>Geomorphology</italic> 412: 108329. 10.1016/j.geomorph.2022.108329.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wdowinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unified conceptual model of coastal response to accelerating sea level rise, Florida, U.S.A</article-title><source>Science of The Total Environment</source><year>2023</year><volume>892</volume><fpage>164448</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.164448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37257607</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Parkinson, R.W., and S. Wdowinski. 2023. A unified conceptual model of coastal response to accelerating sea level rise, Florida, U.S.A. <italic>Science of The Total Environment</italic> 892: 164448. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.164448.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37257607</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wdowinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geomorphic response of the Georgia Bight Coastal Zone to accelerating sea level rise, Southeastern USA</article-title><source>Coasts</source><year>2023</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/coasts4010001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Parkinson, R.W., and S. Wdowinski. 2023b. Geomorphic response of the Georgia Bight Coastal Zone to accelerating sea level rise, Southeastern USA. <italic>Coasts</italic> 4: 1&#x02013;20. 10.3390/coasts4010001.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pratt, A., and J. Nunes. 2012. <italic>Interactive design: an introduction to the theory and application of user-centered design</italic>. Rockport Publishers.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.perlego.com/book/2064889/interactive-design-an-introduction-to-thetheory-and-application-of-usercentered-design-pdf">https://www.perlego.com/book/2064889/interactive-design-an-introduction-to-thetheory-and-application-of-usercentered-design-pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 19 Mar 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ray, G. 2007. <italic>Thin layer placement of dredged material con coastal wetlands - a review of technical and scientific literature</italic>. ERDC/EL TN-07&#x02013;1. Vicksburg, Mississippi: United States Army Corps of Engineers.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reguero</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresch</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Calil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meliane</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing the cost effectiveness of nature-based and coastal adaptation: a case study from the Gulf Coast of the United States. Edited by Juan A. A&#x000f1;el</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0192132</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29641611</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Reguero, B.G., M.W. Beck, D.N. Bresch, J. Calil, and I. Meliane. 2018. Comparing the cost effectiveness of nature-based and coastal adaptation: a case study from the Gulf Coast of the United States. Edited by Juan A. A&#x000f1;el. <italic>PLOS ONE</italic> 13: e0192132. 10.1371/journal.pone.0192132.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29641611</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Restore America&#x02019;s Estuaries. 2015. <italic>Living shorelines - from barriers to opportunities</italic>. Arlington, VA: Restore America&#x02019;s Estuaries.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robison, D., T. Ries, J. Saarinen, D. Tomasko, and C. Sciarrino. 2020. <italic>Tampa Bay Estuary Program 2020 Habitat Master Plan Update</italic>. Technical Report 07&#x02013;20. Tampa, Florida: Tampa Bay Estuary Program.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigua</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tweedale</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water-quality monitoring and biological integrity assessment in the Indian River Lagoon, Florida: Status, trends, and loadings (1988&#x02013;1994)</article-title><source>Environmental Management</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002679910016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594193</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Sigua, G.C., J.S. Steward, and W.A. Tweedale. 2000. Water-quality monitoring and biological integrity assessment in the Indian River Lagoon, Florida: Status, trends, and loadings (1988&#x02013;1994). <italic>Environmental Management</italic> 25: 199&#x02013;209.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594193</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Virnstein</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Setting seagrass depth, coverage, and light targets for the Indian River Lagoon system, Florida</article-title><source>Estuaries</source><year>2005</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02696020</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Steward, J.S., R.W. Virnstein, L.J. Morris, and E.F. Lowe. 2005. Setting seagrass depth, coverage, and light targets for the Indian River Lagoon system, Florida. <italic>Estuaries</italic> 28: 923&#x02013;935. 10.1007/BF02696020.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The accuracy and consistency of 3D elevation program data: A systematic analysis</article-title><source>Remote Sensing</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>940</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/rs14040940</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Stoker, J., and B. Miller. 2022. The accuracy and consistency of 3D elevation program data: A systematic analysis. <italic>Remote Sensing</italic> 14: 940. 10.3390/rs14040940.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Swann, L. 2008. The use of living shorelines to mitigate the effects of storm events on Dauphin Island, Alabama, USA. <italic>American Fisheries Society Symposium</italic>&#x000a0;64:1&#x02013;11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sweet, W. V., B. D. Hamlington, R. E. Kopp, C. P. Weaver, P. L. Barnard, D. Bekaert, W. Brooks, et al. 2022. <italic>Global and regional sea level rise scenarios for the United States: updated mean projections and extreme water level probabilities along U.S. coastlines,</italic> 111.&#x000a0;Technical Report NOS 01, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, National Ocean Service, Silver Spring, Maryland: NOAA.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/hazards/sealevelrise/noaa-nostechrpt01-global-regional-SLR-scenarios-US.pdf">https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/hazards/sealevelrise/noaa-nostechrpt01-global-regional-SLR-scenarios-US.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Temmerman, S., E. M. Horstman, K. W. Krauss, J. C. Mullarney, I. Pelckmans, and K. Schoutens. 2023. Marshes and mangroves as nature-based coastal storm buffers. <italic>Annual Review of Marine Science</italic> 15: annurev-marine-040422&#x02013;092951. 10.1146/annurev-marine-040422-092951.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tetra Tech, Inc. 2022. <italic>Save Our Indian River Lagoon Project Plan 2022 Update</italic>. Brevard County, Florida: Natural Resources Management Department.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">US EPA. 2024. EJScreen: environmental justice screening and mapping tool. <italic>Collections and Lists</italic>.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/ejscreen">https://www.epa.gov/ejscreen</ext-link>. Accessed 1 Mar 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wilber, P. 1992. <italic>Thin-layer disposal: concepts and terminology</italic>. Information Exchange Bulletin D-92&#x02013;1. Environmental Effects of Dredging. Vicksburg, Mississippi: United States Army Corps of Engineers.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zylberman, J. M. 2016. <italic>Modeling site suitability of living shoreline design options in Connecticut</italic>. Master of Science, Storrs, CT: University of Connecticut.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>