<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats-oasis2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Innovation (Abingdon)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Innovation (Abingdon)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Innovation (Abingdon, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1351-1610</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-8412</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11371257</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2309173</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13511610.2024.2309173</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Creating pathways to just and sustainable food systems with citizen assemblies</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">
<italic toggle="yes">Innovation: The European Journal of Social Science Research</italic>
</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head"><italic toggle="yes">P. Schmid</italic> et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="AF2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><xref rid="B01" ref-type="bio"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lamotte</surname><given-names>L&#x000e9;a</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="B02" ref-type="bio"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="AF3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="B03" ref-type="bio"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bieri</surname><given-names>Sabin</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="B04" ref-type="bio"/></contrib><aff id="AF1"><label>a</label>Centre for Development and Environment (CDE), <institution>University of Bern</institution>, <city>Bern</city>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="AF2"><label>b</label>Institute of Geography (GIUB), <institution>University of Bern</institution>, <city>Bern</city>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="AF3"><label>c</label>Department of Food System Sciences, <institution>Research Institute of Organic Agriculture FiBL</institution>, <city>Frick</city>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Corresponding author. Email: <email xlink:href="patricia.schmid@unibe.ch">patricia.schmid@unibe.ch</email> Patricia Schmid, Centre for Development and Environment (CDE), Mittelstrasse 43, 3012 Bern</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-title>Special Issue on Citizen Assemblies</issue-title><fpage seq="8">832</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="received"><date><day>7</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="accepted"><date><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="tagger"><event-desc>Nova techset</event-desc><date><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="final"><event-desc>Converted to JATS 1.2 by Nova Techset</event-desc><date><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The terms on which this article has been published allow the posting of the Accepted Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="CIEJ_37_2309173.pdf"/><abstract><p>Food systems affect and are affected by the interrelated crises of climate change, biodiversity loss, resource depletion and health, amongst others. Transforming to sustainable approaches is vital, yet entangled with uncertainties, complexity and a great value diversion with stakeholders. Deliberative processes such as citizen assemblies offer a valuable contribution to such a transformation, since the crises and their responses affect everyday life, and therefore inviting individual and collective action. Still, who is included and whose knowledge counts affects outcomes. Theoretically anchored in concepts of environmental justice, our study analyses three nation-wide citizens&#x02019; assemblies on climate change and food systems from Western Europe. It assesses (a) how citizens&#x02019; assemblies can incorporate a broad set of viewpoints and design more substantive political answers to current crises, and (b) whether citizens&#x02019; assemblies include environmental justice aspects to facilitate social change. The paper argues that systematic and methodologically reflected inclusion of various positionalities can inspire decision-making processes in that they incorporate procedural, recognition, and distributional justice to address problems of climate change or modern food systems. It concludes with offering further approaches to include more than scientific knowledge in deliberative processes for a just transformation towards sustainability.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>deliberation process</kwd><kwd>citizen assemblies</kwd><kwd>just transformation</kwd><kwd>climate crisis</kwd><kwd>food systems</kwd><kwd>environmental justice</kwd></kwd-group><support-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Swiss National Science Foundation, Sinergia Funding Programme</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001711</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CRSII5_202300</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation, Sinergia Funding Programme &#x02018;Deliberative Diets: Connecting producers and consumers to value the sustainability of Swiss food systems scenarios&#x02019; [Grant no. CRSII5_202300]</funding-statement></funding-group></support-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="67"/><page-count count="19"/><word-count count="8292"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" disp-level="1" id="S001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The crises our world faces today are unprecedented, interconnected and complex. The ongoing and accelerating crises of climate change, biodiversity loss, pollution and health, among others, endanger lives and well-being of current and future generations of humans and non-humans, and are unfairly distributed. The results mounting up from these crises, such as heatwaves, recent wildfires across Europe, and droughts, show the urgency for change.</p><p>The drastic effects of global crises can be exemplified by their interrelated links to food. The way we grow, distribute, access, prepare, eat and dispose of food affect and are affected by climate change, biodiversity loss, hunger and malnutrition, inequality, resource depletion and land degradation, among others (IPES-Food <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). For instance, farming is vulnerable to the increased variability in precipitation and temperature, and agricultural fertilisers decrease agrobiodiversity (Vermeulen, Campbell, and Ingram <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Smallholder farmers, ethnic minorities, women and people with low economic resources are unequally exposed to extreme hazardous climate events or to daily pollution from air, water and soil (Schlosberg and Collins <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Environmental injustice, driven by racial discrimination and socioeconomical exclusion, is reinforced by climate change, which reflects and increases social inequalities (Mohai, Pellow, and Roberts <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Furthermore, just working conditions for all workers and beings involved across the food value chains and equality in economic and physical access to healthy, environmentally friendly and culturally appropriate food for all are not ensured by the dominant agro-industrial food system (Mohai, Pellow, and Roberts <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Various external shocks at the regional and international level, including the war in Ukraine and the Covid-19 pandemic, have exacerbated these inequalities (Fiske et al. <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Rabbi et al. <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>)</p><p>Business-as-usual is not an option in the face of the multidimensional crises of the global food system, whose processes, responses and outcomes are closely linked to social, economic and political mechanisms (Castree <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Characterised by large uncertainties, complexity and divergent values among stakeholders (Rittel and Webber <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">1974</xref>; Scoones et al. <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), the global food system crisis can be identified as a &#x02018;wicked&#x02019; problem. As current dominating production, distribution and consumption practices are the underlying causes of the issues, fundamental transformations are urgently needed. Yet there exist diverging views on how a food system transformation would look like, and what sustainability entails (Moragues-Faus and Marsden <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). For example, technocratic and capital-intensive solutions and top-down approaches arguing for a green growth stand opposed to long-lived and new formations of community initiatives, subsistence practices and non-commodified relations with food (Moragues-Faus and Marsden <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). As such, how to act is contested and leads increasingly to polarisation among political parties and citizens. The call for immediate change and transformation to sustainability (FAO <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; HLPE <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) conclude with the need to redesign agri-food policies based on democratic processes and call for methods that bring local voices into decision-making (HLPE <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Pimbert, Thompson, and Vorley <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>).</p><p>Existing political institutions, both by design and development, are unable to address the scale and urgency of these challenges. Political processes tend to be slow and indecisive in implementing substantial and radical changes. Further, political decisions are generally taken in the rhythm of the electoral cycle rather than in response to actual crises (Smith <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). In response to the political deficit on immediate action, deliberative approaches have become more popular (Goodin and Dryzek <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). This participatory turn signals a widespread acceptance of the need to include a range of social actors in more open policy forums to deal with increasingly complex issues (Blue <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Deliberative approaches are &#x02018;grounded in an ideal in which people come together, based on the equal status and mutual respect, to discuss the political issues they face, and based on those discussions, decide on policies that will affect their lives&#x02019; (B&#x000e4;chtiger et al. <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, 2). By evaluating new information and arguments made by other participants, they can make well-informed decisions and revise their preferences (Chambers <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).</p><p>In Europe, the institutionalised deliberative wave has been building since the 1980s and became stronger in recent years (Chwalisz <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). For instance, recent national citizen assemblies took place in Austria and the UK on climate change, and the first national citizen assembly on food system policy was carried out in Switzerland in 2022 (Buergerinnenrat <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). The OECD report entitled &#x02018;Catching the deliberative wave: Innovative Citizen Participation &#x00026; New Democratic Institutions&#x02019; (Chwalisz <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) is the first comprehensive body of work on the use and effectiveness of citizen assemblies and recommends deliberative processes for complex problems that involve trade-offs. It recommends them as a mean for better policy outcomesand enhance trust between citizens and government (Chwalisz <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).</p><p>In this paper, we discuss the potential of citizen assemblies as a tool to respond to crises such as climate change or governing food systems, and how they incorporate justice aspects in their design and outcomes. To do this, we first articulate the contemporary food system crisis and citizen assemblies as a tool to articulate solutions, and put them in relation to environmental justice. Second, we conduct a comparative qualitative analysis of three citizen assemblies (two on climate change and one on food system policy) and assess the role of justice in their process design and recommendations. The paper concludes with a discussion of the key findings.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" disp-level="1" id="S002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2001"><title>Review of the literature on food systems and deliberative democracy</title><p>As a conceptual framework, we used an informal review of the literature. First, we discuss the necessary transformation of the global food system in crisis and highlight why justice is a central component towards transformation. Second, we connect key studies from the deliberative democracy literature that examine citizen assemblies with justice aspects lend from environmental justice. In both cases, we did not aim for a reproducible or systematic approach but selected key literature in the respective topics.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2002"><title>Qualitative, comparative case study analysis</title><p>The paper employs a comparative case study approach based on the analysis of public material and scientific articles resulting from three European national citizen assemblies; two on climate change in Austria and the UK, and one on food system policy in Switzerland. The cases were selected based on their recent implementation, relevance to food systems, Western European context, national scale, and public availability of documentation and other material. While diverse forms of deliberative mini-publics occurred all over the world and at various scales (from local to global), we decided to engage only in a Western European context to better facilitate comparison within aligned conditions and a partly shared political system.</p><p>The material analysed consists of written, public documents from the citizen assemblies, related to their design and citizens&#x02019; recommendations. This approach focuses on the collective public statements and recommendations of the assemblies as a participatory learning and action approach (Kuruganti, Pimbert, and Wakeford <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), in contrast to conducting individual interviews with participants or experts after the process.</p><p>The case study material was analysed using two analytic frameworks: (a) the OECD set of good practice criteria for deliberative processes (Chwalisz <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) and (b) a perspective based on the three components (distribution, procedure and recognition) of environmental justice (Schlosberg <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). These two frameworks were selected because of their relevance to evaluate the case studies in terms of their setup and outcomes. Additionally, the environmental justice framework plays well into some of the OECD criteria and complements with its specific justice focus. The following section explains these frameworks and relates them to the food system and citizen assemblies.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="S003"><title>Conceptual framework</title><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2001"><title>Transforming the global food system in crisis</title><p>Multiple socioeconomic and political drivers have pushed the food system into its current state, including large-scale commercial farming practices and long value chains that put profit over social and ecological well-being (Willett et al. <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The industrialisation, globalisation and corporatisation of the food system have been intensified by increasing financialisation (Clapp <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). This resulted from liberalisation of agricultural futures markets in the 1980s and 1990s, leading to new speculative markets to emerge around agricultural commodities (e.g. &#x02018;commodity index funds&#x02019;) and direct investment in farmland (Clapp <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). As a consequence, increasing institutional and corporate investments have spurred alarming trends in land and water grabbing, which increases asset prices and threatens local food security and nutrition, and has been observed across all of the world&#x02019;s continents (Rulli, Saviori, and D&#x02019;Odorico <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In terms of environmental impact, global agriculture is responsible for 21&#x02013;37% of global emissions (IPCC <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), of which the livestock sector alone is accountable for roughly 9% (Caro et al. <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Large-scale monocultures lead to soil depletion, and these effects as well as further influences from climate change impact farming (IPCC <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Additionally, agriculture uses 70% of freshwater resources in the world, mostly for irrigation (IPCC <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Dietary trends have seen rising meat consumption globally, along with other animal source protein (such as dairy, seafood), which put a huge pressure on life support systems (Godfray et al. <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Even though these impacts are severe, a third of the produced food is wasted along the food chain (IPCC <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p><p>While the production of our daily food relies on the many smallholder farmers, the concentration of control by a handful of firms forms the decision-making (Pimbert, Thompson, and Vorley <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). A handful of firms are involved and increasingly control what we eat from biotechnology to production and processing food (Pimbert, Thompson, and Vorley <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). As a result, the food system resembles an hour-glass: at the top are millions of farmers and farm labourers who produce the food, and at the bottom are billions of consumers. At the narrow point in the middle are the few multinational corporations such as input suppliers, processors and retailers, which earn a significant profit from every transaction (Pimbert, Thompson, and Vorley <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). These unjust power relations underline the lack of democracy in the global food system.</p><p>The social burden of these trends is immense and unjustly carried. Even though the narrative of the globalised food system promised to decrease hunger (Campbell <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), hunger levels are rising again since 2014 while many suffer from diseases of malnutrition and overconsumption (FAO <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The 2022 Global Report on Food Crises (FAO <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>) highlights the remarkably high severity and numbers of people in crisis, driven by persistent conflict, pre-existing and COVID-19-related economic shocks, and weather extremes. Additionally, the war in Ukraine has led to global shortages of grains and fertilisers due to high import dependency and brittle globalized supply chains, particularly affecting farmers and consumers who cannot afford skyrocketing prices (IPES-Food <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Taken together, because of the inadequate nourishment of the world&#x02019;s population and the many environmental systems and processes pushed beyond their safe boundaries by food production, a transformation of the food system is urgently needed (Willett et al. <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p><p>For such a transformation, it is important to account that the crises do not affect all in the same way (Bailey <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). As such, people who are currently more impacted due to unequal power relations need to be at the centre of restructuring to ensure a fair change. Some examples of the global food system inequalities include the structural hindrance for women to access land (Agarwal and Bina <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Meinzen-Dick et al. <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>); poor and toxic working conditions for mostly migrant workers along the food chain (Bogoeski <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>); erasure of traditional agricultural and spiritual knowledge relating to food preparation and consumption (Swiderska et al. <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>); and uneven economic and physical access to healthy and sustainable food (Sen <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">1982</xref>). Thus, the complex of racism, sexism and ethnocentrism continues to pervade all relations of domination (Verg&#x000e8;s, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and reinforces existing unequal power relations. If marginalised and previously excluded groups continue to be denied a seat at the table, the crises cannot be tackled in a just way. However, justice-relevant considerations in transforming the food system remain scare (Tribaldos and Kortetm&#x000e4;ki <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p><p>While these &#x02018;wicked problems&#x02019; impact all citizens in one way or another, many consumers are estranged from them as well as from the realities on farms, as supermarkets display a variety of products whose sources are not easily recognisable. Yet, food is a basic human need, and the structure of the food system affects us all. The way food is produced and consumed forms part of everyday life and therefore inviting individual and collective action (United Nations <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). As such, public deliberation on food systems offers a valuable contribution to address the crises.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2002"><title>Citizen assemblies as a response to the food system crisis</title><p>Participatory tools such as citizen assemblies provide bottom-up, place-based answers that consider local needs, and diverse value positions. Citizen assemblies consist of a certain number of people who represent the population of a specific area in relation to age, gender, professions, political affiliations, among others, who then deliberate over a certain period of time on a given issue. Perhaps the best-known citizen assemblies and most effective in terms of policy implementation took place in Ireland on same-sex marriage (2015), and later on abortion and climate change (2016&#x02013;2018). They not only led to changes in law, but also challenged the presumption that some obstacles to reform were immutable. During the COVID-19 pandemic, citizen assemblies formed in many European cities, such as the COVID-19 Forum in the German state of Saxony, or the Bristol Citizen&#x02019;s Assembly on &#x02018;ways out of the Covid-19 crisis&#x02019;. On the issue of climate change, further local and national citizen assemblies took place in Austria, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Scotland and United Kingdom in 2020&#x02013;2022. Additionally, a network was created to link existing initiatives and support further assemblies (KNOCA <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p><p>The OECD developed principles for high-quality deliberative processes that result in useful recommendations for process design (Chwalisz <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The OECD report explored close to 300 deliberative processes, upon which the principles were based. The list of criteria, along with a description of how they were used in the case study research is provided in <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. These include the deliberation on a public problem; the commitment of commissioning authorities to respond to or act on recommendations in a timely manner; the constellation of participants as a microcosmos of the general public; efforts to ensure inclusiveness through remuneration and providing for care work; access to wide range of expertise and evidence; finding common ground through careful and active listening that weights and considers multiple perspectives (Chwalisz <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, 17).
<table-wrap position="float" id="T0001"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Evaluation criteria for the three citizen assemblies compared in the study (based on Chwalisz <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Schlosberg <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left">Criterion</th><th align="center">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" align="left"><italic toggle="yes">OECD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Problem formulation</td><td align="left">The task should be clearly defined as a question that is linked to a public problem.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Agreed political impact</td><td align="left">The commissioning authority should publicly commit to responding to or acting on recommendations in a timely manner and should monitor and regularly report on the progress of their implementation.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Transparency and communication</td><td align="left">Anyone should be able to easily find the following information about the process: its purpose, design, methodology, recruitment details, experts, recommendations, the authority&#x02019;s response, and implementation follow-up. Better public communication should increase opportunities for public learning and encourage greater participation.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Demographic representation</td><td align="left">Participants should be a microcosm of the general public; this can be achieved through random sampling from which a representative selection is made to ensure the group matches the community&#x02019;s demographic profile.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Socio-economic inclusiveness</td><td align="left">Efforts should be made to ensure inclusiveness, such as through remuneration, covering expenses, and/or providing/paying for childcare or eldercare.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Balanced, wide and partly open input material</td><td align="left">Participants should have access to a wide range of accurate, relevant, and accessible evidence and expertise, and have the ability to request additional information.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High-quality facilitation</td><td align="left">Group deliberation entails finding common ground; this requires careful and active listening, weighing and considering multiple perspectives, every participant having an opportunity to speak, a mix of formats, and skilled facilitation.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sufficient depth and duration</td><td align="left">For high-quality processes that result in informed recommendations, participants should meet for at least four full days in person, as deliberation requires adequate time for participants to learn, weigh evidence, and develop collective recommendations.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Independence of coordination team</td><td align="left">To help ensure the integrity of the process, it should be run by an arm&#x02019;s&#x02019; length co-ordinating team.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left"><italic toggle="yes">Environmental Justice</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Distribution</td><td align="left">Allocation of benefits and burdens, focusing on recommendations</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Procedure</td><td align="left">Process of decision-making, fair inclusion of all involved people</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Recognition</td><td align="left">Recognition of certain groups or people, cultural aspects, recognised knowledges in both process and recommendations</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2003"><title>Justice in deliberative processes</title><p>Current power relations enforce environmental inequalities regarding race, ethnicity, gender, class, abilities and other social categories (Pulido <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). These are often internalised and, as such, need to be reflected upon in participatory processes. To examine how these cases of citizen assemblies contribute to justice in social change, this analysis borrows from the three interrelated dimensions of environmental justice, being distributional justice, procedural justice and recognition (Schlosberg <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). The early environmental justice scholarship, born out of a movement of racialised communities in North Carolina who lived close to hazardous waste sites (Mohai, Pellow, and Roberts <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), focused mainly on distributional justice. The biological necessities for living a life towards flourishing should be justly accessed and enjoyed (Mohai, Pellow, and Roberts <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). As such, all people should have the ability to breathe clean air, drink clean water, grow food within soil that is unpolluted or harm-filled, and eat fish, plants and animals without fear of poisoning (Stock and Szrot <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Later on, issues of representation, participation and self-determination formed part of the discourse (Young <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>), which formed into the framework with distributional, procedural and recognition justice (Schlosberg <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). These three dimensions are subsequently put into relation to the design and outcomes of citizen assemblies.</p><p>Distributional justice looks at the allocation of benefits and burdens in a specific context or social system (Schlosberg <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). As Smith (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) points out, deliberation orients people toward the common good and makes space to consider the interests of future generations as well as non-human beings. As such, the crises can be considered with significance from short to long-term, counterbalancing the tendency in politics on the immediate (Willis, Curato, and Smith <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Citizen assemblies allow for recommendations less dependent on existing power structures (Dryzek et al. <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The variety of sources and evidence exposed to the assembly is a key factor, framing the issues and influencing both process and outcomes. As such, deliberative theory suggests that the issue frame should be a fair representation of conflicting views and arguments (Nabatchi et al. <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, 210), which could help participants to reflect on how to equally (re)allocate wealth and responsibilities.</p><p>Procedural justice is concerned about the process of decision-making with a fair participation, equal say for involved people and transparent procedures (Fraser <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). This concerns the process design such as voting mechanisms within citizen assemblies, and a facilitation that ensures that all voices are heard. Moral and ethical positions, the value of knowledges of different actors, particularly the most affected and vulnerable, is considered in deliberative democracy literature (Hammond <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Deliberative democracy, at its heart, aims to counter the expression of dominant power and interests for their own benefit (Willis, Curato, and Smith <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). It opens a space for collective decision-making within a range of perspectives that might otherwise be absent from expert communities and political or media discourses (Blue <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Additionally, participants may feel pressured that the recommendations are accepted by the broader public and policy makers and thus soften their demands. These inherent power relations are crucial to consider for the process design and, as stated by Curato (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, vi), deliberation &#x02018;gains relevance when it navigates complex relations of power in modern societies, learns from its mistakes, and remains epistemically humble but not politically meek&#x02019;.</p><p>Finally, recognition deals with practices of cultural domination, non-recognition rendering certain peoples or groups invisible, and disrespect of certain peoples or groups in public and cultural discourse (Fraser <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Recognition valorises capabilities, experiences, contributions, knowledges and normative judgement (Fraser <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) of the participants. Further, scholars have discussed knowledge representation in citizen assemblies (Blue <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Petts and Brooks <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) and whether lay publics are viewed as lacking requisite knowledge who need to be informed to take good decisions. Such a bias towards expert knowledge can hinder the inclusion of other knowledges (Blue <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Iris Young&#x02019;s conception of communicative democracy aims to include diverse knowledges within deliberation with
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p>particularities instead of universalisms, narratives instead of speeches, emotional components instead of abstract reason, bodily expressions instead of protocols and formalism, thus making pluralism and its diverse forms of evidence emerge, so that people and groups previously silenced and obliterated can feel part of the democratic dynamics. (Lima and Sobottka <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>)</p></disp-quote></p><p>The importance of the positionalities and knowledges of citizens can be exemplified through food. All of us need to eat to live and should therefore have a say in the access to food that is healthy, culturally appropriate and respectful of the environment. Thus, a representative sample of the population automatically includes farmers, farm workers, distributors and consumers, who can share their perspectives in a citizen assembly.</p><p>To understand the procedure and how citizen assemblies contribute to environmental justice in an European setting, the paper subsequently presents the analysis of three country-wide citizen assemblies in terms of the procedure and recommendations and therein incorporation of the mentioned justice aspects.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" id="S004"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2" id="S004-S2001"><title>Case studies: citizen assemblies as response to systemic crises</title><p>In this section, the three selected citizen assemblies are explored in terms of process and outcomes. A summary of characteristics and evaluation results is provided in <xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.
<table-wrap position="float" id="T0002"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Summary of the characteristics and evaluation of each case study with respect to the OECD criteria for good practice deliberation.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left">Case study and country</th><th align="center">Der Klimarat (climate assembly), AU</th><th align="center">Climate assembly, UK</th><th align="center">Citizen assembly on food system policy, CH</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Schedule</bold></td><td align="left">2022 (6 months)</td><td align="left">2020 (5 months)</td><td align="left">2022 (6 months)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Problem formulation</bold></td><td align="left">Climate policy up to 2040 (general task: &#x02018;What do we have to do today, to live in a climate friendly future tomorrow?&#x02019;)</td><td align="left">Climate policy up to 2050 (specific task: &#x02018;How should the UK meet its target of net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050?&#x02019;)</td><td align="left">Food system policy up to 2030 (specific task: &#x02018;How should a food policy for Switzerland look like that makes healthy, sustainable, animal-friendly and fairly produced food available to all people by 2030?&#x02019;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Agreed political impact</bold></td><td align="left">No direct policy consequences. Federal council promised to deal with recommendations.</td><td align="left">No direct policy consequences.</td><td align="left">No direct policy consequences. Federal council promised to deal with recommendations.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Transparency and communication</bold></td><td align="left">Information and details of process and outcomes are readily available</td><td align="left">Information and details of process and outcomes are readily available</td><td align="left">Information and details of process and outcomes are readily available</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Demographic representation</bold></td><td align="left">Random selection according to characteristics of age, gender, highest completed school education, income, regions, country of birth, degree of urbanisation, to represent people living in Austria</td><td align="left">Sortition according to age, gender, educational qualification, ethnicity, where in the UK they live, whether they live in an urban or rural area, and attitudes to climate change</td><td align="left">Random selection representative of the Swiss resident population in terms of age, gender, language, place of residence, and political interests.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Socio-economic inclusiveness</bold></td><td align="left">Small renumeration for participants, travel, food, and accommodation expenses during meetings.</td><td align="left">Small renumeration for participants, travel, food, and accommodation expenses during meetings. Costs related to childcare or bringing a carer covered.</td><td align="left">Small renumeration for participants, travel, food, and accommodation expenses during meetings.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Balanced, wide and partly open input material</bold></td><td align="left">Mixed consortium of scientific experts and interest groups</td><td align="left">Mixed consortium of scientific experts</td><td align="left">Mixed consortium of scientific experts and interest groups</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>High-quality facilitation</bold></td><td align="left">Independent facilitation and mixed format of inputs, discussions</td><td align="left">Independent facilitation and mixed format of inputs, discussions, preferred visions</td><td align="left">Independent facilitation and mixed format of inputs, discussions, learning journeys</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Sufficient depth and duration</bold></td><td align="left">Six full weekend meetings (all present) during 6 months</td><td align="left">Six full weekends, three present and three online during 5 months</td><td align="left">Two full weekends to start and close, one day mid-meeting (all present); six online meetings; 2 learning journeys per participant. During 6 months</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Independence of coordination team</bold></td><td align="left">Commissioned by Federal Ministry for Climate Protection, Environment, Energy, Mobility, Innovation and Technology, participant recruiting by Austria&#x02019;s Federal Statistical Office, facilitation by consortium of &#x000d6;GUT, pulswerk und PlanSinn</td><td align="left">Commissioned by six select committees of the House of Commons, participant recruiting by Sortition Foundation, facilitation by The Involve Foundation, branding and website by mySociety</td><td align="left">Commissioned by grassroot organisation &#x02018;Landwirtschaft mit Zukunft&#x02019;, the foundation &#x02018;Biovision&#x02019; and the SDSN network for sustainability solutions, participant recruiting by Demoscope, facilitation by Collaborato Helvetica</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec disp-level="3" id="S004-S2001-S3001"><title>Case 1: Der Klimarat (climate council) Austria</title><p>At the end of 2021, 58% of the population in Austria were of the opinion that the political system does not function well (SORA, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). To respond to a popular petition claiming for a climate referendum which gathered 400,000 signatories (Verein Klimavolksbegehren <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), the Federal Ministry for Climate Protection, Environment, Energy, Mobility, Innovation and Technology commissioned the creation &#x02018;der Klimarat&#x02019;, the first citizens&#x02019; council at the federal level. This national citizens&#x02019; assembly was formed to explore new political avenues for addressing climate change, debate policy responses and guide future good practices to achieve Austria&#x02019;s climate targets (Buzog&#x000e1;ny et al. <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Hollaus <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). From January to June 2022, 84 people, randomly selected though Austria&#x02019;s Federal Statistical Office according to characteristics of age, gender, highest completed school education, income, regions, country of birth and degree of urbanisation, to represent people living in Austria, were tasked with drafting measures to submit to National Council and the Federal Ministry for Climate Protection (Hollaus <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Propositions should answer the open question: &#x02018;What do we need to do today to live in a climate-friendly future tomorrow?&#x02019; The timeline was further specified up to 2040.</p><p>According to the resolution of the Austrian National Council, the Climate Council was a &#x02018;participatory process for discussing and elaboration of concrete proposals for the climate protection measures necessary to achieve the goals on the way to climate neutrality in 2040&#x02019;. (ARGE Klimarat, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>, 11). At its core laid the question of how to make thoughtful decisions that combat climate change and empower citizens simultaneously (Buzog&#x000e1;ny et al. <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). On the first weekend, the Federal Council guaranteed the participants that they would deal with each of the Climate Council&#x02019;s proposals (ARGE Klimarat, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>:31), yet did not specify how. The measures were submitted to the Climate Cabinet and the Federal Government respectively with a press conference. As such, the final decision on the implementation of the proposed measures were in the hands of the political authorities <underline>(</underline>Hollaus <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref><underline>)</underline>. The participating citizens decided to set up an association after the process and regularly meet with organisations and politicians to further the demands of the citizen assembly (Noren <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p><p>The evaluation of Buzog&#x000e1;ny et al. (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>) highlights an &#x02018;adequate level of knowledge integration&#x02019;. A mixed consortium of scientific experts provided participants with information texts and video interviews. During the first three weekends, scientists gave inputs to the five defined fields of action, being Energy, Production/Consumption, Food/Land Use, Mobility and Housing. The task was discussed in ten smaller groups, consisting of two groups within each of the five themes. The group met physically on six full weekends and prepared individually during the time in-between. The scientific consortium compiled four to five levers per theme, and the ten working groups developed recommendations on these levers. In their analysis, Buzog&#x000e1;ny et al. (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>) also show that the deliberative process succeeded in bringing together participants from different social groups and encouraged them to engage in dialogue and self-reflection.</p><p>The climate assembly agreed on a total of 93 recommendations within the five themes (ARGE Klimarat, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). The measures are very diverse and operate at different levels of government from local to national and involve different departments. The spectrum ranges from compulsory climate change education in schools to the introduction of a carbon tax of 55&#x020ac;/t CO<sub>2</sub>, rising to 240&#x020ac;/t by 2030, with specific social design, to a ban on the destruction of new goods and services (Clar, Omann, and Scherhaufer <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). As such, the recommendations call for a more demanding climate policy than existing Austrian policy-making in the field (Buzog&#x000e1;ny et al. <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p><p>Justice in terms of distribution has been mentioned in the recommendations. The preface of the recommendations outlines that &#x02018;[w]e know that there is a danger that the socially weakest part of the population will have to bear a particularly high burden in terms of climate protection, which is why the proposals also take into account that compensation must be provided here, e.g. through an urgently needed tax reform&#x02019; (ARGE Klimarat <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>, 7). Furthermore, the council elaborated on principles for political action, which includes regulations and framework conditions that make climate-friendly action very simple for everyone; that climate protection should not be a luxury; that climate protection measures must not lead to socially weaker groups losing out further, thus attention must be paid to social balance; people with a higher income should make a higher contribution to climate protection; the forming of cross-border alliances and financial and know-how support for other countries; institutionalising citizen participation; and the regular evaluation and adaption of measures and strategies. These principles were of a general nature. In specific recommendations, distributional justice was considered in two recommendations, namely introducing greenhouse gas tariffs and providing funding for innovative distribution channels. In terms of greenhouse gas tariffs, food and agricultural products should be subject to a greenhouse gas tax. As higher food prices due to these taxes are an additional burden on low-income households, a redistribution should compensate for it, as climate protection should not depend on income (ARGE Klimarat <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>, 47). In terms of funding for innovative distribution channels, the recommendation highlighted that the security of supply and social compatibility are not neglected. Social compatibility is currently also impaired by overcapacities that are exported cheaply to countries in the global South and destroy local economic structures there. According to the recommendations, these exports through overproduction should be avoided in the future by moving away from the current support system towards an incentive and support system that is more focused on climate protection and other social needs (ARGE Klimarat <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Thus, a fair distribution is especially discussed within economic means.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S004-S2001-S3002"><title>Case 2: Climate assembly UK</title><p>As the first nation-wide citizen assembly in the United Kingdom, the UK climate assembly took place between January and May 2020. The assembly was commissioned by the UK Parliament in autumn 2019 (Elstub et al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) by six committees of the House of Commons (Business Energy and Industrial Strategy; Environmental Audit; Housing, Communities and Local Government, Science and Technology; Transport; and Treasury) (UK Parliament <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). The discussion question was formulated as &#x02018;How should the UK meet its target of net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050?&#x02019; (UK Parliament <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>).</p><p>108 people took part in the climate assembly, and facilitation was provided by an independent organisation. Three organisations were contracted to run the climate assembly, one of which independently recruited the members through sortition. Members were represented according to age, gender, educational qualification, ethnicity, UK place of residence, urban or rural setting, and attitudes to climate change, to represent the UK population according to recent statistics of these metrics (Climate Assembly UK <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Inclusiveness was aspired with a small renumeration for participants, and travel, food, and hotel expenses.</p><p>The parliament showed a strong interest in citizen&#x02019;s opinion, but did not commit to implement any of the recommendations. In comparison to the Austrian case, the UK government set a legally binding target of net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050, and the citizen assembly was initiated to consider how this could be achieved. The resulting recommendations should be used by politicians and policy makers to scrutinise Government&#x02019;s policies and inform on public preferences. Ten areas were covered in the discussions: underpinning principles for the path to net zero; travel on land; travel by air; heat and energy use at home; eating and the use of land; buying; electricity; greenhouse gas removal; Covid-19; and additional recommendations. The final report was presented to the six select committees in September 2020.</p><p>On all six weekends, assembly participants received inputs from stakeholders and researchers and discussed specific topics related to reducing emissions. There was not a final voting on recommendations, as they were jointly discussed, and individual concerns were captured in the final report. Half of the meetings took place in person and had to be moved to online discussions due to COVID-19 restrictions. The climate assembly came forward with over 50 recommendations in a detailed 556-page report (Climate Assembly UK <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The evaluation by Elstub et al. (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) highlights that the participants became more knowledgeable on climate change and that their conviction on the achievability of net zero greenhouse gas emissions target evolved through the process. The researcher team of the climate assembly concluded that the involved citizens generated far more ambitious policies than politicians have ever come up with (Mellier &#x00026; Wilson <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Nevertheless, Elstub et al. (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) showed in their evaluation of the deliberative process that the effects of the process are endangered by the length of the assembly report, the lack of public awareness of the process and the turnover in the commissioning members.</p><p>In the introduction section of the report, fairness was a key theme:
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p>as with most things in life, the solutions to climate change are neither easy nor free, but they need to be fair. Fair to people with jobs in different sectors. Fair to people with different incomes, travel preferences and housing arrangements. Fair to people who live in different parts of the UK. (Climate Assembly UK <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, 6)</p></disp-quote>&#x02018;Fairness within the UK, including for the most vulnerable (affordability, jobs, UK regions, incentives and rewards) in actions, not just words&#x02019; (Climate Assembly UK <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, 12) was the second highest principle ordered in priority, just after education. Fairness for the most vulnerable globally was also a principle. This implies a broad understanding of fairness as it does not specifically mention intersectional or marginalised groups, except for &#x02018;most vulnerable globally&#x02019;. In specific recommendations, making low-carbon food more affordable was a recommendation that took distributional justice into account with &#x02018;[s]upport for people on low incomes to be able to access and cook/use healthy local foods&#x02019; (Climate Assembly UK <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, 263). Other aspects of distributional justice were not reflected in the recommendations.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S004-S2001-S3003"><title>Case 3: Swiss citizen assembly on food system policy</title><p>The first national citizen assembly in Switzerland took place over six months from June to November 2022. The task was clearly formulated as a question linked to a public problem: &#x02018;How should a food policy for Switzerland look like that makes healthy, sustainable, animal-friendly and fairly produced food available to all people by 2030?&#x02019;</p><p>The commissioning authority consisted of a grassroot organisation &#x02018;Landwirtschaft mit Zukunft&#x02019; (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.landwirtschaftmitzukunft.ch" ext-link-type="uri">www.landwirtschaftmitzukunft.ch</ext-link>), the foundation &#x02018;Biovision&#x02019; (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.biovision.ch" ext-link-type="uri">www.biovision.ch</ext-link>) and the Sustainable Development Solutions Network (SDSN; <ext-link xlink:href="https://sdsn.ch" ext-link-type="uri">https://sdsn.ch</ext-link>) and it was financially supported by federal state&#x02019;s offices for Agriculture, Food Safety and Veterinary Affairs and for the Environment <underline>(</underline>Buergerinnenrat <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref><underline>)</underline>. Such an institutional support legitimized the deliberative process. The assembly participants consisted of 80 people, recruited through a random process by an independent market research company, to be as representative as possible of the Swiss resident population in terms of age, gender, language, place of residence and political interests. Inclusiveness was aspired with a small renumeration for participants, travel and hotel expenses if necessary, and solutions for special assistance or care work were sought after. However, there were no general child care or other care services available. The assembly was conducted in German, French and Italian with translations where necessary, so that citizens from all parts of Switzerland could participate and exchange without limits of national languages.</p><p>An exchange event was organised between the citizen assembly, members of the cantonal and national council, and scientific members at the end of the process in November 2022. Additionally, during a one-day event at the beginning of February 2023, the recommendations were officially handed over to the federal council and further discussed between representatives of the jury, scientific members of the SDSN network, parliament members and other stakeholders. Thus, the government showed interest in the process, yet did not commit to implement the recommendations.</p><p>The guiding question was discussed in ten smaller groups, consisting of two groups within five themes: health, environment, social, economy and production. Facilitation was conducted through an independent organisation focusing on facilitating various change processes. The discussion in smaller groups aimed for all participants to share their voices. There were five full-day in-person meetings and six online meetings. The starting weekend to get to know each other, understand the process and receive inputs from science and a diverse range of stakeholders and interest groups; a mid-term day to discuss ideas and recommendations across smaller groups; and a finalising weekend to complete recommendations and vote on them in plenary. Six online meetings of two hours each were held in-between, focusing on dialogue in the respective groups per theme. Additionally, the participants joined two organised day excursions to actors that are creating change within the food system. During these learning journeys to a variety of innovative farms, producers and processors, participants learned from the knowledge of diverse actors. As such, a range of knowledge and inputs was given to participants, while they were informed that stakeholders represent a certain position and should be viewed as such <underline>(</underline>Buergerinnenrat <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref><underline>)</underline>.</p><p>A total of 126 recommendations were developed and accepted during the final voting day. They encompassed concrete and detailed ideas along the themes of ameliorating the social and economic situation of farmers, align agricultural practice and subsidies towards sustainability, align processing and trade, political instruments as well as education, consulting, and research towards sustainability, raising awareness towards health and sustainability for consumers, promote the truth of cost, and promoting the marketing of healthy and sustainable products (Buergerinnenrat <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>).</p><p>In terms of distributional justice, the recommendations addressed producers or consumers in a uniform way without intersectional distinctions. We identified four recommendations towards more specific distributional justice. First, the recommendation 85 concerning justice in food chains aims to align labels with social aspects in terms of the responsibility of corporations towards working conditions in their supply chains. Second, the recommendation 92 on price suggests to lower prices for healthy and sustainable products, so that people with lower incomes can eat healthy and seasonal. Third, the recommendation 93 on redistribution of profit voices for a fair payment of workers and actors in supply chains, as well as for redistributing profit from unsustainable products towards poorly paid actors in supply chains. Fourth, the recommendation 109 suggests providing grocery vouchers for healthy and sustainable food for people with less economic means.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" id="S005"><title>Discussion</title><p>The three cases all incorporate the best practices as suggested by OECD with a slight variability depending on their context. The setup of the three case studies includes a fair representation of inhabitants of each country with slightly differing criteria. In all cases, attention was given to inclusion in terms of financial remuneration, yet no specific care facilities were mentioned. The independent and professional facilitation increased that all voices were heared. In terms of outcomes, all three examples shows that citizens can put forward concrete recommendations on pressing issues and demand action that go further than governments&#x02019; agendas. This shows that citizens support a radical change when they are involved with the topic, which, in turn, could motivate policy makers to implement more profound measures than currently. In the case of the Austrian climate assembly, the provincial councillor of Salzburg voiced that &#x02018;[t]here is no lack of knowledge about what to do. We do not need new papers, not more concept writers. We need encouragers and courage for concrete results&#x02019; (ARGE Klimarat <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>, 35).</p><p>The three cases have shown that community interests and needs of marginalised people are considered in such deliberations, but are not explored in-depth.The statements of including the most vulnerable in the UK case highlights the participants&#x02019; understanding that climate change is embedded in complex international dynamics, yet measures remain on the surface. In Austria, the distributional justice perspective focused on social compatibility, and overcapacities that are exported cheaply to countries in the global South, thus reinforcing power imbalances. The report from the Klimarat suggested that such exports through overproduction should be avoided in the future by moving away from the current support system towards an incentive system that is more focused on climate protection and other social needs (ARGE Klimarat <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>, 47). The Swiss case explicitly mentioned justice in only four recommendations, which are, like the UK case, focusing on economic redistribution. As such, there remains a lack of fully incorporating distributional justice in the recommendations.</p><p>In terms of representation justice, participants should be able to voice their opinions, experiences, hopes and concerns. This was possible through independent facilitation, where all three cases mention the importance of hearing all voices. At the same time, all three cases are strongly oriented on scientific inputs, especially during the introductory meetings. The UK climate assembly, for instance, began with expert leads deciding on &#x02018;the range of evidence the assembly would need to hear to ensure members heard a balanced, accurate and comprehensive view of the topic&#x02019; (Climate Assembly UK <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), which makes the people&#x02019;s own experience secondary to expert inputs. While the cases gave attention to provide a range of views and inputs, more recognition and dedicated time could be given to citizens&#x02019; own knowledges.</p><p>Thus, a suggestion is the inclusion of more diverse knowledges in these processes. The Swiss citizen assembly included for example two field visits per participant to a diversity of food-related initiatives, which allows for a different way of learning from concrete experiences and includes a variety of knowledges. Inspiration could also come from other deliberation processes, for example through the KNOCA network in Europe. It may be valuable to try out a format where citizens are included in shaping the agenda, for example, the themes to discuss. (Pimbert, Thompson, and Vorley <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Other important factors are culture and emotional values connected to the problem that would allow for other, intimate knowledge to emerge as an addition to scientific inputs. To do so, Iris Young (<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>) advocates for various articulations of reason-giving, such as storytelling or testimonies, or Gordon, Haas, and Michelson (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), advocate for role-playing games in deliberative processes.</p><p>In terms of the process frame, Stirling (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) offers the distinction between opening up and closing down of policy options in deliberative processes. Processes that follow a closing-down approach show a set of possible pathways that make sense under a particular framing condition. The example from the UK climate assembly illustrates this pre-defined approach well. Here, participants deliberated on pre-defined pathways, while, in the other two cases, citizens brought up their own options. The opening up process, as such, examines neglected issues, marginalised perspectives and ignored uncertainties. The outputs are more of exploratory nature and can accommodate a broader range of options.</p><p>A further crucial point within a well-structured and inclusive deliberation process is that participants acquire skills of deep listening and learning from other perspectives. Involved citizen might also want to remain actively engaged with the topic, as the Austrian case shows with the establishment of an association of participants of the citizen assembly.</p><p>Finally, there still exists an implementation gap of the recommendations. Indeed, in all three cases, the recommendations were read with interest by political institutions, yet not concretely implemented. The long-term impact of citizen assemblies depends on the commitment of policy makers to take up the recommendations. Without it, citizen assemblies&#x02019; voices might be noted, yet established political and institutional power will remain untouched. As public authorities from all levels of government increasingly show their interest in citizen assemblies and other representative deliberative processes to tackle complex problems, they should show more commitment as to reinvigorate and enhance trust from citizens.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" disp-level="1" id="S006"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This paper discussed citizen assemblies as a tool to find solutions to current crises and advance towards transformation. It framed the global food system in crisis and how deliberative approaches could, with an integration of justice, provide necessary recommendations. The three case studies of national citizen assemblies in Austria, the United Kingdom and Switzerland showed that well-organised citizen assemblies can bring forward a variety of voices and opinions and that their recommendations go further than existing policies. The OECD good practice criteria for deliberative processes are valuable for an institutional and thorough setup, however, justice aspects should be better integrated. The environmental justice framework with distributional justice, procedural justice and recognition provides a helpful approach to ensure that justice is incorporated in the design and outcome of deliberative approaches.</p><p>As a shortcoming, we find that the investigated cases tend to focus on scientific inputs rather than participants&#x02019; own experiences and knowledges. It is crucial to reflect on whose narrative is given space, taken up and seen as valid in deliberative processes. This has somewhat been taken up within the deliberative processes design, yet, especially when deliberating on topics such as food where everyone is part of the chain, more importance could be laid on participants&#x02019; sources. This may be aided through testimonies or games.</p><p>Further, we found that justice is not an explicit concept used both in the structure of the researched citizen assemblies and their recommendations. We argue that their outcomes would benefit from such an integration. While justice aspects came up within the recommendations, they remained rather on the surface with speaking of a homogenous group of vulnerable people, and remained scarce in the number of recommendations.</p><p>Moreover, we framed citizen assemblies as a tool to strengthen policies and enhance trust between government and citizens. Yet, governments and policy makers did not oblige to implement the recommendations and continue to be slow in advancing measures for change. As such, the assemblies have not effectively been used for this goal.</p><p>We conclude that citizen assemblies could play a major role in finding solutions to crises and complex issues, if distributional, procedural and recognition justice form a part of the framework, participants&#x02019; knowledges are given more attention, and governments commit to the results.</p></sec></body><back><bio id="B01"><p><italic toggle="yes"><bold>Patricia Schmid</bold></italic> is a PhD student in Geography and Sustainable Development at the Centre of Development and Environment (CDE) and the Institute of Geography at the University of Bern, and holds a Master's degree in Human Ecology from Lund University in Sweden. Her research is informed by feminist political ecology and participatory approaches, and she is interested in justice aspects in food system transformation.</p></bio><bio id="B02"><p><italic toggle="yes"><bold>L&#x000e9;a Lamotte</bold></italic> is a PhD student in geography and sustainable development at the Centre for Development and Environment (CDE) in Switzerland. She holds a master's degree in political sciences and sustainable food systems politics from Sciences Po Lyon and Montpellier SupAgro (France). Her studies focus on exploring participatory creative methods, transformative pedagogies, students' daily food practices and sustainable food systems.</p></bio><bio id="B03"><p><italic toggle="yes"><bold>Michael Curran</bold></italic> is a senior research in sustainability sciences at the Research Institute of Organic Agriculture (FiBL) in Switzerland. He holds a PhD in environmental engineering from the ETH Z&#x000fc;rich and has published in the fields of ecology, conservation biology, ecological economics and sustainability sciences.</p></bio><bio id="B04"><p><italic toggle="yes"><bold>Sabin Bieri</bold></italic> is a sustainability specialist whose professional focus lies with issues of international development, poverty, inequality, and justice. A social geographer by background, she seeks to understand processes of uneven development in the North-South context, thus framing sustainability transformations from a truly global perspective. Her main areas of expertise include labour, agricultural transition, resilience in rural livelihoods, digital technology and gender relations. Her research builds on fieldproven scientific enquiries. As project leader she combined dirty-feet science, permanent stakeholder involvement and cutting-edge theoretical and methodological research in the service of grounded results that spurs innovations shared by local communities. Currently she is Director at the Centre for Development and Environment (CDE), University of Bern. Her work informs CDE&#x02018;s activities in land governance and global change from a social justice perspective.</p></bio><sec sec-type="COI-statement" disp-level="1" id="S007"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author(s).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Agarwal</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Bina</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>1994</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">A Field of One&#x02019;s Own: Gender and Land Rights in South Asia (No. 58)</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>ARGE Klimarat</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Klimaneutralit&#x000e4;t bis 2040: Die Empfehlungen</italic></source>. Accessed 10 February 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://klimarat.org/wp-content/uploads/Klimarat-Endbericht-WEB.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://klimarat.org/wp-content/uploads/Klimarat-Endbericht-WEB.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>B&#x000e4;chtiger</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J. S.</given-names>
<surname>Dryzek</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Mansbridge</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Warren</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Oxford Handbook of Deliberative Democracy</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Oxford: Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bailey</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Growing a Better Future: Food Justice in a Resource-Constrained World</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Oxford: Oxfam Policy and Practice</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Blue</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Public Deliberation with Climate Change: Opening Up or Closing Down Policy Options?</article-title>&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Review of European, Comparative &#x00026; International Environmental Law</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/reel.12122</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bogoeski</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Continuities of Exploitation: Seasonal Migrant Workers in German Agriculture During the COVID-19 Pandemic</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Law and Society</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jols.12389</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Buergerinnenrat</collab></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. <italic toggle="yes">Empfehlungen f&#x000fc;r die schweizer Ern&#x000e4;hrungspolitik</italic>. Accessed February 10, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.buergerinnenrat.ch/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/230207_Buergerinnenrat_DE.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.buergerinnenrat.ch/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/230207_Buergerinnenrat_DE.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Buzog&#x000e1;ny</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Ehs</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Pl&#x000f6;chl</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Scherhaufer</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;Evaluation Report of the Austrian Climate Citizens&#x02019; Assembly: Assessment of Input, Process, and Output.&#x0201d; Discussion Paper, Institute of Forest, Environmental and Natural Resource Policy, University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences, Vienna.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>. &#x0201c;<part-title>Let Us Eat Cake?: Historically Reframing the Problem of World Hunger and Its Purported Solutions</part-title>.&#x0201d; In <source><italic toggle="yes">Food Systems Failure</italic></source>, <fpage>edited by Christopher Rosin, Paul Stock, Hugh Campbell. 30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <publisher-name>Oxon: Routledge</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Caro</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S. J.</given-names>
<surname>Davis</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Bastianoni</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Caldeira</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Global and Regional Trends in Greenhouse Gas Emissions from Livestock</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Climatic Change</italic></source>
<volume>126</volume> (<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>): <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-014-1197-x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Castree</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Neoliberalising Nature: Processes, Effects, and Evaluations</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Environment and Planning A: Economy and Space</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1068/a39100</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chambers</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Deliberative Democratic Theory</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Annual Review of Political Science</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>326</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.polisci.6.121901.085538</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chwalisz</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<part-title>Good Practice Principles for Deliberative Processes for Public Decision Making</part-title>.&#x0201d; In <source><italic toggle="yes">Innovative Citizen Participation and New Democratic Institutions: Catching the Deliberative Wave</italic></source>, <fpage>edited by Pe&#x000f1;a-L&#x000f3;pez, Ismael. 115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>OECD</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Clapp</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Distant Agricultural Landscapes</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Sustainability Science</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>316</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-014-0278-0</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Clar</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Omann</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Scherhaufer</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <italic toggle="yes">Der &#x000f6;sterreichische Klimarat&#x02013;ein Beitrag zur Weiterentwicklung von Demokratie und Politik?</italic> Accessed January 15, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.momentum-kongress.org/system/files/congress_files/2022/clar-et-al.%3B-klimarat-als-beitrag-zur-transformation-von-demokratie_momentum-2022_final.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.momentum-kongress.org/system/files/congress_files/2022/clar-et-al.%3B-klimarat-als-beitrag-zur-transformation-von-demokratie_momentum-2022_final.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Climate Assembly UK</collab></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <italic toggle="yes">The Path to Net Zero. Climate Assembly UK Full Report</italic>. Accessed December 15, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.climateassembly.uk/report/read/final-report.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.climateassembly.uk/report/read/final-report.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Curato</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Hammond</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J. B.</given-names>
<surname>Min</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Power in Deliberative Democracy</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name><italic toggle="yes">Palgrave Macmillan</italic></publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dryzek</surname>, <given-names>J. S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>B&#x000e4;chtiger</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Chambers</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Cohen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J. N.</given-names>
<surname>Druckman</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Felicetti</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>James S.</given-names>
<surname>Fishkin</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Crisis of Democracy and the Science of Deliberation</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>
<volume>363</volume> (<issue>6432</issue>): <fpage>1144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1146</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaw2694</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30872504</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Elstub</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. D.</given-names>
<surname>Farrell</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Carrick</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Mockler</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of Climate Assembly UK</italic>. Accessed December 23, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://eprints.ncl.ac.uk/file_store/production/277537/A3EE1B3A-B9F3-4F79-A2BB-9BAE82090FE6.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://eprints.ncl.ac.uk/file_store/production/277537/A3EE1B3A-B9F3-4F79-A2BB-9BAE82090FE6.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>FAO</collab></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Global Report on Food Crises</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>FAO, IFAD, UNICEF, WFP and WHO</collab></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The State of Food Security and Nutrition in the World 2018. Building Climate Resilience for Food Security and Nutrition</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fiske</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Galasso</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Eichinger</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Stuart</given-names>
<surname>McLennan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Isabella</given-names>
<surname>Radhuber</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Bettina</given-names>
<surname>Zimmermann</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Barbara</given-names>
<surname>Prainsack</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Second Pandemic: Examining Structural Inequality through Reverberations of Covid-19 in Europe</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Social Science &#x00026; Medicine</italic></source>
<volume>292</volume>:<fpage>114634</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.114634</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34883310</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fraser</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Rethinking Recognition</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">The New Left</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Godfray</surname>, <given-names>H. C. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Aveyard</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Garnett</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J. W.</given-names>
<surname>Hall</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T. J.</given-names>
<surname>Key</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Lorimer</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ray T.</given-names>
<surname>Pierrehumbert</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Peter</given-names>
<surname>Scarborough</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Marco</given-names>
<surname>Springmann</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Susan A.</given-names>
<surname>Jebb</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Meat Consumption, Health, and the Environment</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>
<volume>361</volume> (<issue>6399</issue>): <fpage>eaam5324</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aam5324</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30026199</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Goodin</surname>, <given-names>R. E.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J. S.</given-names>
<surname>Dryzek</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Deliberative Impacts: The Macro-Political Uptake of Mini-Publics</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Politics &#x00026; society</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0032329206288152</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gordon</surname>, <given-names>Eric</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Jason</given-names>
<surname>Haas</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Becky</given-names>
<surname>Michelson</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Civic Creativity: Role-Playing Games in Deliberative Process</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Communication</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>3789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3807</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hammond</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Sustainability as a Cultural Transformation: The Role of Deliberative Democracy</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Environmental Politics</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644016.2019.1684731</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>HLPE</collab></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Food Security and Nutrition: Building A Global Narrative Towards 2030</italic></source>. A Report by the High Level Panel of Experts on Food Security and Nutrition of the Committee on World Food Security.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hollaus</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Recent Developments in Austria: A Citizens&#x02019; Council on Climate Change</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">CCLR - Carbon and Climate Law Review Band</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>79</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPCC</collab></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;Summary for Policymakers.&#x0201d; In <italic toggle="yes">Climate Change and Land: An IPCC Special Report on Climate Change, Desertification, Land Degradation, Sustainable Land Management, Food Security, and Greenhouse Gas Fluxes in Terrestrial Ecosystems</italic> [Edited by P. R. Shukla, J. Skea, E. Calvo Buendia, V. Masson-Delmotte, H.- O. P&#x000f6;rtner, D. C. Roberts, P. Zhai, R. Slade, S. Connors, R. van Diemen, M. Ferrat, E. Haughey, S. Luz, S. Neogi, M. Pathak, J. Petzold, J. Portugal Pereira, P. Vyas, E. Huntley, K. Kissick, M. Belkacemi, and J. Malley]. In press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPES-Food</collab></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The New Science of Sustainable Food Systems: Overcoming Barriers to Food System Reform</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Panel of Experts on Sustainable Food Systems</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author" specific-use="dash"><collab>IPES-Food</collab></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">COVID-19 and the Crisis in Food Systems: Symptoms, Causes, and Potential Solutions</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Panel of Experts on Sustainable Food Systems</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>KNOCA</collab></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <italic toggle="yes">Knowledge Network on Climate Assemblies</italic>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://knoca.eu/" ext-link-type="uri">https://knoca.eu/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kuruganti</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Pimbert</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Wakeford</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The People&#x02019;s Vision &#x02013; UK and Indian Reflections on Prajateerpu</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Participatory Learning and Action</italic></source>
<volume>58: 11-17</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lima</surname>, <given-names>F. J. G. D.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>E. A.</given-names>
<surname>Sobottka</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Young&#x02019;s Communicative Democracy as a Complement to Habermas&#x02019; Deliberative Democracy</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Educa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o e Pesquisa</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-4634202046224095</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meinzen-Dick</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Quisumbing</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Doss</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Theis</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Women&#x02019;s Land Rights as a Pathway to Poverty Reduction: Framework and Review of Available Evidence</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Agricultural systems</italic></source>
<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agsy.2017.10.009</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mellier</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Wilson</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;Getting Climate Citizens&#x02019; Assemblies Right.&#x0201d; [Online]. <ext-link xlink:href="https://carnegieeurope.eu/2020/11/05/getting-cli" ext-link-type="uri">https://carnegieeurope.eu/2020/11/05/getting-cli</ext-link> mate-citizens-assemblies-right-pub-83133.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mohai</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Pellow</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J. T.</given-names>
<surname>Roberts</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Environmental Justice</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Annual Review of Environment and Resources</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>430</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-environ-082508-094348</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moragues-Faus</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Marsden</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Political Ecology of Food: Carving &#x02018;Spaces of Possibility&#x02019; in a New Research Agenda</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Rural Studies</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jrurstud.2017.08.016</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nabatchi</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Gastil</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>G. M.</given-names>
<surname>Weiksner</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Leighninger</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Democracy in Motion: Evaluating the Practice and Impact of Deliberative Civic Engagement</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Oxford: Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Noren</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2022</year>. <italic toggle="yes">Verein des &#x000f6;sterreichischen Klimarat der B&#x000fc;rger:innen</italic>. Accessed February 9, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://klimarat-verein.at/" ext-link-type="uri">https://klimarat-verein.at/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Petts</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Brooks</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Expert Conceptualisations of the Role of Lay Knowledge in Environmental Decisionmaking: Challenges for Deliberative Democracy</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Environment and Planning A: Economy and Space</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1059</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1068/a37373</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pimbert</surname>, <given-names>Michel</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>John</given-names>
<surname>Thompson</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>William</given-names>
<surname>Vorley</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Global Restructuring, Agri-Food Systems and Livelihoods</italic></source>. London: International Institute for Environment and Development.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pulido</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Geographies of Race and Ethnicity II: Environmental Racism, Racial Capitalism and State-Sanctioned Violence</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Progress in human geography</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>533</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0309132516646495</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rabbi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Ben Hassen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>El Bilali</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Dele</given-names>
<surname>Raheem</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Ant&#x000f3;nio</given-names>
<surname>Raposo</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Food Security Challenges in Europe in the Context of the Prolonged Russian&#x02013;Ukrainian Conflict</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Sustainability</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>4745</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su15064745</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rittel</surname>, <given-names>H. W.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>M. M.</given-names>
<surname>Webber</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>1974</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Wicked Problems</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Man-Made Futures</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rulli</surname>, <given-names>M. C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Saviori</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>D&#x02019;Odorico</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2013</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Global Land and Water Grabbing</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</italic></source>
<volume>110</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>892</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>897</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1213163110</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schlosberg</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Defining Environmental Justice: Theories, Movements, and Nature</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Oxford: OUP Oxford</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schlosberg</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>B. L.</given-names>
<surname>Collins</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>From Environmental to Climate Justice: Climate Change and the Discourse of Environmental Justice</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Wires Climate Change</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcc.275</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Scoones</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Stirling</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Abrol</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Atela</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Charli-Joseph</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Eakin</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Yang</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transformations to Sustainability</italic></source>. STEPS Working Paper 104. <publisher-loc>Brighton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>STEPS Centre</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sen</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Poverty and Famines: An Essay on Entitlement and Deprivation</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Oxford: Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Deliberative Democracy and the Environment. Environmental Politics</italic></source>. <publisher-name>London: Routledge</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author" specific-use="dash"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2021</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can Democracy Safeguard the Future? Democratic Futures</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge: Polity Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>SORA</collab></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. Systemvertrauen auf Tiefpunkt. Accessed February 10, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.sora.at/nc/news-presse/news/news-einzelansicht/news/systemvertrauen-auf-tiefpunkt-1091.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.sora.at/nc/news-presse/news/news-einzelansicht/news/systemvertrauen-auf-tiefpunkt-1091.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stirling</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Opening Up&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;closing down&#x0201d; Power, Participation, and Pluralism in the Social Appraisal of Technology</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Technology, and Human Values</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stock</surname>, <given-names>P. V.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Szrot</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<part-title>Chapter 8. Justice</part-title>.&#x0201d; In <source><italic toggle="yes">Routledge Handbook of Sustainable and Regenerative Food Systems</italic></source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Duncan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. S.</given-names>
<surname>Carolan</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J. S.</given-names>
<surname>Wiskerke</surname></string-name></person-group>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge: 98-112</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Swiderska</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Argumedo</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Wekesa</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Ndalilo</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Song</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Rastogi</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Ryan</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Indigenous Peoples&#x02019; Food Systems and Biocultural Heritage: Addressing Indigenous Priorities Using Decolonial and Interdisciplinary Research Approaches</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Sustainability</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume> (<issue>18</issue>): <fpage>11311</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tribaldos</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Kortetm&#x000e4;ki</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Just Transition Principles and Criteria for Food Systems and Beyond</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Environmental Innovation and Societal Transitions</italic></source>
<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eist.2022.04.005</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UK Parliament</collab></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. Accessed February 10, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.parliament.uk/get-involved/committees/climate-assembly-uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.parliament.uk/get-involved/committees/climate-assembly-uk/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United Nations</collab></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <italic toggle="yes">The Sustainable Development Goals Report</italic> 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Verein Klimavolksbegehren</collab></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <italic toggle="yes">Forderungen</italic>. Accessed February 10, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://klimavolksbegehren.at/forderungen/" ext-link-type="uri">https://klimavolksbegehren.at/forderungen/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Verg&#x000e8;s</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2019</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Un f&#x000e9;minisme d&#x000e9;colonial</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>La Fabrique &#x000e9;ditions</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vermeulen</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>B. M.</given-names>
<surname>Campbell</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J. S. I.</given-names>
<surname>Ingram</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Climate Change and Food Systems</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">Annual Review of Environment and Resources</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-environ-020411-130608</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Willett</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Rockstr&#x000f6;m</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Loken</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Springmann</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Lang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Vermeulen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Tara</given-names>
<surname>Garnett</surname></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Food in the Anthropocene: the EAT&#x02013;Lancet Commission on Healthy Diets from Sustainable Food Systems</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">The Lancet</italic></source>
<volume>393</volume> (<issue>10170</issue>): <fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31788-4</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Willis</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Curato</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Smith</surname></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Deliberative Democracy and the Climate Crisis</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source><italic toggle="yes">WIREs Climate Change</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>e759</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcc.759</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>, <given-names>I. M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Justice and the Politics of Difference</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Princeton: Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author" specific-use="dash"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>, <given-names>I. M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>. &#x0201c;<part-title>Difference as a Resource for Democratic Communication</part-title>.&#x0201d; In <source><italic toggle="yes">Not for Sale, edited by Anatole Anton.</italic></source>, <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage>. <publisher-name>New York: Routledge</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>