<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-3-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats-oasis2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Equity</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Equity</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">heq</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health Equity</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2473-1242</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Mary Ann Liebert, Inc., publishers</publisher-name><publisher-loc>140 Huguenot Street, 3rd Floor New Rochelle, NY 10801 USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11512084</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1089/heq.2024.0087</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/heq.2024.0087</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Advancing Active Transportation Through Mobility Justice and Centering Community</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Baquero<italic toggle="yes">, et al.; Health Equity</italic> 2024, 00.0<break/><ext-link xlink:href="http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/10.1089/heq.2024.0087" ext-link-type="uri">http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/10.1089/heq.2024.0087</ext-link></alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">
<bold>TRANSPORTATION THROUGH MOBILITY JUSTICE</bold>
</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Baquero</surname><given-names>Barbara I.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="corr1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berney</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>Evalynn Fae T.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>Olivia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Getch</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Crystal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>Stephen J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>Dori</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saelens</surname><given-names>Brian E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff9 aff10 aff11" ref-type="aff">
<sup>9&#x02013;11</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoerster</surname><given-names>Katherine D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff12" ref-type="aff">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>Department of Health Systems and Population Health, School of Public Health, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>College of Built Environments, Urban Design &#x00026; Planning, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label><sup>3</sup></label>Beacon Hill Safe Streets, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label><sup>4</sup></label>Daniel J. Evans School of Public Policy and Governance, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label><sup>5</sup></label>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label><sup>6</sup></label>Harborview Injury Prevention and Research Center, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff7">
<label><sup>7</sup></label>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff8">
<label><sup>8</sup></label>Seattle Neighborhood Greenways, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff9">
<label><sup>9</sup></label>Seattle Children&#x02019;s Research Institute, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff10">
<label><sup>10</sup></label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff11">
<label><sup>11</sup></label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff><aff id="aff12">
<label><sup>12</sup></label>Mental Health Service, Seattle Division, VA Puget Sound Healthcare System, Seattle, Washington, USA.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1">
<label><sup>*</sup></label>Address correspondence to: Barbara I. Baquero, PhD, MPH, Department of Health Systems and Population Health, School of Public Health, University of Washington, 3980 15th NE Avenue Seattle, WA 98185, USA, <email>bbaquero@uw.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><history>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year><string-date>Accepted September 10, 2024</string-date></date>
</history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons License [CC-BY] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="heq.2024.0087.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="S019"><title>Objectives:</title><p>We established a community&#x02013;academic&#x02013;policy partnership to examine mobility challenges and opportunities by centering members of a diverse South Seattle neighborhood.</p></sec><sec id="S020"><title>Methods:</title><p>Three participatory research methods were used: (a) 30- to 60-min qualitative interviews with community leaders (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12) and members (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16); (b) a photovoice with youth (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10); and (c) mobility audits. We also engaged extensively in community dissemination and advocacy.</p></sec><sec id="S021"><title>Results:</title><p>Four major themes emerged: experiences with the built environment; conflicting views on promoting active transportation; experiences of danger, violence, and racism while moving in the community; and pride and connections within the community. Mobility audit findings reinforced many community member messages about needed infrastructure changes. Participants consistently expressed the need for neighborhood and city-wide structural improvements to support transportation and mobility, including enhanced public transportation; better lighting, crosswalks, sidewalks, pavement, and curb cuts; and maintenance of a neighborhood mixed-use trail. Participants shared the importance of community connection while walking, rolling, or using public transit and wanted to maintain this experience.</p></sec><sec id="S022"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Collectively, findings identified ways to increase nonmotorized transportation and public transit access, safety, and resilience, centering solutions on communities of color. We disseminated and amplified community recommendations to advance mobility justice in South Seattle via a community forum, developing a website, holding meetings with local leaders, and writing through print and electronic media. A key, novel strength of our project was the addition of community organizations, community&#x02013;academic partners, and government leaders from the project&#x02019;s inception. Local leaders should engage in mobility justice-focused community engagement to advance equity.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>mobility</kwd><kwd>health disparities</kwd><kwd>equity</kwd><kwd>active transportation</kwd><kwd>public transportation</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="00"/><ref-count count="44"/><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s001"><title>Introduction </title><p>Fair and just access to mobility&#x02014;being able to get from place to place for essential and leisure activities&#x02014;is a social determinant of health.<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> In the United States, driving personal vehicles has been the default mobility option. However, this is neither sufficient nor just, given driving cars is associated with inactivity and cardiovascular risk,<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> and motor vehicle accidents are highly prevalent and preventable leading causes of death.<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Cars also pollute and fuel climate change,<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> with dire predicted health consequences<sup><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> that disproportionately affect people of color, individuals with disabilities, and low-income individuals.<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8&#x02013;10</xref></sup> Given the importance of mobility for economic opportunity and the high expense of personal vehicle ownership, inadequate mobility access also affects economic well-being.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p><p>Active transportation&#x02014;walking, rolling (e.g., cycling, scooting, using a wheelchair) by itself or in combination with public transportation&#x02014;is more inclusive, economical, and healthy than personal vehicle reliance.<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12&#x02013;14</xref></sup> Yet active transportation is a practical option only in contexts where built and social environments include supportive features such as frequent high-quality transit, sidewalks, and adequate lighting. These features are not equitably distributed, with inequities growing. Specifically, gentrification-fueled displacement from denser and transit-rich areas hinders people of color and low-income individuals from being able to use active transportation.<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></p><p>Governments must ensure equitable access to transportation options that do not require a personal vehicle. Yet improving mobility via policy and infrastructure changes often do not include low-income communities of color and individuals with disabilities, thereby advantaging those with more resources, and possibly fueling gentrification.<sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Changing this approach to policy and action requires authentic and thorough community engagement to ensure planning centers community needs and vision.</p><p>A community-based participatory research (CBPR) approach,<sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> guided by a mobility justice framework, holds promise for addressing prior gaps. CBPR emphasizes active and equal collaborations among community members and researchers, yielding sustained and long-term community-driven actions and solutions.<sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Mobility justice centers Black, Indigenous, and people of color (BIPOC) communities and acknowledges historical, structural, and intersectional barriers and solutions to advance the freedom to move safely and without fear in public spaces and freedom from displacement.<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Combined CBPR-mobility justice frameworks have been underutilized in empirical studies<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and are also substantially underutilized by practitioners and governments as an approach for informing policies and practices. The present study sought to overcome these gaps in practice. <xref rid="tb1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> depicts how we combined the CBPR approach to capture the mobility justice concepts in the framework with examples of the outputs and outcomes of the study.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tb1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Examples Outputs from PATHSS Demonstrating the Combine CBPR Approach and Mobility Justice Framework</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">CBPR approach</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom">Mobility justice</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Example outputs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Recognize community as unit of identity</p></list-item><list-item><p>Build on resources of community</p></list-item><list-item><p>Promote co-learning among partners</p></list-item><list-item><p>Achieve research and action</p></list-item><list-item><p>Emphasis relevance of community-defined problem</p></list-item><list-item><p>Apply an iterative process to maintain partnership</p></list-item><list-item><p>Disseminate knowledge produced by all and to all partners</p></list-item><list-item><p>Require long-term commitment by all partners</p></list-item></list>
</td><td align="left" valign="top"><bold>Decolonize</bold><break/>Honor the voices of the often overlook in mobility conversations prioritizing their power</td><td align="left" valign="top"><bold>Decongest</bold><break/>Advocate for equitable access to mobility and well-being</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Community organizations reached out to researchers to develop and conduct the study</p></list-item><list-item><p>Photovoice with BIPOC youth</p></list-item><list-item><p>Interviews with BIPOC community members and community leaders</p></list-item><list-item><p>Mobility audits</p></list-item><list-item><p>Community Forum</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dissemination products</p></list-item><list-item><p>Website
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>o</label><p>Op-edits in local newspapers</p></list-item><list-item><label>o</label><p>Video and infographic</p></list-item><list-item><label>o</label><p>Meeting with local policymakers</p></list-item><list-item><label>o</label><p>Manuscripts</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"><bold>Dream</bold><break/>Identify solutions grounded in community knowledge and expertise</td><td align="left" valign="top"><bold>Decriminalize</bold><break/>Recognize that policing and mobility do not equal safety</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Dignity</bold><break/>Center safety of people navigating their community and their sense of belonging</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf1"><p>BIPOC, Black, Indigenous, and people of color; CBPR, community-based participatory research; PATHSS, Participatory Active Transportation for Health in South Seattle.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s002"><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted the Participatory Active Transportation for Health in South Seattle (PATHSS) study using mixed-methods guided by a CBPR-mobility justice framework. The primary research question of all PATHSS study components was intentionally broad: to understand barriers and facilitators for active transportation and mobility in South Seattle. Through this design, we set out to co-create generalizable knowledge and recommendations for researchers, practitioners, and government leaders working together to advance equitable access to mobility. However, per the University of Washington Institutional Review Board of Human Subjects regulations they deemed this study as &#x0201c;not involving human subjects research&#x0201d; per federal regulations because PATHSS <italic toggle="yes">primarily</italic> focused on generating recommendations for improving mobility in a specific Seattle community.</p><p>PATHSS was conducted in an ethnically, economically, and historically diverse<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> South Seattle neighborhood that experiences disproportionate health risks, including higher rates of high body mass index, inactivity, pollution exposure, and traffic-related injuries and fatalities.<sup><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22&#x02013;24</xref></sup> Concerned by disparities, the Seattle Department of Transportation (SDOT) announced in 2019 that it would spend up to $10 million to improve South Seattle&#x02019;s active transportation infrastructure, including an SDOT project to enhance an existing 3-mile bicycle and walking path.<sup><xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> In response to this government action, several community leaders from two local mobility-focused organizations (Beacon Hill Safe Streets [BHSS] and Seattle Neighborhood Greenways [SNG]) reached out to members of our academic team, wanting to conduct a community engagement project that would ensure community voice was centered as this SDOT project launched and to use this project to broadly identify barriers, facilitators, solutions, and other observations to active transportation and mobility. Through this budding partnership, we developed the PATHSS study, which sought to center and activate community input to inform community and government leaders about needed mobility changes. PATHSS established a leadership structure composed of a community&#x02013;academic&#x02013;policy partnership (CAPP) that mutually developed and established its priorities. In addition to interdisciplinary university faculty, the CAPP included representatives of two local mobility-focused organizations (BHSS and SNG) and government (SDOT) leaders.</p><p>This article describes (a) 30- to 60-min qualitative interviews with community leaders and members; (b) mobility audits; and (c) a photovoice study with 10 youth, the methods and findings of which are described in a separately published article.<sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> We also describe our process for disseminating findings to community members, leaders, and decision-makers.</p><sec id="s003"><title>Community Leader and Member Qualitative Interviews</title><p>Participants were recruited through snowball sampling, outreach to community-based organizations and their listservs, social media, and flyers in community spaces. Community leaders were eligible to participate if they work or volunteer with, represent, or advocate for South Seattle communities of color. Community members were eligible to participate if they were 13 years of age or older and reported that they live, work, go to school, use services, or travel through the focal South Seattle neighborhood. We used purposive and quota sampling for community member interviews to ensure a diverse sample for age, gender, race and ethnicity, and transportation modes used.</p><p>Semi-structured interview guides focused on identifying barriers and facilitators of mobility in the neighborhood and obtaining feedback on the planned multiuse trail project. Interviews were held by phone or secure video conferencing. Interviews were audio-recorded and transcribed verbatim. Community members were paid $30 for their time.</p><p>Analysis was carried out using a rapid template qualitative analysis,<sup><xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> a method ideally suited for pragmatically describing textual data.<sup><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> First, we developed an initial coding template summarizing broad &#x0201c;codes&#x0201d; based on the interview guides, mobility justice framework, findings from our parallel work with community member youth, and by reading a random sample of responses.<sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Codes were applied independently by two project staff. Templates were subsequently updated based on emerging topics. With discrepancies or lack of clarity, discussion occurred until an agreement was reached. Once we determined that our template sufficiently identified mobility barriers and facilitators across a host of domains, we established a &#x0201c;final&#x0201d; template used to complete and finalize coding.</p></sec><sec id="s004"><title>Mobility Audits</title><p>We conducted nonintrusive observations of the built and social environment using mobility audits at walksheds surrounding specific neighborhood intersections. Walksheds are defined as the area around a transit station&#x02014;or any central destination&#x02014;that is reachable on foot for the average person. A 5-min walkshed was used around three intersections chosen because community members routinely identified them as being important for mobility and/or needing improvement. We identified a 10-min walkshed around an intersection adjacent to a light rail station because a 10-min walk is generally considered the minimum catchment area for transit station walksheds.<sup><xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Audits included walking and rolling counts and use of mobility support devices by people at those intersections. Audits also evaluated sidewalk and crosswalk conditions and the presence of amenities (e.g., benches, bike lanes, street trees, transit shelter, water fountains) throughout identified walksheds.</p><p>Fifteen Urban Planning and Transportation Engineering students were trained to conduct the audits. Data were collected visually and recorded using an app the audit team created using Anvil, a Python-based app builder. Intersections were graded based on the worst curb-cut or crosswalk condition present. Students followed the standard that if one curb cut or crosswalk is inaccessible or in bad condition, then the whole intersection is not accessible. The analysis sorted the sidewalks and crosswalks by the categories: poor, fair, and good.</p></sec><sec id="s005"><title>Youth Photovoice</title><p>As previously published, we conducted a photovoice with 10 youth of color aged 13&#x02013;18 using the same inclusion criteria as the community member interviews.<sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Photovoice is a CBPR methodology that uses photography and storytelling in consecutive focus group sessions to collectively identify needs, set priorities, and advocate for change.<sup><xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> We conducted a thematic content analysis of verbatim transcripts. While these findings are published separately, the insights from the photovoice were merged with PATHSS interviews and audit findings.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s006"><title>Results</title><sec id="s007"><title>Participants Characteristics</title><p>Sixteen community members were interviewed (demographic characteristics: 9 Asian, 2 mixed race, 2 Black, 2 White, and 1 Hispanic; 3 genderqueer, 1 genderqueer/female, 10 females, and 2 males; ages 17&#x02013;80 [mean = 38]). One reported using a wheelchair. The 12 community leaders were executive directors, staff, and organizers of nonprofit, grassroot, and volunteer-led organizations and community centers; a pastor of a faith-based community; and a high school principal. In the previously published PATHSS photovoice study, 10 BIPOC youth (&#x0003c;18) participated.<sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s008"><title>Community Leaders and Member Qualitative Interviews</title><p>Four major themes emerged: experiences with the built environment; conflicting views on promoting active transportation; experiences of danger, violence, and racism while transporting and moving in the community; and pride and connections in their community. <xref rid="tb2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents themes and representative quotes. Participants consistently expressed the need for neighborhood and city-wide structural improvements to support transportation and mobility, including enhanced public transportation, lighting, crosswalks, sidewalks, pavement, curb cuts, and maintenance of the multiuse trails. Participants shared the importance of community connection while walking, rolling, or using public transit and wanted to maintain this experience. These desires competed with mixed feedback regarding bike lanes and hasty transportation infrastructure changes that fail to incorporate community input.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tb2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Qualitative Feedback from Community Members, Beacon Hill, Seattle, 2020&#x02013;2021</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Themes</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Mobility barriers, facilitators, solutions, and observations</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Representative participant quotes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Experiences with the built environment</td><td align="left" valign="top">Buses
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Free fare for everyone</p></list-item><list-item><p>Extended hours that support workers who do not work 9&#x02013;5 jobs</p></list-item><list-item><p>Covered bus shelters with benches and timetables</p></list-item><list-item><p>More routes, especially east-west</p></list-item><list-item><p>Increase on-demand ride-share services that Metro provides to link people to transit</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;...how can we [expand transportation], so that [it&#x02019;s] actually benefiting the existing community&#x02026; not pushing them out?&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Visibility
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Clearly marked crosswalks and more flashing beacon crosswalks</p></list-item><list-item><p>More streetlights</p></list-item><list-item><p>Street design to slow cars</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;If it&#x02019;s really dark&#x02026; you don&#x02019;t feel safe there because you can&#x02019;t really see where you&#x02019;re going or where you&#x02019;re at or who&#x02019;s around you&#x02026;&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Streets and sidewalks
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Curb cuts everywhere</p></list-item><list-item><p>Smooth sidewalks and pavement</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sidewalks clear of obstruction</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;The uneven pavement... we can&#x02019;t afford [for] our elders to fall. That&#x02019;s a hip&#x02026; or a knee problem, so that&#x02019;s extremely dangerous.&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Beacon Ave. Trail
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Consistent maintenance and beautification</p></list-item><list-item><p>More trees for shade, esthetics, and barriers from the street</p></list-item><list-item><p>Smoother pavement for safety</p></list-item><list-item><p>Improved seating options</p></list-item><list-item><p>Planned bike project should ensure pedestrians remain priority</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;I would imagine that if it was nicely paved, if it were safer, if there were lights, if there were benches that were not only six feet apart, but more frequent... it would be a lot more used and a lot more accessible.&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Conflicting views on promoting active transportation</td><td align="left" valign="top">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Some participants wanted bike lanes on Beacon Ave. Trail and throughout Beacon Hill, while some did not want bike lanes</p></list-item><list-item><p>Some participants wanted to keep the parking on and around Beacon Ave. Trail, while some wanted to remove the parking</p></list-item><list-item><p>In comparison to adults, youth find phone applications that provide real-time arrival information for transit to be more accurate than not and do not mind if the app is incorrect</p></list-item></list>
</td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;...I feel like there&#x02019;s not that many people that ride bikes on Beacon Ave. It&#x02019;s a good enough amount that it&#x02019;s manageable right now, but I don&#x02019;t know if people don&#x02019;t ride their bikes because it&#x02019;s not accommodating on Beacon Hill or they just don&#x02019;t ride their bikes there.&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Experiencing danger, violence, and racism</td><td align="left" valign="top">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Feelings of vigilance, powerlessness, and anticipation of harm from factors such as poor streetlights and unsafe drivers</p></list-item><list-item><p>Feeling vulnerable in transit with people experiencing mental health issues (e.g., visible intoxication). Would like to be able to call for mental health care and discourage police involvement</p></list-item><list-item><p>Experiencing racism when navigating public spaces with family who speak languages other than English</p></list-item></list>
</td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;He wants to feel safe while going around the community &#x02018;cause you wouldn&#x02019;t want to go around somewhere if you don&#x02019;t feel safe.&#x0201d;<break/><italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;The moment Black women leave their homes we experience anxiety because we measure our safety by the capriciousness of white people and the police. I feel like when I take the train, I&#x02019;m singled out to prove fare, and the presence of transit security and fare enforcement can make it feel threatening. These kinds of interactions can be unhealthy, things like raising your blood pressure for more than just that moment and potentially for hours.&#x0201d;</italic><sup><xref rid="tf2" ref-type="table-fn"><italic toggle="yes"><sup>a</sup></italic></xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Pride and connections in their community</td><td align="left" valign="top">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Views of sunsets and the city</p></list-item><list-item><p>Community spaces: parks, soccer field, and community center</p></list-item><list-item><p>Appreciation for local restaurants and other businesses, particularly those owned by people of color, given the impact of gentrification on the neighborhood</p></list-item><list-item><p>Strong sense of community: people in the neighborhood are friendly to one another, support and look out for one another. Organizations for social justice are present in the community</p></list-item><list-item><p>Importance of fighting displacement through affordable housing and programs such as rent relief</p></list-item></list>
</td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x0201c;...we sometimes run into each other and say hi&#x02026; because we recognize each other from our daily walks. It&#x02019;s a very welcoming community.&#x0201d;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf2"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>A community forum breakout room participant contributed this quote, included here because it so powerfully conveys this theme that was raised frequently across interviews and the photovoice project.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s009"><title>Mobility Audits</title><p>Mobility audit findings confirmed themes regarding infrastructure that emerged from community members. Many existing curb cuts were not designed for safe, easy wheelchair use (e.g., too narrow, obstructions). As shown in <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, crosswalk and curb-cut quality varied throughout the neighborhood but was rarely good; 4% were good (conditions 7&#x02013;9), 21% were fair (conditions 4&#x02013;6), and 75% were poor (conditions 0&#x02013;3).</p><fig position="float" id="f1" fig-type="figure"><label>FIG. 1.</label><caption><p>Findings from the mobility audits of key neighborhood intersections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="heq.2024.0087_figure1" position="float"/></fig><p>Curb cuts east and west of the light rail station were generally in poor shape. Many were missing, and those that existed were too narrow for wheelchairs, did not have an accompanying curb cut on the other side of the street, and had a steep grade or no flat landing surface. Curb cuts south of the station were similar, rarely having curb cuts on all four corners of an intersection, even at busy intersections with marked crosswalks.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s010"><title>Dissemination of Findings, Outreach, and Advocacy</title><p>We engaged in several activities to share key findings and advocate for corresponding infrastructure and policy changes, with our focus on dissemination led by community member encouragement: (1) a virtual community forum codeveloped with youth photovoice participants; (2) a website of the project activities and products, for example, a youth-produced short video; (3) meetings with SDOT, local, and regional transportation officials; and (4) print and online media articles.</p><p><xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> depicts the timeline of events and products and a sampling of products we cocreated. Early in the project, research and BHSS partners drew on PATHSS findings to cocraft a letter to city leaders educating SDOT&#x02019;s staff on the vision of the community on the proposed multiuse trail. We held a virtual community forum, coordinated by PATHSS team members and youth photovoice participants, where PATHSS findings were shared, and a youth panel discussed their experiences moving through the community. Over 70 people attended the forum, including community members, allies, transportation and city officials, and media representatives. Forum panelists and participants emphasized the important role identity plays in how they move through public spaces, the racism that drives mobility decision-making and impacts experience, and the deep costs of mobility barriers to well-being.</p><fig position="float" id="f2" fig-type="figure"><label>FIG. 2.</label><caption><p>Timeline of project, events, and dissemination products.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="heq.2024.0087_figure2" position="float"/></fig><p>We developed and disseminated a website<sup><xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> where community members can learn how to advocate for change based on PATHSS findings. From January 7, 2021, to October 3, 2023, 833 people accessed the website, with most (98%) from the United States. Among U.S. visitors, users hailed from 142 cities, with the highest number of U.S. visitors from Seattle, WA (37%), and the second highest from Cheyenne, WY (20%).</p><p>We developed an infographic policy brief for community members and leaders summarizing community recommendations for improved neighborhood mobility, which was broadly distributed via email to community members, leaders, and policymakers. We partnered with youth and community partners to share PATHSS findings via op-eds, letters to the editor, presentations to transportation agencies, and interviews, in local, regional, and state-wide outlets. We included all media coverage of PATHSS findings and advocacy on the website. For example, the two lead investigators cowrote an op-ed with their key community partner, calling for policy changes to reduce systemic racism-based barriers to exercise and mobility.<sup><xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> In addition, youth photovoice participants wrote an op-ed advocating for free public transit and enhanced South Seattle mobility under the mentorship of senior PATHSS researchers. See <xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> for a sample of these dissemination tools.</p><fig position="float" id="f3" fig-type="figure"><label>FIG. 3.</label><caption><p>Simple tools for disseminating PATHSS key findings to advance mobility justice. PATHSS, Participatory Active Transportation for Health in South Seattle.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="heq.2024.0087_figure3" position="float"/></fig><p>Our community partner SNG hosted a web platform tool for community members to advocate to city leaders for key policy and infrastructure changes based on PATHSS findings. Thirty people advocated through the web tool alone. The highest use of the PATHSS website (275 users) was during this promotion campaign. Following this outreach, King County Metro and Sound Transit, the two regional public transportation agencies, met with us to discuss their policies (e.g., free transit, fare enforcement) and youth engagement. We also met with SDOT&#x02019;s Vision Zero and Safe Routes to Schools leaders. PATHSS community partners (BHSS and SBG), youth, and representatives participated in these meetings and were compensated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s011"><title>Discussion</title><p>PATHSS was a CBPR study seeking to identify community mobility challenges and opportunities for change. The connection between place, transportation, and health has been studied empirically for years. However, that evidence has limitations as it often centers on individuals and how they access those places while neglecting those place&#x02019;s social, economic, and historical contexts.<sup><xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Moreover, prior research has successfully documented transportation challenges but is too rarely paired with immediate community-driven advocacy. Conducting this project with a mobility justice lens helped focus and articulate the social action call central to CBPR, while more holistically examining people&#x02019;s transportation experiences (e.g., the stress caused by experiencing harassment). Last, including government leaders in our project from its inception&#x02014;even before we obtained funding&#x02014;made PATHSS a unique model for ensuring community-driven policy and practice.</p><p>Infrastructure changes recommended by community members and leaders&#x02014;and confirmed by the mobility audits&#x02014;are evidence-based strategies for creating safe and walkable communities.<sup><xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Improving safe and fair public transit access is critical for advancing public health and equity<sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> in the context of dramatically reduced ridership and funding during the COVID-19 pandemic.<sup><xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> Participants advocated specifically for free transit for youth or all people, implemented in Kansas City, MO, in 2019,<sup><xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> and for students and low-income individuals in parts of Los Angeles, CA, in 2021.<sup><xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> Funding for free fare systems can come from various sources, including local and federal funding and employer subsidies.<sup><xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38&#x02013;40</xref></sup> In addition, fare collection and enforcement are costly, so eliminating those can help offset the loss of fare revenue.<sup><xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> King County (of which Seattle is a part) made all transit free for youth 18 and younger beginning September 2022.<sup><xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Even with the free youth transit victory, PATHSS youth and community member participants requested additional changes that would help increase transit access, including expanded hours, more comfortable and useful shelters, and increased reliability. Transit agencies should implement these changes to further improve mobility.</p><p>As mobility justice indicates, fair, free, and safe movement in communities goes beyond physical transportation. Community members shared concerns that infrastructure improvements drive gentrification and displacement. They shared their concerns about the well-being of unhoused individuals and mentioned the importance of affordable housing. Many expressed concerns about addressing safety with police, given Black and American Indian/Alaska Native people are significantly more likely than White people to be killed by police.<sup><xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> Government leaders must work to reduce displacement, improve access to affordable housing, tackle harms imposed by policing and criminal (in)justice systems, and dismantle the ways in which systemic racism undergirds harmful policies and practices.</p></sec><sec id="s012"><title>Recommendations</title><p>Based on the PATHSS process and findings, our research team has identified several recommendations for researchers, government staff and officials, and practitioners working together to advance health equity through mobility justice:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Researchers, government staff, and officials: maintain proactive, ongoing communication with community partners and experts, working around partners&#x02019; schedules.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Prioritize the voices of community partners, persons with disabilities, BIPOC, youth, and elders, who are most impacted by policy decisions, yet are often excluded from decision-making.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Regularly share and synthesize feedback with community partners and decision-makers, guided by timelines relevant to leaders and the community.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Adapt to changing community and partner needs.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Link community needs and resources with the appropriate governmental entity (e.g., city council and mayor, transportation agencies, parks) and audiences such as business leaders with a shared interest in community development&#x02014;and potential influence.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Adopt an antioppression research framework, such as mobility justice or public health critical race praxis, to center the experiences of those most affected, examine contextual injustices, and address root causes of inequities.<sup><xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></p></list-item><list-item><p>Engage in community-partnered <italic toggle="yes">action</italic> rather than simply observing and describing problems. We include here a quote from a community leader that we heard early on and that influenced our approach with PATHSS going forward: &#x0201c;Am I looking for what I don&#x02019;t know? Am I shifting some focus and power away from the most privileged in my research? &#x02026;an opportunity to do better and do more, instead of just an examination of the ways to get around and how these efforts are failing.&#x0201d;</p></list-item></list></p><sec id="s013"><title>Limitations and Strengths</title><p>Several limitations should be considered when interpreting our findings. PATHSS took place at the start of the COVID-19 pandemic; how findings will translate to times less impacted by COVID-19 is unknown. As this study&#x02019;s methods and findings are intentionally focused on a specific South Seattle neighborhood, findings may not generalize to other communities. However, we believe that it is likely the barriers and facilitators identified are shared by other diverse urban communities and should, therefore, be a focus of inquiry and action in other similar communities. Furthermore, the broad lessons learned about engaging community members to advance local community mobility apply.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s014"><title>Health Equity Implications</title><p>PATHSS effectively collaborated with community and policy partners to identify and address South Seattle mobility challenges and opportunities. The CBPR-mobility justice approach allowed PATHSS to interpret findings and act from an antioppression stance. This allowed us to go beyond simply describing community members&#x02019; experiences, to directly and collaboratively address the current unjust and unfair systems that marginalize and oppress BIPOC community members. Our study serves as a road map for researchers, policymakers, implementers, and community members, shifting from applying an intra- and interpersonal approach to health promotion to one that is grounded on the dignity, freedom, safety, and well-being of communities.</p><p>Future work must continue to promote access to mobility, improve healthy behaviors and access to economic resources, reduce climate impacts, and strengthen community capacity for health and environmental advocacy. Such work will benefit from using a CBPR-mobility justice approach.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank PATHSS participants, community partners, and the Beacon Hill community. The authors are grateful to the University of Washington (UW) students who performed the mobility audits: Michael Berlinger, Kip Diaz, Claire Farrington, Elizabeth Hert, Barnabas Hong, Dawn Jansen, Stephanie Kennedy, Art Lansing, Nicole Larson, Adela Mu, Pedro Popoca, Flora Tempel, Thomas Valdriz, Rachel Vierstra, and Zian Zheng. The authors thank Mary Schooler and Norma Garfias Avila for their administrative support with this article. The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></ack><sec id="s016"><title>Authors&#x02019; Contributions</title><p>B.B.: Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, funding acquisition, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, visualization, writing&#x02014;original draft, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. R.B.: Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, funding acquisition, investigation, methodology, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. E.F.T.R.: Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, project administration, resources, visualization; writing&#x02014;original draft, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. O.F.: Funding acquisition, methodology, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. R.G.: Funding acquisition, methodology, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. C.H.: Funding acquisition, methodology, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. S.J.M.: Funding acquisition, methodology, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. D.R.: Funding acquisition, methodology, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. K.S.: Funding acquisition, investigation, methodology, resources, visualization, writing&#x02014;original draft, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. B.E.S.: Funding acquisition, methodology, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing. K.D.H.: Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, funding acquisition, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, visualization, writing&#x02014;original draft, and writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing.</p></sec><sec id="s017"><title>Author Disclosure Statement</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></sec><sec id="s018"><title>Funding Information</title><p>This work was supported by the <funding-source>University of Washington Population Health Initiative</funding-source> Pilot Grant.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="parsed"><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>Centers of Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <article-title>Disability and Obesity</article-title>. <year>2019</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/disabilityandhealth/obesity.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/disabilityandhealth/obesity.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gebel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phongsavan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Driving: A road to unhealthy lifestyles and poor health outcomes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e94602</fpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24911017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacobson</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>What is driving obesity? A review on the connections between obesity and motorized transportation</article-title>. <source>Curr Obes Rep</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13679-017-0238-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28243840</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Danaei</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mozaffarian</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The preventable causes of death in the United States: Comparative risk assessment of dietary, lifestyle, and metabolic risk factors</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1000058</fpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19399161</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>Centers of Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <article-title>Motor Vehicle Injuries</article-title>. <year>2017</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/winnablebattles/report/motor.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/winnablebattles/report/motor.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>United Nations</collab>. <article-title>The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</article-title>. <year>n.d</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ipcc.ch/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Ten Threats to Global Health in 2019</article-title>. <year>n.d</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/spotlight/ten-threats-to-global-health-in-2019" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/spotlight/ten-threats-to-global-health-in-2019</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</collab>. <article-title>Motor vehicle traffic-related pedestrian deaths - United States, 2001-2010</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23594683</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tessum</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Apte</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodkind</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Inequity in consumption of goods and services adds to racial-ethnic disparities in air pollution exposure</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>6001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6006</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1818859116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30858319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bleich</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cradock</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Projected U.S. State-level prevalence of adult obesity and severe obesity</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>381</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>2440</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2450</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsa1909301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31851800</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>AAA</collab>. <article-title>AAA Reveals True Cost of Vehicle Ownership</article-title>. <source>AAA NewsRoom</source>
<year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>She</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacobson</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Analyzing the impact of public transit usage on obesity</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2017.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28322880</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Flint</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cummins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Active commuting and obesity in mid-life: Cross-sectional, observational evidence from UK Biobank</article-title>. <source>Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-8587(16)00053-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26995106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heaps</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abramsohn</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skillen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Public Transportation In The US: A Driver Of Health And Equity</article-title>. <source>Policy Anal Brief H Ser</source>
<year>2021</year>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hpb20210630.810356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lugo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doerner</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Untokening Mobility: Beyond Pavement, Paint and Place</article-title>. <year>2018</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.untokening.org/updates/2018/1/27/untokening-mobility-beyond-pavement-paint-and-place" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.untokening.org/updates/2018/1/27/untokening-mobility-beyond-pavement-paint-and-place</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hosking</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodward</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Systematic literature review of built environment effects on physical activity and active transport - an update and new findings on health equity</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>158</fpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12966-017-0613-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29145884</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wallerstein</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernstein</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Introduction to community empowerment, participatory education, and health</article-title>. <source>Health Educ Q</source>
<year>1994</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/109019819402100202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8021144</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Israel</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coombe</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheezum</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Community-based participatory research: A capacity-building approach for policy advocacy aimed at eliminating health disparities</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2094</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2102</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2009.170506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20864728</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sheller</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Theorising mobility justice</article-title>. <source>Tempo Soc</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Juarez</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The movement towards mobility justice in Los Angeles: Building a framework grounded in popular education &#x00026; community knowledge</article-title>. <source>UCLA</source>
<year>2020</year>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17610/T6RW2M</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>United States Census Bureau</collab>. <article-title>Quick Facts: Seattle City, Washington</article-title>. <year>2019</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/dashboard/seattlecitywashington/PST045219" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/dashboard/seattlecitywashington/PST045219</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gore</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>City of Seattle Health and Equity Assessment</article-title>. <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Austin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gould</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Mobile ObserVations of Ultrafine Particles: The MOV-UP Study Report</source>. <publisher-name>University of Washington</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Anonymous</collab>. <source>2019 Traffic Report</source>. <publisher-name>Seattle Department of Transportation</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Anonymous</collab>. <article-title>UW PATHSS</article-title>. <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Romano</surname>
<given-names>EFT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baquero</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hicks</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>No one should feel like they&#x02019;re unsafe</article-title>. <source>Fam Community Health</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/FCH.0000000000000344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35943214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Symon</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cassel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Qualitative Methods and Analysis in Organizational Research</source>. <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>; <year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCluskey</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turley</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The utility of template analysis in qualitative psychology research</article-title>. <source>Qual Res Psychol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14780887.2014.955224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27499705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morrall</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Walking distances to and from light-rail transit stations</article-title>. <source>Transportation Research Record</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>1538</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0361198196153800103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burris</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Photovoice: Concept, methodology, and use for participatory needs assessment</article-title>. <source>Health Educ Behav</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>387</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/109019819702400309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9158980</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bailey</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krieger</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ag&#x000e9;nor</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Structural racism and health inequities in the USA: Evidence and interventions</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>389</volume>(<issue>10077</issue>):<fpage>1453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1463</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30569-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28402827</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>National Association of City Transportation Officials</collab>. <source>Urban Street Design Guide</source>. <publisher-name>NACTO</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>National Association of City Transportation Officials</collab>. <source>Urban Street Design Guide: Sidewalks</source>. <publisher-name>NACTO</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheff</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The impacts of COVID-19 pandemic on public transit demand in the United States</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e0242476</fpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0242476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33206721</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Aguilar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>B&#x000e9;nichou</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blanchard</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Showing Its Worth During Pandemic, Momentum Builds for Free or Reduced-Fare Transit</article-title>. <source>Wash Post</source>
<year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>Kansas City Area Transportation Authority</collab>. <article-title>ZeroFareKC</article-title>. <year>2020</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://zerofarekc.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://zerofarekc.com/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vega</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Metro votes to create financial plan for offering free rides to students, low-income riders</article-title>. <source>Los Angel Times</source>
<year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kite</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>&#x02032;Only a Beginning&#x02019;: Mayor Quinton Lucas Promises Equity in First State of the City</source>. <publisher-name>Kans City Star</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>Kansas City Area Transportation Authority</collab>. <article-title>Coronavirus Relief Funds for Transit</article-title>. <year>n.d</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.kcata.org/about_kcata/entries/covid-allocations" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.kcata.org/about_kcata/entries/covid-allocations</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>ORCA for All</article-title>. <year>2019</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://seattletransitblog.com/2019/09/25/orca-for-all/" ext-link-type="uri">https://seattletransitblog.com/2019/09/25/orca-for-all/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Volinski</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <part-title>Transit cooperative research program</part-title>. In: <source>Implementation and Outcomes of Fare-Free Transit Systems</source>. <publisher-name>Transportation Research Board</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fesler</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Zero youth fares approved for king county metro and sound transit just in time for school</article-title>. <year>2022</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.theurbanist.org/2022/07/28/zero-youth-fares-approved-for-king-county-metro-and-sound-transit-just-in-time-for-school/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.theurbanist.org/2022/07/28/zero-youth-fares-approved-for-king-county-metro-and-sound-transit-just-in-time-for-school/</ext-link> [Last accessed: <date-in-citation><month>May</month>
<day>3</day>, <year>2023</year></date-in-citation>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esposito</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of being killed by police use of force in the United States by age, race-ethnicity, and sex</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>16793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16798</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1821204116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31383756</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ford</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Airhihenbuwa</surname>
<given-names>CO</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The public health critical race methodology: Praxis for antiracism research</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1398</lpage>; doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2010.07.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20822840</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec><boxed-text position="float"><p><bold>Cite this article as:</bold> Baquero BI, Berney R, Romano EF T, Hicks O, Getch R, Hall C, Mooney SJ, Rosenberg D, Shannon K L, Saelens BE, and Hoerster KD (2024) Advancing active transportation through mobility justice and centering community, <italic toggle="yes">Health Equity</italic> 8:1, 720-730, DOI: 10.1089/heq.2024.0087.</p></boxed-text></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations Used</title><def-list><def-item><term id="G1">BHSS</term><def><p>Beacon Hill Safe Streets</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">BIPOC</term><def><p>Black, Indigenous, and People of Color</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">CAPP</term><def><p>Community-Academic-Policy Partnership</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">CBPR</term><def><p>Community-Based Participatory Research</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">PATHSS</term><def><p>Participatory Active Transportation for Health in South Seattle</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">SDOH</term><def><p>Social Determinants of Health</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">SDOT</term><def><p>Seattle Department of Transportation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">SNG</term><def><p>Seattle Neighborhood Greenways</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>