<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="discussion" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_LANAM100801 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Reg Health Am</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Reg Health Am</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Lancet Regional Health - Americas</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2667-193X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11177188</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2667-193X(24)00128-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2024.100801</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100801</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Climate change, health, and human rights: calling on states to address the health risks of climate change, through the Inter-American Court of Human Rights</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Benesch</surname><given-names>Tara</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Sergeeva</surname><given-names>Milena</given-names></name><email>milena.sergeeva@climateandhealthalliance.org</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Wainstock</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Jeni</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>University of Colorado Climate and Health Fellow, United States</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Latin American and Caribbean Climate &#x00026; Health Network, of the Global Climate &#x00026; Health Alliance, Chile</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Global Climate and Health Alliance, United States</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>milena.sergeeva@climateandhealthalliance.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><elocation-id>100801</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Climate change is projected to cause the deaths of 1 billion people by the end of this century if average warming reaches or exceeds 2&#x000b0;C.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The health impacts of climate change, including cardiopulmonary disease, vector-borne illness, mental illness, and migration events, pose severe threats to Latin America and the Caribbean (LAC), a region especially prone to climate disasters.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Furthermore, the consequences of climate change aggravate existing inequalities, disproportionately affecting indigenous communities, children, the elderly, those living in poverty, and those living in what have been designated &#x0201c;sacrifice zones&#x0201d;.</p><p id="p0015">Current national policies put the world on a trajectory to reach nearly 3&#x000b0;C of warming,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> yet countries in the LAC region have not responded to the associated threats, exacerbated by government instability, dependence on wealthier nations, and high poverty rates.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> As the adverse effects of global warming challenge the fundamental rights to life, health, food, shelter, and safety, recent years have seen increasing efforts to address climate change through the courts. Between 2017 and 2022, there were over 2000 cases including lawsuits against governments, corporations, and individuals, and calls for advisory opinions from national, regional, and international courts.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> In 2022 the United Nations Human Rights Council recognized the &#x0201c;right to a clean, healthy and sustainable environment&#x0201d; as a fundamental human right. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change has recognized human rights-based climate litigation as an important approach to driving more ambitious climate action.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> We see a valuable role for health experts, and evidence of the health impacts of climate change, in litigation strategies to drive climate action.</p><p id="p0020">In January 2023, Chile and Colombia requested an Advisory Opinion from the Inter-American Court of Human Rights (IACtHR) on &#x0201c;the climate emergency and human rights&#x0201d;, asking the court to clarify the responsibilities of the State concerning the human impacts of climate change, in alignment with International Human Rights Law.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> In response to this request, the Global Climate and Health Alliance, a coalition of health organizations from around the world, submitted a &#x0201c;friend of the court&#x0201d; brief (<italic>Amicus Curiae</italic>)<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> to inform the court&#x02019;s decision-making. Our Amicus brief encapsulates the far-reaching health repercussions of climate change, as described above. And it delineates the legal duties and principles pertinent to tackling climate change and health issues, suggesting crucial steps to protect and deliver both climate and health benefits.</p><p id="p0025">To address the impacts of climate change ethically, equitably, and effectively, we recommend guiding principles that include equity, focusing on inclusive strategies for vulnerable populations; justice, demanding accountability for historical emissions and a larger role for high-income nations in support and emission reduction; the precautionary principle, advocating for early protective action despite scientific uncertainties; children's rights, emphasizing children&#x02019;s well-being in climate policies; public participation and the right to justice in climate-related decisions; protection of vulnerable communities, including by integrating their knowledge into policies; and shared but differentiated obligations, with developed countries leading in emission reductions and supporting vulnerable nations to achieve climate mitigation and adaptation goals.</p><p id="p0030">To effectively limit global warming to 1.5&#x000b0;C and promote a healthy, equitable future, we suggest key actions: (<italic>i</italic>) prioritize health and environmental considerations, based on scientific evidence, in project evaluations and legislation; (<italic>ii</italic>) develop policies focused on the wellbeing of vulnerable communities, including those in low-income, rural, and tribal areas; and (<italic>iii</italic>)&#x000a0;transition from fossil fuels to clean renewable energy, with an emphasis on community benefits, stringent air quality standards, and legal protections for environmental advocates. We underscore the necessity of universal access to sustainable healthcare, the importance of sustainable land management, urban design that protects pedestrians and cyclists, and the need for international cooperation on climate strategies and disaster response plans.</p><p id="p0035">The path to mitigating climate impacts on health in the LAC region and beyond requires a concerted effort that transcends national borders, emphasizing global solidarity, both shared and national responsibility, and an unwavering commitment to justice and equity. Incorporating human rights into climate action emphasizes the imperative to protect the most vulnerable populations, ensuring their right to health, safety, and a sustainable environment. A common understanding of the convergence of climate change, human rights and health is needed to accelerate ambitious action nationally and internationally towards a just and healthy tomorrow. Through its advisory opinion, the IACtHR has the potential to establish such a common understanding for the LAC region and beyond, and to undergird future human rights-based climate litigation that will help drive the changes needed to deliver health, equity, and a sustainable environment for all in the region.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Contributors</title><p id="p0040">JM conceptualised the comment; TB provided the original draft and substantial edits; MS, DW, and JM provided substantial inputs in writing, review and editing. All authors revised and approved the final version for submission.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of interests</title><p id="p0045">MS and JM are affiliated with the Global Climate and Health Alliance. All authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parncutt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying global greenhouse gas emissions in human deaths to guide energy policy</article-title><source>Energies</source><volume>16</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>6074</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartinger</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmeiro-Silva</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Llerena-Cayo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The 2023 Latin America report of the <italic>Lancet</italic> Countdown on health and climate change: the imperative for health-centred climate-resilient development</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Am</source><volume>33</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100746</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Environment UN</collab></person-group><part-title>UNEP - UN environment programme</part-title><source>Emissions gap report 2023</source><year>2023</year><comment>[cited 2024 Apr 9]. Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unep.org/resources/emissions-gap-report-2023" id="intref0010">http://www.unep.org/resources/emissions-gap-report-2023</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Posse</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergeeva</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate change and&#x000a0;public health in South America: a scoping review of governance and public engagement research</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Am</source><volume>26</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100603</object-id><comment>[cited 2024 Apr 9]. Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanam/article/PIIS2667-193X(23)00177-1/fulltext" id="intref0015">https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanam/article/PIIS2667-193X(23)00177-1/fulltext</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Environment UNE</collab></person-group><part-title>Global climate litigation report: 2023 status review [internet]</part-title><year>2023</year><publisher-name>United Nations Environment Programme</publisher-name><comment>[cited 2024 Apr 9]. Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wedocs.unep.org/xmlui/handle/20.500.11822/43008" id="intref0020">https://wedocs.unep.org/xmlui/handle/20.500.11822/43008</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref6"><part-title>Climate change 2022: impacts, adaptation and vulnerability</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skea</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Contribution of working group III to the sixth assessment report of the intergovernmental Panel on climate change</source><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref7"><article-title>Request for an advisory opinion on the climate emergency and human rights submitted to the inter-American court of human rights by the republic of Colombia and the republic of Chile</article-title><comment>[cited 2024 Apr 9]. Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.corteidh.or.cr/docs/opiniones/soc_1_2023_en.pdf" id="intref0025">https://www.corteidh.or.cr/docs/opiniones/soc_1_2023_en.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Amicus Curiae Brief [Internet]</collab></person-group><article-title>The global climate and health alliance</article-title><comment>[cited 2024 Apr 9]. Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://climateandhealthalliance.org/amicus-curiae-brief/" id="intref0030">https://climateandhealthalliance.org/amicus-curiae-brief/</ext-link></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>