<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11516450</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckae144.639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckae144.639</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Parallel Programme</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>10.G. Practice session: Innovation technology to promote healthy lifestyles: teachings from multi-national EU funded projects</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>10.G. Practice session: Innovation technology to promote healthy lifestyles: teachings from multi-national EU funded projects</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>Organised by: EUPHA-FN, -HP, -DH</collab></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><collab>Chair persons: Eric Breton (France), Anna Odone (EUPHA-DH -IDC)</collab><xref rid="ckae144.639-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--giuseppe.grosso@unict.it--></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckae144.639-cor1">Contact: <email>giuseppe.grosso@unict.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-10-28"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><issue-title>17th European Public Health Conference 2024 Sailing the Waves of European Public Health: Exploring a Sea of Innovation Lisbon, Portugal 12&#x02013;15 November 2024</issue-title><elocation-id>ckae144.639</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ckae144.639.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1818"><title>&#x02002;</title><p>The global burden of disease attributable to lifestyle risk factors is constantly escalating on a worldwide scale. Inadequate diet and sedentary behaviors stand out as particularly impactful contributors to chronic non-communicable diseases, resulting in millions of deaths annually and projecting stable, alarming trends for the foreseeable future. These statistics raise significant concerns among public health experts, particularly regarding the pervasive influence of unhealthy lifestyles on younger generations. This demographic cohort&#x02019;s susceptibility poses a substantial threat to the future trajectory of non-communicable diseases and places immense strain on healthcare systems and global health outcomes. In light of these challenges, the imperative for public health initiatives and interventions aimed at promoting healthy lifestyles becomes glaringly apparent. Addressing the root causes of unhealthy behaviors through targeted interventions is essential to reverse the projected trends and mitigate future health risks. Public health authorities shoulder the responsibility of prioritizing such endeavors, as they play a pivotal role in shaping environments conducive to healthy living for present and future generations alike. Embracing innovative methodologies, leveraging technological advancements, and adopting modern approaches are imperative to engage and mobilize younger populations effectively. Initiatives funded by entities such as the European Union serve as promising examples, highlighting the potential for collaborative efforts to drive meaningful change. Sharing the methodologies and findings of such projects within the public health community can catalyze knowledge dissemination and foster collaboration, ultimately amplifying the impact of intervention strategies worldwide. By prioritizing intervention studies for behavioral change, stakeholders can collectively address the pressing challenge of lifestyle-related diseases and pave the way for healthier, more resilient communities. The aim of this workshop is to provide an overview of multi-national EU funded projects aiming to promote healthy lifestyles in the Mediterranean region.</p></sec><sec id="s1819"><title>Key messages</title><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Innovative and more modern approaches are needed to improve the diet in the Mediterranean region.</p><p>&#x02022;&#x02002;Children and adolescents are the main targets to counteract the rise of non-communicable diseases.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>